[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "When two vectors are perpendicular, their",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dot product is zero",
            "b) Cross product is zero",
            "c) Both are zero",
            "d) Both are not necessarily zero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dot product of two perpendicular vectors is given by A.B = |a||b|cos 90, which is zero. Thus, dot product is zero and vectors are perpendicular."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "The cross product of the vectors 3i + 4j – 5k and –i + j – 2k is,",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3i – 11j + 7k",
            "b) -3i + 11j + 7k",
            "c) -3i – 11j – 7k",
            "d) -3i + 11j – 7k"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cross product of two vectors is, A X B = (a2*b3 – b2*a3)i – (a1*b3 – b1*a3)j + (a1*b2 – b1*a2)k. Using the formula, the answer can be calculated."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "Which of the following are not vector functions in Electromagnetics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gradient",
            "b) Divergence",
            "c) Curl",
            "d) There is no non- vector functions in Electromagnetics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since all the coordinates in electromagnetic are space coordinates, direction and magnitude both are important. Thus all functions are vector only."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "The work done of vectors force F and distance d, separated by angle θ can be calculated using,",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cross product",
            "b) Dot product",
            "c) Addition of two vectors",
            "d) Cannot be calculated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Force is a vector quantity, whereas distance is scalar. Work is defined as the product of force and distance, which is given by dot product."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "Find whether the vectors are parallel, (-2,1,-1) and (0,3,1)",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parallel",
            "b) Collinearly parallel",
            "c) Not parallel",
            "d) Data insufficient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Two vectors are parallel when their cross product is zero. Since their cross product is 4i + 2j – 6k (non-zero), the vectors are not parallel."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "Lorentz force is based on,",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dot product",
            "b) Cross product",
            "c) Both dot and cross product",
            "d) Independent of both"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lorentz force is given by, F = q (v x B).Thus cross product is the answer."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "Electromagnetic forces are defined by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fleming’s right hand rule",
            "b) Fleming’s left hand rule",
            "c) Faraday’s law",
            "d) Ampere law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The three left hand fingers denote electric field, magnetic field and wave propagation in free space, analogous to force, magnetic field and current respectively in any conductor."
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "Which of the Pythagorean Theorem is valid in Electromagnetics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) |dot product| + |dot product| = 1",
            "b) |cross product| – |cross product| = 1",
            "c) |dot product|2 + |cross product|2 = 1",
            "d) |dot product| + |cross product| = 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dot product is an algebraic operation that takes two equal length sequences and returns a scalar. Cross product is a binary operation that calculates area of two vectors, thus vector quantity."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A . (B . C) = scalar value",
            "b) A . (B x C) = scalar value",
            "c) A x (B . C) = scalar value",
            "d) A x (B x C) = vector value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Option |dot product|2 + |cross product|2 = 1 gives |cos|2 + |sin|2 = 1, which is the right answer."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "The distance vector is obtained in",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cartesian coordinate system",
            "b) Spherical coordinate system",
            "c) Circular coordinate system",
            "d) Space coordinate system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Vector formed by connecting two points in space is distance vector. Thus, it is obtained in space coordinate system."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "The divergence of distance vector is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The distance vector of any coordinates is generally, r = xi + yj + zk. The divergence of r is 1 + 1 + 1 = 3."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "Find a vector normal to a plane consisting of points p1(0,1,0), p2(1,0,1) and p3(0,0,1)",
        "Options": [
            "a) –j – k",
            "b) –i – j",
            "c) –i – k",
            "d) –i – j – k"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Distance vector from p1 and p2 is a = i – j + k. Distance vector from p1 and p3 is b = –j + k. The vector normal to these points is a X b = -j – k."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "The unit vector to the points p1(0,1,0), p2(1,0,1), p3(0,0,1) is",
        "Options": [
            "a) (-j – k)/1.414",
            "b) (-i – k)/1.414",
            "c) (-i – j)/1.414",
            "d) (-i – j – k)/1.414"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cross product of p1, p2, p3 is a X b = -j – k and its magnitude is 1.414. The unit normal vector is given by, (-j –\n k)/1.414."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "The polar form of Cartesian coordinates is",
        "Options": [
            "a) Circular coordinates",
            "b) Spherical coordinates",
            "c) Cartesian coordinates",
            "d) Space coordinates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The radius in the polar coordinates is the Pythagorean triplet-(r,x,y).Thus it is the circular coordinates."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "The work-electric field relation is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volume integral",
            "b) Surface integral",
            "c) Line integral",
            "d) Relation impossible"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The work done is given by, W = -Q ∫E dl. Thus it is line integral."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "The distance vector can be used to compute which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dot product",
            "b) Cross product",
            "c) Unit normal vector",
            "d) Area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The distance vector is the distance between two points on space, thus the unit normal vector is computed using the distance vector."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "Find the projection of A on B. Given A = 10j + 3k and B = 4j + 5k.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6",
            "b) 6.25",
            "c) 6.5",
            "d) 6.75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Position or distance of a vector is dependent on the field strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "The del operator is called as",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gradient",
            "b) Curl",
            "c) Divergence",
            "d) Vector differential operator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Del operator is used to replace the differential terms, thus called vector differential operator in electromagnetics."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "The relation between vector potential and field strength is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gradient",
            "b) Divergence",
            "c) Curl",
            "d) Del operator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The vector potential and field is given by, E = -Del (V)."
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "The Laplacian operator is actually",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grad(Div V)",
            "b) Div(Grad V)",
            "c) Curl(Div V)",
            "d) Div(Curl V)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Laplacian operator is the divergence of gradient of a vector, which is also called del2V operator."
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "Identify the correct vector identity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) i . i = j . j = k . k = 0",
            "b) i X j = j X k = k X i = 1",
            "c) Div (u X v) = v . Curl(u) – u . Curl(v)",
            "d) i . j = j . k = k . i = 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The curl of a vector is the circular flow of flux. The divergence of circular flow is considered to be zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "A vector is said to be solenoidal when its",
        "Options": [
            "a) Divergence is zero",
            "b) Divergence is unity",
            "c) Curl is zero",
            "d) Curl is unity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The differential flow of flux in a vector is a vector. The curl of this quantity will be zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "The magnetic field intensity is said to be",
        "Options": [
            "a) Divergent",
            "b) Curl free",
            "c) Solenoidal",
            "d) Rotational"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: By standard proof, Div (u X v) = v . Curl(u) – u . Curl (v)."
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "A field has zero divergence and it has curls. The field is said to be",
        "Options": [
            "a) Divergent, rotational",
            "b) Solenoidal, rotational",
            "c) Solenoidal, irrotational",
            "d) Divergent, irrotational"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the divergence of a vector is zero, it is said to be solenoidal /divergent-free."
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "When a vector is irrotational, which condition holds good?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stoke’s theorem gives non-zero value",
            "b) Stoke’s theorem gives zero value",
            "c) Divergence theorem is invalid",
            "d) Divergence theorem is valid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  By Maxwell’s equation, the magnetic field intensity is solenoidal due to the absence of magnetic monopoles."
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "The Cartesian system is also called as",
        "Options": [
            "a) Circular coordinate system",
            "b) Rectangular coordinate system",
            "c) Spherical coordinate system",
            "d) Space coordinate system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The other name for Cartesian is rectangular system, which is given by (x,y,z)."
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "The volume of a parallelepiped in Cartesian is",
        "Options": [
            "a) dV = dx dy dz",
            "b) dV = dx dy",
            "c) dV = dy dz",
            "d) dV = dx dz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The volume of a parallelepiped is given by product of differential length, breadth and height."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "A charge is placed in a square container. The position of the charge with respect to the origin can be found by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spherical system",
            "b) Circular system",
            "c) Cartesian system",
            "d) Space coordinate system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Since the container possesses dimensions of a square (length, breadth and height), it can be found by Cartesian system."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "The angular separation between the vectors A = 4i + 3j + 5k and B = i – 2j + 2k is (in degrees)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 65.8",
            "b) 66.8",
            "c) 67.8",
            "d) 68.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The range of Cartesian system is one to infinity. Thus the minimum scalar value of the system is unity."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "Transform the vector A = 3i – 2j – 4k at P(2,3,3) to cylindrical coordinates",
        "Options": [
            "a) -3.6j – 4k",
            "b) -3.6j + 4k",
            "c) 3.6j – 4k",
            "d) 3.6j + 4k"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The dot product the vector is 8. Angle of separation is cos θ = 8/ (7.07 X 3) = 0.377 and θ = cos-1(0.377) = 67.8."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "The spherical equivalent of the vector B = yi + (x + z)j located at (-2,6,3) is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) (7,64.62,71.57)",
            "b) (7,-64.62,-71.57)",
            "c) (7,-64.62,71.57)",
            "d) (7,64.62,-71.57)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All the coordinate systems are inter-convertible and all the vector operations are applicable to it."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "Which of the following criteria is used to choose a coordinate system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Distance",
            "b) Intensity",
            "c) Magnitude",
            "d) Geometry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Convert the Cartesian form to cylindrical form by formula and substitute the points to get -3.6j – 4k."
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "Vector transformation followed by coordinate point substitution and vice-versa, both given the same result. Choose the best answer.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Possible, when the vector is constant",
            "b) Possible, when the vector is variable",
            "c) Possible in all cases",
            "d) Not possible"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Substitute the points in the vector and convert the Cartesian to cylindrical form to get radius as 7, plane angle1 as 64.62 and plane angle2 as -71.57."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "The cylindrical coordinate system is also referred to as",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cartesian system",
            "b) Circular system",
            "c) Spherical system",
            "d) Space system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cylindrical coordinates(r,φ,z) is also called as circular system and is used for systems with circular dimensions."
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "Transform the vector B=yi+(x+z)j located at point (-2,6,3) into cylindrical coordinates.",
        "Options": [
            "a) (6.325,-71.57,3)",
            "b) (6.325,71.57,3)",
            "c) (6.325,73.57,3)",
            "d) (6.325,-73.57,3)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ρ = √(x2+y2) = √40 = 6.325\n Φ = tan-1(y/x) = tan-1(-6/2) = -71.57\nz = 3."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "Cylindrical systems have the following scalar values respectively",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1, ρ ,1",
            "b) 1, 1, 1",
            "c) 0,1,0",
            "d) 1,0,0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The range of radius is one to unity, that of plane angle is one to 360 degree and that of z plane is one to infinity. Thus the minimum scalar factor has to be 1, ρ , 1."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "A charge located at point p (5,30⁰,2) is said to be in which coordinate system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cartesian system",
            "b) Cylindrical system",
            "c) Spherical system",
            "d) Space system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cylindrical system is of the form (ρ, φ, z), which relates the point given in the question."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "The pressure inside a piston cylinder is a variable of",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radius",
            "b) Plane angle",
            "c) Z plane distance",
            "d) Constant, not a variable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cylindrical systems are employed in circular waveguides, whereas Cartesian systems are employed in rectangular waveguides."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "Charges filled inside a cylindrical will possess flux in which direction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Upwards",
            "b) Downwards",
            "c) Laterally outwards",
            "d) Inwards"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pressure varies up and down in a cylinder due to suction. Thus it is dependent on the z plane distance of the cylinder."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "Rectangular waveguides dominate the circular waveguides. Find the reason.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low cut-off frequency",
            "b) Easy to design",
            "c) More wave propagation",
            "d) The statement is false"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  c\nExplanation: The flux due to the charges will act outside the cylinder. Since the cylinder possesses curved surfaces, it will flow laterally outwards."
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "Transform the spherical system B = (10/r)i + (10cos θ)j + k into cylindrical form at (5, π/2, -2)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.467i + j + 1.167k",
            "b) 2.467i – j + 1.167k",
            "c) 2.467i – j – 1.167k",
            "d) 2.467i + j – 1.167k"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Due to linear design, the desired dimensions can be easily constructed using rectangular waveguides than circular ones."
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "Convert the given rectangular coordinates A(2,3,1) into corresponding cylindrical coordinates",
        "Options": [
            "a) (3.21,56.31,1)",
            "b) (3.21,57.31,0)",
            "c) (3.61,57.31,0)",
            "d) (3.61,56.31,1)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The equivalent cylindrical form is given by,\nB = (10sin θ/r + rcos2θ)i + j + (10cos θ/r –r sin θ cos θ)k\nAt (5, π/2, -2), r = √(52+-22) = √29\nsin θ = 5/√29 and cos θ = -2/√29\nThus, B = 2.467i + j + 1.167k."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "Convert the point (3,4,5) from Cartesian to spherical coordinates",
        "Options": [
            "a) (7.07,45⁰,53⁰)",
            "b) (0.707,45⁰,53⁰)",
            "c) (7.07,54⁰,63⁰)",
            "d) (0.707,54⁰,63⁰)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: r = √(x2+y2+z2) = √50 = 7.07\nΘ = cos-1(z/r) = cos-1(5/5√2) = 45⁰\nΦ = tan-1(y/x) = tan-1(4/3) = 53⁰."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "Example of spherical system in the following is",
        "Options": [
            "a) Charge in space",
            "b) Charge in box",
            "c) Charge in dielectric",
            "d) Uncharged system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From a point charge +Q, the electric field spreads in all 360 degrees. The calculation of electric field in this case will be spherical system. Thus it is charge in the space."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "Choose which of following condition is not required for a waveguide to exist.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The dimensions should be in accordance with desired frequency",
            "b) Cut-off frequency should be minimum 6GHz",
            "c) The shape should be spherical",
            "d) No specific condition is required for waveguide design"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There is no waveguide designed spherically to avoid absorption, rather than propagation."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "Find the spherical coordinates of A(2,3,-1)",
        "Options": [
            "a) (3.74, 105.5⁰, 56.13⁰)",
            "b) (3.74, 105.5⁰, 56.31⁰)",
            "c) (3.74, 106.5⁰, 56.13⁰)",
            "d) (3.74, 106.5⁰, 56.31⁰)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A waveguide need not be spherical, it has to be rectangular or circular, as it violates the propagation of the wave."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "Find the Cartesian coordinates of B(4,25⁰,120⁰)",
        "Options": [
            "a) (0.845, 1.462, 3.625)",
            "b) (-0.845, 1.462, 3.625)",
            "c) (-8.45, 2.462, 6.325)",
            "d) (8.45, 2.462, 6.325)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: r = √(x2+y2+z2) = √14 = 3.74\nΘ = cos-1(z/r) = cos-1(-1/3.74) = 105.5⁰\nΦ = tan-1(y/x) = tan-1(3/2) = 56.31⁰."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "Given B= (10/r)i+( rcos θ) j+k in spherical coordinates. Find Cartesian points at (-3,4,0)",
        "Options": [
            "a) -2i + j",
            "b) 2i + k",
            "c) i + 2j",
            "d) –i – 2k"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: x = r sin θ cos φ = 4 sin25⁰ cos 120⁰ = -0.845\ny = r sin θ sin φ = 4 sin 25⁰ sin 120⁰ = 1.462\nz = r cos θ = 4 cos 25⁰ = 3.625."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "The scalar factor of spherical coordinates is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1, r, r sin θ",
            "b) 1, r, r",
            "c) r, r, 1",
            "d) r, 1, r"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: On double integrating the differential volume, the area can be computed for a sphere."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "Transform the vector (4,-2,-4) at (1,2,3) into spherical coordinates.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.197i – 2.393j + 4.472k",
            "b) -3.197i + 2.393j – 4.472k",
            "c) 3.197i + 2.393j + 4.472k",
            "d) -3.197i – 2.393j – 4.472k"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: r = √(x2+y2+z2) = √25 = 5\nΘ = cos-1(z/r) = 1\nΦ = tan-1(y/x) = tan-1(-4/3)\nThus, B = -2i + j."
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "The mathematical perception of the gradient is said to be",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tangent",
            "b) Chord",
            "c) Slope",
            "d) Arc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gradient of any scalar function may be defined as a vector. The vector’s magnitude and direction are those of the maximum space rate of change of φ."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "Divergence of gradient of a vector function is equivalent to",
        "Options": [
            "a) Laplacian operation",
            "b) Curl operation",
            "c) Double gradient operation",
            "d) Null vector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The gradient is the rate of change of space of flux in electromagnetics. This is analogous to the slope in mathematics."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "The gradient of xi + yj + zk is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Div (Grad V) = (Del)2V, which is the Laplacian operation. A function is said to be harmonic in nature, when its Laplacian tends to zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "Find the gradient of t = x2y+ ez at the point p(1,5,-2)",
        "Options": [
            "a) i + 10j + 0.135k",
            "b) 10i + j + 0.135k",
            "c) i + 0.135j + 10k",
            "d) 10i + 0.135j + k"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Grad (xi + yj + zk) = 1 + 1 + 1 = 3. In other words, the gradient of any position vector is 3."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "Curl of gradient of a vector is",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unity",
            "b) Zero",
            "c) Null vector",
            "d) Depends on the constants of the vector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Grad(t) = 2xy i + x2 j + ez k. On substituting p(1,5,-2), we get 10i + j + 0.135k."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "Find the gradient of the function given by, x2 + y2 + z2 at (1,1,1)",
        "Options": [
            "a) i + j + k",
            "b) 2i + 2j + 2k",
            "c) 2xi + 2yj + 2zk",
            "d) 4xi + 2yj + 4zk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gradient of any function leads to a vector. Similarly curl of that vector gives another vector, which is always zero for all constants of the vector. A zero value in vector is always termed as null vector(not simply a zero)."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "The gradient can be replaced by which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maxwell equation",
            "b) Volume integral",
            "c) Differential equation",
            "d) Surface integral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Grad(x2+y2+z2) = 2xi + 2yj + 2zk. Put x=1, y=1, z=1, the gradient will be 2i + 2j + 2k."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "Find the gradient of the function sin x + cos y.",
        "Options": [
            "a) cos x i – sin y j",
            "b) cos x i + sin y j",
            "c) sin x i – cos y j",
            "d) sin x i + cos y j"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Since gradient is the maximum space rate of change of flux, it can be replaced by differential equations."
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "Compute the divergence of the vector xi + yj + zk.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Divergence can be computed only for a vector. Since it is the measure of outward flow of flux from a small closed surface as the volume shrinks to zero, the result will be directionless (scalar)."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "Find the divergence of the vector yi + zj + xk.",
        "Options": [
            "a) -1",
            "b) 0",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Consider the illustration of Pascal’s law, wherein a ball is pricked with holes all over its body. After water is filled in it and pressure is applied on it, the water flows out the holes uniformly. This is analogous to the flux flowing outside a closed surface as the volume reduces."
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Find the divergence of the vector F= xe-x i + y j – xz k",
        "Options": [
            "a) (1 – x)(1 + e-x)",
            "b) (x – 1)(1 + e-x)",
            "c) (1 – x)(1 – e)",
            "d) (x – 1)(1 – e)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The vector given is a position vector. The divergence of any position vector is always 3."
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "Determine the divergence of F = 30 i + 2xy j + 5xz2 k at (1,1,-0.2) and state the nature of the field.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1, solenoidal",
            "b) 0, solenoidal",
            "c) 1, divergent",
            "d) 0, divergent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Div (yi + zj + xk) = Dx(y) + Dy(z) + Dz(x), which is zero. Here D refers to partial differentiation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "Find whether the vector is solenoidal, E = yz i + xz j + xy k",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yes, solenoidal",
            "b) No, non-solenoidal",
            "c) Solenoidal with negative divergence",
            "d) Variable divergence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Div (D) = Dx(e-xsin y) + Dy(-e-xcos y ) = -e-xsin y + e-xsin y = 0."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "Find the divergence of the field, P = x2yz i + xz k",
        "Options": [
            "a) xyz + 2x",
            "b) 2xyz + x",
            "c) xyz + 2z",
            "d) 2xyz + z"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Div(F) = Dx(xe-x) + Dy(y)+Dz(-xz) = -xe-x + e-x + 1 – x =\ne-x(1 – x) + (1 – x) = (1 – x)(1 + e-x)."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "Identify the nature of the field, if the divergence is zero and curl is also zero.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solenoidal, irrotational",
            "b) Divergent, rotational",
            "c) Solenoidal, irrotational",
            "d) Divergent, rotational"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Div(F) = Dx(30) + Dy(2xy) + Dz(5xz2) = 0 + 2x + 10xz = 2x + 10xz\nDivergence at (1,1,-0.2) will give zero. As the divergence is zero, field is solenoidal.\nAlternate/Shortcut: Without calculation, we can easily choose option “0, solenoidal”, as by theory when the divergence is zero, the vector is solenoidal. “0, solenoidal” is the only one which is satisfying this condition. "
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "The curl of curl of a vector is given by,",
        "Options": [
            "a) Div(Grad V) – (Del)2V",
            "b) Grad(Div V) – (Del)2V",
            "c) (Del)2V – Div(Grad V)",
            "d) (Del)2V – Grad(Div V)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Curl is defined as the circulation of a vector per unit area. It is the cross product of the del operator and any vector field. Circulation implies the angular at every point of the vector field. It is obtained by multiplying the component of the vector parallel to the specified closed path at each point along it, by the differential path length and summing the results."
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "Which of the following theorem use the curl operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Green’s theorem",
            "b) Gauss Divergence theorem",
            "c) Stoke’s theorem",
            "d) Maxwell equation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Curl (Curl V) = Grad (Div V) – (Del)2V is a standard result of the curl operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "The curl of a curl of a vector gives a",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scalar",
            "b) Vector",
            "c) Zero value",
            "d) Non zero value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Stoke’s theorem is given by ∫ A.dl = ∫Curl(A).ds, which uses the curl operation. There can be confusion with Maxwell equation also, but it uses curl in electromagnetics specifically, whereas the Stoke’s theorem uses it in a generalised manner. Thus the best option is Stoke’s theorem."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "Find the curl of A = (y cos ax)i + (y + ex)k",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2i – ex j – cos ax k",
            "b) i – ex j – cos ax k",
            "c) 2i – ex  j + cos ax k",
            "d) i – ex j + cos ax k"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Curl is always defined for vectors only. The curl of a vector is a vector only. The curl of the resultant vector is also a vector only."
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "Find the curl of the vector A = yz i + 4xy j + y k",
        "Options": [
            "a) xi + j + (4y – z)k",
            "b) xi + yj + (z – 4y)k",
            "c) i + j + (4y – z)k",
            "d) i + yj + (4y – z)k"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Curl F = -5z2 j + 2y k. At (1,1,-0.2), Curl F = -0.2 j + 2 k. |Curl F| = √(-0.22+22) = √4.04."
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "Curl cannot be employed in which one of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Directional coupler",
            "b) Magic Tee",
            "c) Isolator and Terminator",
            "d) Waveguides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Curl E = i(Dy(xy) – Dz(xz)) – j (Dx(xy) – Dz(yz)) + k(Dx(xz) – Dy(yz)) =\ni(x – x) – j(y – y) + k(z – z) = 0\nSince the curl is zero, the vector is irrotational or curl-free."
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "Which of the following Maxwell equations use curl operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maxwell 1st  and 2nd equation",
            "b) Maxwell 3rd and 4th equation",
            "c) All the four equations",
            "d) None of the equations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Curl A = i(Dy(y + ex)) – j (Dx(y + ex) – Dz(y cos ax)) + k(-Dy(y cos ax))\n= 1.i – j(ex) – k cos ax = i – ex j – cos ax k."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "An electric field is given as E = 6y2z i + 12xyz j + 6xy2 k. An incremental path is given by dl = -3 i + 5 j – 2 k mm. The work done in moving a 2mC charge along the path if the location of the path is at p(0,2,5) is (in Joule)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.64",
            "b) 0.72",
            "c) 0.78",
            "d) 0.80"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: W = -Q E.dl\nW = -2 X 10-3 X (6y2z i + 12xyz j + 6xy2 k) . (-3 i + 5 j -2 k)\nAt p(0,2,5), W = -2(-18.22.5) X 10-3 = 0.72 J."
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "If V = 2x2y – 5z, find its electric field at point (-4,3,6)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 47.905",
            "b) 57.905",
            "c) 67.905",
            "d) 77.905"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vab = -∫ E.dl is the relation between potential and field. It is clear that it is given by line integral."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "Find the potential between two points p(1,-1,0) and q(2,1,3) with E = 40xy i + 20x2 j + 2 k",
        "Options": [
            "a) 104",
            "b) 105",
            "c) 106",
            "d) 107"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: E = -Grad (V) = -4xy i – 2×2 j + 5k\nAt (-4,3,6), E = 48 i – 32 j + 5 k, |E| = √3353 = 57.905 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "Find the potential between a(-7,2,1) and b(4,1,2). Given E = (-6y/x2 )i + ( 6/x) j + 5 k.",
        "Options": [
            "a) -8.014",
            "b) -8.114",
            "c) -8.214",
            "d) -8.314"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: V = -∫ E.dl = -∫ (40xy dx + 20x2 dy + 2 dz) , from q to p.\nOn integrating, we get 106 volts."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Options": [
            "6. The potential of a uniformly charged line with density λ is given by,",
            "     λ/(2πε) ln(b/a). State True/False.",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: V = -∫ E.dl = -∫ (-6y/x2 )dx + ( 6/x)dy + 5 dz, from b to a.\nOn integrating, we get -8.214 volts."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "A field in which a test charge around any closed surface in static path is zero is called",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solenoidal",
            "b) Rotational",
            "c) Irrotational",
            "d) Conservative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The electric field intensity is given by, E = λ/(2πεr)\nVab = -∫ E.dr = -∫ λ/(2πεr). On integrating from b to a, we get λ/(2πε) ln(b/a)."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "The potential in a lamellar field is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 0",
            "c) -1",
            "d) ∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Work done in moving a charge in a closed path is zero. It is expressed as, ∫ E.dl = 0. The field having this property is called conservative or lamellar field."
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "Line integral is used to calculate",
        "Options": [
            "a) Force",
            "b) Area",
            "c) Volume",
            "d) Length"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Work done in a lamellar field is zero. ∫ E.dl = 0,thus ∑V = 0. The potential will be zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "The energy stored in the inductor 100mH with a current of 2A is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.2",
            "b) 0.4",
            "c) 0.6",
            "d) 0.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Length is a linear quantity, whereas area is two dimensional and volume is three dimensional. Thus single or line integral can be used to find length in general."
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "Surface integral is used to compute",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surface",
            "b) Area",
            "c) Volume",
            "d) density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gauss law states that the electric flux passing through any closed surface is equal to the total charge enclosed by the surface. Thus the charge is defined as a surface integral."
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "Evaluate Gauss law for D = 5r2/4 i in spherical coordinates with r = 4m and θ = π/2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 600",
            "b) 599.8",
            "c) 588.9",
            "d) 577.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Surface integral is used to compute area, which is the product of two quantities length and breadth. Thus it is two dimensional integral."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "Compute the Gauss law for D= 10ρ3/4 i, in cylindrical coordinates with ρ= 4m, z=0 and z=5.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6100 π",
            "b) 6200 π",
            "c) 6300 π",
            "d) 6400 π"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gauss law, Q = ∫∫D.ds\nBy considering area of a sphere, ds = r2sin θ dθ dφ.\nOn integrating, we get Q = 4πr2D and D = εE, where E = F/Q.\nThus, we get Coulomb’s law F = Q1 x Q2/4∏εR2."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "Compute divergence theorem for D= 5r2/4 i in spherical coordinates between r=1 and r=2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 80π",
            "b) 5π",
            "c) 75π",
            "d) 85π"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ∫∫ ( 5r2/4) . (r2 sin θ dθ dφ), which is the integral to be evaluated.\nPut r = 4m and substitute θ = 0→ π/4 and φ = 0→ 2π, the integral evaluates to 588.9."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "Find the value of divergence theorem for A = xy2 i + y3 j + y2z k for a cuboid given by 0<x<1, 0<y<1 and 0<z<1.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 4/3",
            "c) 5/3",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: ∫∫ D.ds = ∫∫ (10ρ3/4).(ρ dφ dz), which is the integral to be evaluated. Put ρ = 4m, z = 0→5 and φ = 0→2π, the integral evaluates to 6400π."
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "The ultimate result of the divergence theorem evaluates which one of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Field intensity",
            "b) Field density",
            "c) Potential",
            "d) Charge and flux"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  ∫∫ ( 5r2/4) . (r2 sin θ dθ dφ), which is the integral to be evaluated. Since it is double integral, we need to keep only two variables and one constant compulsorily. Evaluate it as two integrals keeping r = 1 for the first integral and r = 2 for the second integral, with φ = 0→2π and θ = 0→ π. The first integral value is 80π, whereas second integral gives -5π. On summing both integrals, we get 75π. "
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "Find the value of divergence theorem for the field D = 2xy i + x2 j for the rectangular parallelepiped given by x = 0 and 1, y = 0 and 2, z = 0 and 3.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 12",
            "c) 14",
            "d) 16"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A cuboid has six faces. ∫∫A.ds = ∫∫Ax=0 dy dz + ∫∫Ax=1 dy dz + ∫∫Ay=0 dx dz + ∫∫Ay=1 dx dz + ∫∫Az=0 dy dx + ∫∫Az=1 dy dx. Substituting A and integrating we get (1/3) + 1 + (1/3) = 5/3."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "If D = 2xy i + 3yz j + 4xz k, how much flux passes through x = 3 plane for which -1<y<2 and 0<z<4?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12",
            "b) 24",
            "c) 36",
            "d) 48"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  Gauss law states that the electric flux passing through any closed surface is equal to the total charge enclosed by the surface. Thus, it is given by, ψ = ∫∫ D.ds= Q, where the divergence theorem computes the charge and flux, which are both the same."
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "1.\tThe divergence theorem converts",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLine to surface integral",
            "b)\tSurface to volume integral",
            "c)\tVolume to line integral",
            "d)\tSurface to line integral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The divergence theorem is given by, ∫∫ D.ds = ∫∫∫ Div (D) dv. It is clear that it converts surface (double) integral to volume(triple) integral."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the charged enclosed by a sphere of charge density ρ and radius a.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tρ (4πa2)",
            "b)\tρ(4πa3/3)",
            "c)\tρ(2πa2)",
            "d)\tρ(2πa3/3)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The triple integral, as the name suggests integrates the function/quantity three times. This gives volume which is the product of three independent quantities."
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "5.\tEvaluate Gauss law for D = 5r2/4 i in spherical coordinates with r = 4m and θ = π/2 as volume integral.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t600",
            "b)\t588.9",
            "c)\t577.8",
            "d)\t599.7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Volume integral integrates the independent quantities by three times. Thus it is said to be three dimensional integral or triple integral."
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "6.\tCompute divergence theorem for D = 5r2/4 i in spherical coordinates between r = 1 and r = 2 in volume integral.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t80 π",
            "b)\t5 π",
            "c)\t75 π",
            "d)\t85 π"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The charge enclosed by the sphere is Q = ∫∫∫ ρ dv.\nWhere, dv = r2 sin θ dr dθ dφ and on integrating with r = 0->a, φ = 0->2π and θ = 0->π, we get Q = ρ(4πa3/3)."
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "7.\tCompute the Gauss law for D = 10ρ3/4 i, in cylindrical coordinates with ρ = 4m, z = 0 and z = 5, hence find charge using volume integral.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t6100 π",
            "b)\t6200 π",
            "c)\t6300 π",
            "d)\t6400 π"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ∫∫ D.ds = ∫∫∫ Div (D) dv, where RHS needs to be computed.\nThe divergence of D given is, Div(D) = 5r and dv = r2 sin θ dr dθ dφ. On integrating, r = 0->4, φ = 0->2π and θ = 0->π/4, we get Q = 588.9."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "8.\tUsing volume integral, which quantity can be calculated?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tarea of cube",
            "b)\tarea of cuboid",
            "c)\tvolume of cube",
            "d)\tdistance of vector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: D.ds = ∫∫∫ Div (D) dv, where RHS needs to be computed.\nThe divergence of D given is, Div(D) = 5r and dv = r2 sin θ dr dθ dφ. On integrating, r = 1->2, φ = 0->2π and θ = 0->π, we get Q = 75 π."
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "9.\tCompute the charge enclosed by a cube of 2m each edge centered at the origin and with the edges parallel to the axes. Given D = 10y3/3 j.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t20",
            "b)\t70/3",
            "c)\t80/3",
            "d)\t30"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Q = D.ds = ∫∫∫ Div (D) dv, where RHS needs to be computed.\nThe divergence of D given is, Div(D) = 10 ρ2 and dv = ρ dρ dφ dz. On integrating, ρ = 0->4, φ = 0->2π and z = 0->5, we get Q = 6400 π."
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "10.\t Find the value of divergence theorem for the field D = 2xy i + x2 j for the rectangular parallelepiped given by x = 0 and 1, y = 0 and 2, z = 0 and 3.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t10",
            "b)\t12",
            "c)\t14",
            "d)\t16"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The volume integral gives the volume of a vector in a region. Thus volume of a cube can be computed."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Options": [
            "1. The point form of Gauss law is given by, Div(V) = ρv",
            " State True/False.",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The integral form of Gauss law is ∫∫∫ ρv dv = V. Thus differential or point form will be Div(V) = ρv."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "2.\tIf a function is said to be harmonic, then",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCurl(Grad V) = 0",
            "b)\tDiv(Curl V) = 0",
            "c)\tDiv(Grad V) = 0",
            "d)\tGrad(Curl V) = 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Though option Curl(Grad V) = 0 & Div(Curl V) = 0 are also correct, for harmonic fields, the Laplacian of electric potential is zero. Now, Laplacian refers to Div(Grad V), which is zero for harmonic fields."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "4.\tGiven the potential V = 25 sin θ, in free space, determine whether V satisfies Laplace’s equation.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tYes",
            "b)\tNo",
            "c)\tData sufficient",
            "d)\tPotential is not defined"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Poisson equation is a general case for Laplace equation. If volume charge density exists for a field, then (Del)2V= -ρv/ε, which is called Poisson equation."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "5.\tIf a potential V is 2V at x = 1mm and is zero at x=0 and volume charge density is -106εo, constant throughout the free space region between x = 0 and x = 1mm. Calculate V at x = 0.5mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.875",
            "b)\t0.675",
            "c)\t0.475",
            "d)\t0.275"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: (Del)2V = 0\n(Del)2V = (Del)2(25 sin θ), which is not equal to zero. Thus the field does not satisfy Laplace equation."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "9.\tThe Laplacian operator cannot be used in which one the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTwo dimensional heat equation",
            "b)\tTwo dimensional wave equation",
            "c)\tPoisson equation",
            "d)\tMaxwell equation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Del2(V) = -ρv/εo= +106\nOn integrating twice with respect to x, V = 106. (x2/2) + C1x + C2.\nSubstitute the boundary conditions, x = 0, V = 0 and x = 1mm, V = 2V in V,\nC1 = 1500 and C2 = 0. At x = 0.5mm, we get, V = 0.875V."
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "10.\t When a potential satisfies Laplace equation, then it is said to be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSolenoidal",
            "b)\tDivergent",
            "c)\tLamellar",
            "d)\tHarmonic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: (Del) V = 2x – 2y + 2z\n(Del)2 V = 2 – 2 + 2= 2, which is non zero value. Thus it doesn’t satisfy Laplace equation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "1.\tFind the value of Stoke’s theorem for y i + z j + x k.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\ti + j",
            "b)\tj + k",
            "c)\ti + j + k",
            "d)\t–i – j – k"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The curl of y i + z j + x k is i(0-1) – j(1-0) + k(0-1) =\n-i –j –k. Since the curl is zero, the value of Stoke’s theorem is zero. The function is said to be irrotational."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "2.\tThe Stoke’s theorem uses which of the following operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDivergence",
            "b)\tGradient",
            "c)\tCurl",
            "d)\tLaplacian"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ∫A.dl = ∫∫ Curl (A).ds is the expression for Stoke’s theorem. It is clear that the theorem uses curl operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "3.\tWhich of the following theorem convert line integral to surface integral?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGauss divergence and Stoke’s theorem",
            "b)\tStoke’s theorem only",
            "c)\tGreen’ s theorem only",
            "d)\tStoke’s and Green’s theorem"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Stoke’s theorem is given by ∫A.dl = ∫∫ Curl (A).ds. Green’s theorem is given by, ∫ F dx + G dy = ∫∫ (dG/dx – dF/dy) dx dy. It is clear that both the theorems convert line to surface integral."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the value of Stoke’s theorem for A = x i + y j + z k. The state of the function will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSolenoidal",
            "b)\tDivergent",
            "c)\tRotational",
            "d)\tCurl free"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since curl is required, we need not bother about divergence property. The curl of the function will be i(0-0) – j(0-0) + k(0-0) = 0. The curl is zero, thus the function is said to be irrotational or curl free."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "5.\tThe Stoke’s theorem can be used to find which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tArea enclosed by a function in the given region",
            "b)\tVolume enclosed by a function in the given region",
            "c)\tLinear distance",
            "d)\tCurl of the function"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It states that the line integral of a function gives the surface area of the function enclosed by the given region. This is computed using the double integral of the curl of the function."
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "6.\tThe energy stored in an inductor 2H and current 4A is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t4",
            "b)\t8",
            "c)\t12",
            "d)\t16"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: From Stoke’s theorem, we can calculate energy stored in an inductor as 0.5Li2. E = 0.5 X 2 X 42 = 16 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "7.\tThe voltage of a capacitor 12F with a rating of 2J energy is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.57",
            "b)\t5.7",
            "c)\t57",
            "d)\t570"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We can compute the energy stored in a capacitor from Stoke’s theorem as 0.5Cv2. Thus given energy is 0.5 X 12 X v2. We get v = 0.57 volts."
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the power, given energy E = 2J and current density J = x2 varies from x = 0 and x = 1.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1/3",
            "b)\t2/3",
            "c)\t1",
            "d)\t4/3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From Stoke’s theorem, we can calculate P = E X I = ∫ E. J ds\n= 2∫ x2 dx as x = 0->1. We get P = 2/3 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "9.\tThe conductivity of a material with current density 1 unit and electric field 200 μV is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2000",
            "b)\t3000",
            "c)\t4000",
            "d)\t5000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The current density is given by, J = σE. To find conductivity, σ = J/E = 1/200 X 10-6 = 5000."
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "10.\t The resistivity of a material with resistance 200 ohm, length 10m and area twice that of the length is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t200",
            "b)\t300",
            "c)\t400",
            "d)\t500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Resistance calculated from Ohm’s law and Stoke’s theorem will be R = ρL/A. To get resistivity, ρ = RA/L = 200 X 20/10 = 400.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "1.\tMathematically, the functions in Green’s theorem will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tContinuous derivatives",
            "b)\tDiscrete derivatives",
            "c)\tContinuous partial derivatives",
            "d)\tDiscrete partial derivatives"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Green’s theorem states that if L and M are functions of (x,y) in an open region containing D and having continuous partial derivatives then,\n∫ (F dx + G dy) = ∫∫(dG/dx – dF/dy)dx dy, with path taken anticlockwise."
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "2.\tFind the value of Green’s theorem for F = x2 and G = y2 is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ∫∫(dG/dx – dF/dy)dx dy = ∫∫(0 – 0)dx dy = 0. The value of Green’s theorem gives zero for the functions given."
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "3.\tWhich of the following is not an application of Green’s theorem?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSolving two dimensional flow integrals",
            "b)\tArea surveying",
            "c)\tVolume of plane figures",
            "d)\tCentroid of plane figures"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In physics, Green’s theorem is used to find the two dimensional flow integrals. In plane geometry, it is used to find the area and centroid of plane figures."
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "4.\tThe path traversal in calculating the Green’s theorem is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tClockwise",
            "b)\tAnticlockwise",
            "c)\tInwards",
            "d)\tOutwards"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Green’s theorem calculates the area traversed by the functions in the region in the anticlockwise direction. This converts the line integral to surface integral."
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "5.\tCalculate the Green’s value for the functions F = y2 and G = x2 for the region x = 1 and y = 2 from origin.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t2",
            "c)\t-2",
            "d)\t1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ∫∫(dG/dx – dF/dy)dx dy = ∫∫(2x – 2y)dx dy. On integrating for x = 0->1 and y = 0->2, we get Green’s value as -2."
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "6.\tIf two functions A and B are discrete, their Green’s value for a region of circle of radius a in the positive quadrant is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t∞",
            "b)\t-∞",
            "c)\t0",
            "d)\tDoes not exist"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Green’s theorem is valid only for continuous functions. Since the given functions are discrete, the theorem is invalid or does not exist."
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "7.\tApplications of Green’s theorem are meant to be in",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tOne dimensional",
            "b)\tTwo dimensional",
            "c)\t Three dimensional",
            "d)\tFour dimensional"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Since Green’s theorem converts line integral to surface integral, we get the value as two dimensional. In other words the functions are variable with respect to x,y, which is two dimensional."
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "8.\tThe Green’s theorem can be related to which of the following theorems mathematically?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGauss divergence theorem",
            "b)\tStoke’s theorem",
            "c)\tEuler’s theorem",
            "d)\tLeibnitz’s theorem"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Green’s theorem is a special case of the Kelvin- Stokes theorem, when applied to a region in the x-y plane. It is a widely used theorem in mathematics and physics."
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "10.\t Find the area of a right angled triangle with sides of 90 degree unit and the functions described by L = cos y and M = sin x.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t45",
            "c)\t90",
            "d)\t180"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Shoelace theorem is used to find the area of polygon using cross multiples. This can be verified by dividing the polygon into triangles. It is a special case of Green’s theorem."
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "1.\tGauss theorem uses which of the following operations?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGradient",
            "b)\tCurl",
            "c)\tDivergence",
            "d)\tLaplacian"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Gauss divergence theorem uses divergence operator to convert surface to volume integral. It is used to calculate the volume of the function enclosing the region given."
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "2.\tEvaluate the surface integral ∫∫ (3x i + 2y j). dS, where S is the sphere given by x2 + y2 + z2 = 9.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t120π",
            "b)\t180π",
            "c)\t240π",
            "d)\t300π"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: We could parameterise surface and find surface integral, but it is wise to use divergence theorem to get faster results. The divergence theorem is given by ∫∫ F.dS = ∫∫∫ Div (F).dV\nDiv (3x i + 2y j) = 3 + 2 = 5. Now the volume integral will be ∫∫∫ 5.dV, where dV is the volume of the sphere 4πr3/3 and r = 3units.Thus we get 180π."
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "3.\tThe Gauss divergence theorem converts",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tline to surface integral",
            "b)\tline to volume integral",
            "c)\tsurface to line integral",
            "d)\tsurface to volume integral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The divergence theorem for a function F is given by ∫∫ F.dS = ∫∫∫ Div (F).dV. Thus it converts surface to volume integral."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "4.\tThe divergence theorem for a surface consisting of a sphere is computed in which coordinate system?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCartesian",
            "b)\tCylindrical",
            "c)\tSpherical",
            "d)\tDepends on the function"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Seeing the surface as sphere, we would immediately choose spherical system, but it is wrong. The divergence operation is performed in that coordinate system in which the function belongs to. It is independent of the surface region."
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "5.\tFind the Gauss value for a position vector in Cartesian system from the origin to one unit in three dimensions.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t3",
            "c)\t-3",
            "d)\t1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The position vector in Cartesian system is given by R = x i + y j + z k. Div(R) = 1 + 1 + 1 = 3. By divergence theorem, ∫∫∫3.dV, where V is a cube with x = 0->1, y = 0->1 and z = 0->1. On integrating, we get 3 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "6.\tThe divergence theorem value for the function x2 + y2 + z2 at a distance of one unit from the origin is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Div (F) = 2x + 2y + 2z. The triple integral of the divergence of the function is ∫∫∫(2x + 2y + 2z)dx dy dz, where x = 0->1, y = 0->1 and z = 0->1. On integrating, we get 3 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "7.\tIf a function is described by F = (3x + z, y2 − sin x2z, xz + yex5), then the divergence theorem value in the region 0<x<1, 0<y<3 and 0<z<2 will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t13",
            "b)\t26",
            "c)\t39",
            "d)\t51"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Div (F) = 3 + 2y + x. By divergence theorem, the triple integral of Div F in the region is ∫∫∫ (3 + 2y + x) dx dy dz. On integrating from x = 0->1, y = 0->3 and z = 0->2, we get 39 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the divergence theorem value for the function given by (ez, sin x, y2)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t0",
            "c)\t-1",
            "d)\t2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Since the divergence of the function is zero, the triple integral leads to zero. The Gauss theorem gives zero value."
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "9.\tFor a function given by F = 4x i + 7y j +z k, the divergence theorem evaluates to which of the values given, if the surface considered is a cone of radius 1/2π m and height 4π2 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t2",
            "c)\t3",
            "d)\t4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Div (F) = 4 + 7 + 1 = 12. The divergence theorem gives ∫∫∫(12).dV, where dV is the volume of the cone πr3h/3, where r = 1/2π m and h = 4π2 m. On substituting the radius and height in the triple integral, we get 2 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "1.\tCoulomb is the unit of which quantity?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tField strength",
            "b)\tCharge",
            "c)\tPermittivity",
            "d)\tForce"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The standard unit of charge is Coulomb. One coulomb is defined as the 1 Newton of force applied on 1 unit of electric field."
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "2.\tCoulomb law is employed in",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tElectrostatics",
            "b)\tMagnetostatics",
            "c)\tElectromagnetics",
            "d)\tMaxwell theory"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Coulomb law is applied to static charges. It states that force between any two point charges is proportional to the product of the charges and inversely proportional to square of the distance between them. Thus it is employed in electrostatics."
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "3.\tFind the force between 2C and -1C separated by a distance 1m in air(in newton).",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t18 X 106",
            "b)\t-18 X 106",
            "c)\t18 X 10-6",
            "d)\t-18 X 10-6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: F = q1q2/(4∏εor2) = -2 X 9/(10-9 X 12) = -18 X 109."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "4.\tTwo charges 1C and -4C exists in air. What is the direction of force?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAway from 1C",
            "b)\tAway from -4C",
            "c)\tFrom 1C to -4C",
            "d)\tFrom -4C to 1C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Since the charges are unlike, the force will be attractive. Thus the force directs from 1C to -4C."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "5.\tFind the force of interaction between 60 stat coulomb and 37.5 stat coulomb spaced 7.5cm apart in transformer oil(εr=2.2) in 10-4 N,",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t8.15",
            "b)\t5.18",
            "c)\t1.518",
            "d)\t1.815"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 1 stat coulomb = 1/(3 X 109) C\nF = (1.998 X 1.2488 X 10-16)/(4∏ X 8.854 X 10-12 X 2.2 X (7.5 X 10-2)2) = 1.815 X 10-4 N."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "6.\tFind the force between two charges when they are brought in contact and separated by 4cm apart, charges are 2nC and -1nC, in μN.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.44",
            "b)\t2.44",
            "c)\t1.404",
            "d)\t2.404"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Before the charges are brought into contact, F = 11.234 μN.\nAfter charges are brought into contact and then separated, charge on each sphere is, (q1 + q2)/2 = 0.5nC\nOn calculating the force with q1 = q2 = 0.5nC, F = 1.404μN."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "7.\tThe Coulomb law is an implication of which law?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAmpere law",
            "b)\tGauss law",
            "c)\tBiot Savart law",
            "d)\tLenz law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Coulomb law can be formulated from the Gauss law, using the divergence theorem. Thus it is an implication of Gauss law."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "8.\tTwo small diameter 10gm dielectric balls can slide freely on a vertical channel. Each carry a negative charge of 1μC. Find the separation between the balls if the lower ball is restrained from moving.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.5",
            "b)\t0.4",
            "c)\t0.3",
            "d)\t0.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: F = mg = 10 X 10-3 X 9.81 = 9.81 X 10-2 N.\nOn calculating r by substituting charges, we get r = 0.3m."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "9.\tA charge of 2 X 10-7 C is acted upon by a force of 0.1N. Determine the distance to the other charge of 4.5 X 10-7 C, both the charges are in vacuum.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.03",
            "b)\t0.05",
            "c)\t0.07",
            "d)\t0.09"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: F = q1q2/(4∏εor2) , substituting q1, q2 and F, r2 = q1q2/(4∏εoF) =\nWe get r = 0.09m."
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "10.\t For a charge Q1, the effect of charge Q2 on Q1 will be,",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tF1 = F2",
            "b)\tF1 = -F2",
            "c)\tF1 = F2 = 0",
            "d)\tF1 and F2 are not equal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The force of two charges with respect with each other is given by F1 and F2. Thus F1 + F2 = 0 and F1 = -F2."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "1.\tThe electric field intensity is defined as",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tForce per unit charge",
            "b)\tForce on a test charge",
            "c)\tForce per unit charge on a test charge",
            "d)\tProduct of force and charge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The electric field intensity is the force per unit charge on a test charge, i.e, q1 = 1C. E = F/Q = Q/(4∏εr2)."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "2.\tFind the force on a charge 2C in a field 1V/m.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Force is the product of charge and electric field.\nF = q X E = 2 X 1 = 2 N."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "3.\tFind the electric field intensity of two charges 2C and -1C separated by a distance 1m in air.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t18 X 109",
            "b)\t9 X 109",
            "c)\t36 X 109",
            "d)\t-18 X 109"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: F = q1q2/(4∏εor2) = -2 X 9/(10-9 X 12) = -18 X 109\nE = F/q = 18 X 109/2 = 9 X 109."
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "4.\tWhat is the electric field intensity at a distance of 20cm from a charge 2 X 10-6 C in vacuum?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t250,000",
            "b)\t350,000",
            "c)\t450,000",
            "d)\t550,000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: E = Q/ (4∏εor2)\n= (2 X 10-6)/(4∏ X εo X 0.22) = 450,000 V/m."
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "5.\tDetermine the charge that produces an electric field strength of 40 V/cm at a distance of 30cm in vacuum(in 10-8C)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t4",
            "b)\t2",
            "c)\t8",
            "d)\t6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: E = Q/ (4∏εor2)\nQ = (4000 X 0.32)/ (9 X 109) = 4 X 10-8 C."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "8.\tElectric field intensity due to infinite sheet of charge σ is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tZero",
            "b)\tUnity",
            "c)\tσ/ε",
            "d)\tσ/2ε"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If a test charge +q is situated at a distance r from Q, the test charge will experience a repulsive force directed radially outward from Q. Since electric field is inversely proportional to distance, thus the statement is true."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "9.\tFor a test charge placed at infinity, the electric field will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tUnity",
            "b)\t+∞",
            "c)\tZero",
            "d)\t-∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The electric field intensity of an infinitely long conductor is given by, E = λ/(4πεh).(sin α2 – sin α1)i + (cos α2 + cos α1)j\nFor an infinitely long conductor, α = 0. E = λ/(4πεh).(cos 0 + cos 0) = λ/(2πεh).aN."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "10.\tIn electromagnetic waves, the electric field will be perpendicular to which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMagnetic field intensity",
            "b)\tWave propagation",
            "c)\tBoth H and wave direction",
            "d)\tIt propagates independently"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: E = σ/2ε.(1- cos α), where α = h/(√(h2+a2))\nHere, h is the distance of the sheet from point P and a is the radius of the sheet. For infinite sheet, α = 90. Thus E = σ/2ε."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "1.\tThe lines of force are said to be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tReal",
            "b)\tImaginary",
            "c)\tDrawn to trace the direction",
            "d)\tNot significant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The lines drawn to trace the direction in which a positive test charge will experience force due to the main charge are called lines of force. They are not real but drawn for our interpretation."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "2.\tElectric flux density in electric field is referred to as",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tNumber of flux lines",
            "b)\tRatio of flux lines crossing a surface and the surface area",
            "c)\tDirection of flux at a point",
            "d)\tFlux lines per unit area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electric flux density is given by the ratio between number of flux lines crossing a surface normal to the lines and the surface area. The direction of D at a point is the direction of the flux lines at that point."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "3.\tThe electric flux density is the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tProduct of permittivity and electric field intensity",
            "b)\tProduct of number of flux lines and permittivity",
            "c)\tProduct of permeability and electric field intensity",
            "d)\tProduct of number of flux lines and permeability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: D= εE, where ε=εoεr is the permittivity of electric field and E is the electric field intensity. Thus electric flux density is the product of permittivity and electric field intensity."
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "4.\tWhich of the following correctly states Gauss law?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tElectric flux is equal to charge",
            "b)\tElectric flux per unit volume is equal to charge",
            "c)\tElectric field is equal to charge density",
            "d)\tElectric flux per unit volume is equal to volume charge density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The electric flux passing through any closed surface is equal to the total charge enclosed by that surface. In other words, electric flux per unit volume leaving a point (vanishing small volume), is equal to the volume charge density."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "5.\tThe Gaussian surface is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tReal boundary",
            "b)\tImaginary surface",
            "c)\tTangential",
            "d)\tNormal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is any physical or imaginary closed surface around a charge which satisfies the following condition: D is everywhere either normal or tangential to the surface so that D.ds becomes either Dds or 0 respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "6.\tFind the flux density of a sheet of charge density 25 units in air.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t25",
            "b)\t12.5",
            "c)\t6.25",
            "d)\t3.125"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electric field intensity of infinite sheet of charge E = σ/2ε.\nThus D = εE = σ/2 = 25/2 = 12.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "7.\tA uniform surface charge of σ = 2 μC/m2, is situated at z = 2 plane. What is the value of flux density at P(1,1,1)m?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t10-6",
            "b)\t-10-6",
            "c)\t106",
            "d)\t-106"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The flux density of any field is independent of the position (point). D = σ/2 = 2 X 10-6(-az)/2 = -10-6."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the flux density of line charge of radius (cylinder is the Gaussian surface) 2m and charge density is 3.14 units?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t0.75",
            "c)\t0.5",
            "d)\t0.25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The electric field of a line charge is given by, E = λ/(2περ), where ρ is the radius of cylinder, which is the Gaussian surface and λ is the charge density. The density D = εE = λ/(2πρ) = 3.14/(2π X 2) = 1/4 = 0.25."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "9.\tIf the radius of a sphere is 1/(4π)m and the electric flux density is 16π units, the total flux is given by,",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t3",
            "c)\t4",
            "d)\t5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Total flux leaving the entire surface is, ψ = 4πr2D from Gauss law. Ψ = 4π(1/16π2) X 16π = 4."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "10.\tFind the electric field intensity of transformer oil (εr = 2 approx) with density 1/4π (in 109 units)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2.5",
            "b)\t3.5",
            "c)\t4.5",
            "d)\t5.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: D = εE. E = (1/4π)/(2Xεo) = 4.5 X 109 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "2.\tA point charge 2nC is located at origin. What is the potential at (1,0,0)?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t12",
            "b)\t14",
            "c)\t16",
            "d)\t18"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The electric potential is the ratio of work done to the charge. Also it is the work done in moving a unit positive charge from infinity to a point in an electric field."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "3.\tSix equal point charges Q = 10nC are located at 2,3,4,5,6,7m. Find the potential at origin.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t140.35",
            "b)\t141.35",
            "c)\t142.35",
            "d)\t143.35"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: V = Q/(4πεr), where r = 1m\nV = (2 X 10-9)/(4πε x 1) = 18 volts."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "4.\tA point charge 0.4nC is located at (2, 3, 3). Find the potential differences between (2, 3, 3)m and (-2, 3, 3)m due to the charge.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2.5",
            "b)\t2.6",
            "c)\t2.7",
            "d)\t2.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: V = (1/4πεo) ∑Q/r = (10 X 10-9/4πεo)\n(0.5 + 0.33 + 0.25 + 0.2 + 0.166 + 0.142) = 143.35 volts."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "5.\tFind the potential of V = 60sin θ/r2 at P(3,60,25)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t5.774",
            "b)\t6.774",
            "c)\t7.774",
            "d)\t8.774"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Vab = (Q/4πεo)(1/rA) + (1/rB), where rA and rB are position vectors  rA = 1m and rB = 4m. Thus Vab = 2.7 volts."
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "6.\tGiven E = 40xyi + 20x2j + 2k. Calculate the potential between two points (1,-1,0) and (2,1,3).",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t105",
            "b)\t106",
            "c)\t107",
            "d)\t108"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: V = 60sin θ/r2, put r = 3m, θ = 60 and φ = 25, V = 60 sin 60/32 = 5.774 volts."
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "7.\tThe potential difference in an open circuit is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tZero",
            "b)\tUnity",
            "c)\tInfinity",
            "d)\tCircuit does not exist open"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: V = -∫ E.dl = -∫ (40xy dx + 20x2 dy + 2 dz), from (2,1,3) to (1,-1,0), we get Vpq on integrating from Q to P. Vpq = 106 volts."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "8.\tThe potential taken between two points across a resistor will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPositive",
            "b)\tNegative",
            "c)\tZero",
            "d)\tInfinity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In an open circuit no current exists due to non-existence of loops. Also voltage/potential will be infinity in an open circuit."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "9.\tWhat is the potential difference between 10sinθcosφ/r2 at A(1,30,20) and B(4,90,60)?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2.386",
            "b)\t3.386",
            "c)\t4.386",
            "d)\t5.386"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The resistor will absorb power and dissipate it in the form of heat energy. The potential between two points across a resistor will be negative."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "10.\tThe voltage at any point in an ac circuit will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPeak voltage",
            "b)\tRMS voltage",
            "c)\tAverage voltage",
            "d)\tSource voltage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Potential at A, Va = 10sin30cos20/12 = 4.6985 and Potential at B, Vb = 10sin90cos60/42 = 0.3125. Potential difference between A and B is, Vab = 4.6985 – 0.3125 = 4.386 volts."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "1.\tDivergence theorem is based on",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGauss law",
            "b)\tStoke’s law",
            "c)\tAmpere law",
            "d)\tLenz law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The divergence theorem relates surface integral and volume integral. Div(D) = ρv, which is Gauss’s law."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "2.\tThe Gaussian surface for a line charge will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSphere",
            "b)\tCylinder",
            "c)\tCube",
            "d)\tCuboid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A line charge can be visualized as a rod of electric charges. The three dimensional imaginary enclosed surface of a rod can be a cylinder."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "3.\tThe Gaussian surface for a point charge will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCube",
            "b)\tCylinder",
            "c)\tSphere",
            "d)\tCuboid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A point charge is single dimensional. The three dimensional imaginary enclosed surface of a point charge will be sphere."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "4.\tA circular disc of radius 5m with a surface charge density ρs = 10sinφ is enclosed by surface. What is the net flux crossing the surface?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3",
            "b)\t2",
            "c)\t1",
            "d)\t0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Q = ∫ ρsds = ∫∫ 10sinφ rdrdφ, on integrating with r = 0->5 and φ = 0->2π, we get Q = ψ = 0."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "5.\tThe total charge of a surface with densities 1,2,…,10 is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t11",
            "b)\t33",
            "c)\t55",
            "d)\t77"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Q = ∫∫D.ds. Since the data is discrete, the total charge will be summation of 1,2,…,10,i.e, 1+2+…+10 = 10(11)/2 = 55."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "6.\tThe work done by a charge of 10μC with a potential 4.386 is (in μJ)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t32.86",
            "b)\t43.86",
            "c)\t54.68",
            "d)\t65.68"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: By Gauss law principles, W = Q X V = 10 X 10-6 X 4.386 = 43.86 X 10-6 joule."
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "7.\tThe potential of a coaxial cylinder with charge density 1 unit , inner radius 1m and outer cylinder 2m is (in 109)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t12.74",
            "b)\t13.47",
            "c)\t12.47",
            "d)\t13.74"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The potential of a coaxial cylinder will be ρl ln(b/a)/2πε, where ρl = 1, b = 2m and a = 1m. We get V = 12.47 X 109 volts."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the potential due to a charged ring of density 2 units with radius 2m and the point at which potential is measured is at a distance of 1m from the ring.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t18π",
            "b)\t24π",
            "c)\t36π",
            "d)\t72π"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The potential due to a charged ring is given by λa/2εr, where a = 2m and r = 1m. We get V = 72π volts."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "9.\tGauss law cannot be used to find which of the following quantity?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tElectric field intensity",
            "b)\tElectric flux density",
            "c)\tCharge",
            "d)\tPermittivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Permittivity is constant for a particular material(say permittivity of water is 1). It cannot be determined from Gauss law, whereas the remaining options can be computed from Gauss law."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "10.\t Gauss law for magnetic fields is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDiv(E) = 0",
            "b)\tDiv(B) = 0",
            "c)\tDiv(H) = 0",
            "d)\tDiv(D) = 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The divergence of magnetic flux density is always zero. This is called Gauss law for magnetic fields. It implies the non-existence of magnetic monopoles in any magnetic field."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "1.\tGauss law can be used to compute which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPermittivity",
            "b)\tPermeability",
            "c)\tRadius of Gaussian surface",
            "d)\tElectric potential"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gauss law relates the electric flux density and the charge density. Thus it can be used to compute radius of the Gaussian surface. Permittivity and permeability are constants for a particular material."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "2.\tThree charged cylindrical sheets are present in three spaces with σ = 5 at R = 2m, σ = -2 at R = 4m and σ = -3 at R = 5m. Find the flux density at R = 1m.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since 1m does not enclose any cylinder (three Gaussian surfaces of radius 2m, 4m, 5m exists), the charge density and charge becomes zero according to Gauss law. Thus flux density is also zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "3.\tThree charged cylindrical sheets are present in three spaces with σ = 5 at R = 2m, σ = -2 at R = 4m and σ = -3 at R = 5m. Find the flux density at R = 3m.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3",
            "b)\t10/3",
            "c)\t11/3",
            "d)\t4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The radius is 3m, hence it will enclose one Gaussian cylinder of R = 2m.\nBy Gauss law, ψ = Q\nD(2πRL) = σ(2πRL), D(2π X 3) = σ(2π X 2), Thus D = 10/3 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "4.\tThree charged cylindrical sheets are present in three spaces with σ = 5 at R = 2m, σ = -2 at R = 4m and σ =-3 at R = 5m. Find the flux density at R = 4.5m.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t4/4.5",
            "b)\t3/4.5",
            "c)\t2/4.5",
            "d)\t1/4.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Gaussian cylinder of R = 4.5m encloses sum of charges of two cylinders (R = 2m and R = 4m).\nBy Gauss law,  ψ = Q\nD(2πRL) = σ(2πRL), D(2π X 4.5) = Q1 + Q2 =  σ1(2π X 2) + σ2(2π X 4), here σ1 = 5 and σ2 = -2. We get D = 2/4.5 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "5.\tThree charged cylindrical sheets are present in three spaces with σ = 5 at R = 2m, σ = -2 at R = 4m and σ = -3 at R = 5m. Find the flux density at R = 6m.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t17/6",
            "b)\t-17/6",
            "c)\t13/6",
            "d)\t-13/6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The radius R = 6m encloses all the three Gaussian cylinders.\nBy Gauss law,  ψ = Q\nD(2πRL) = σ(2πRL), D(2π X 6) = Q1 + Q2 + Q3 =  σ1(2π X 2) + σ2(2π X 4) + σ3(2π X 5), here σ1 = 5, σ2 = -2 and σ3 = -3. We get D = -13/6 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "6.\tGauss law can be evaluated in which coordinate system?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCartesian",
            "b)\tCylinder",
            "c)\tSpherical",
            "d)\tDepends on the Gaussian surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Gauss law exists for all materials. Depending on the Gaussian surface of the material, we take the coordinate systems accordingly. Suppose if the material is a coaxial cable, the Gaussian surface is in the form of cylinder. Thus we take Cylinder/Circular coordinate system."
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "7.\tGauss law cannot be expressed in which of the following forms?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDifferential",
            "b)\tIntegral",
            "c)\tPoint",
            "d)\tStokes theorem"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gauss law can be expressed in differential or point form as,\nDiv (D)= ρv and in integral form as ∫∫ D.ds = Q = ψ . It is not possible to express it using Stoke’s theorem."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "10.\t With Gauss law as reference which of the following law can be derived?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAmpere law",
            "b)\tFaraday’s law",
            "c)\tCoulomb’s law",
            "d)\tOhm’s law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Consider a dielectric-dielectric boundary, the electric field intensity in both the surfaces will be Et1 = Et2, which implies that the tangential component of electric field intensity is always continuous at the boundary."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "1.\tThe electric flux density and electric field intensity have which of the following relation?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLinear",
            "b)\tNonlinear",
            "c)\tInversely linear",
            "d)\tInversely nonlinear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The electric flux density is directly proportional to electric field intensity. The proportionality constant is permittivity. D=ε E. It is clear that both are in linear relationship. "
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "3.\tFind the electric potential for an electric field 3units at a distance of 2m.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t9",
            "b)\t4",
            "c)\t6",
            "d)\t 3/2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: V = -∫E.dl is the integral form. On differentiating both sides, we get E = -Grad (V). Thus the electric field intensity is the negative gradient of the electric potential."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the potential at a point (4, 3, -6) for the function V = 2x2y + 5z.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t96",
            "b)\t66",
            "c)\t30",
            "d)\t-66"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The electric field intensity is the ratio of electric potential to the distance. E = V/d. To get V = E X d = 3 X 2 = 6units."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Options": [
            "6.\tIf potential V = 20/(x2 + y2). The electric field intensity for V is",
            "40(x i + y j)/(x2 + y2)2. State True/False.",
            "a)\tTrue",
            "b)\tFalse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The electric potential for the function V = 2x2y + 5z at the point (4, 3, -6) is given by V = 2(4)2(3) + 5(-6) = 96-30 = 66 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "7.\tFind the potential of the function V = 60cos θ/r at the point P(3, 60, 25).",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t20",
            "b)\t10",
            "c)\t30",
            "d)\t60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: D = εE, where ε = εo εr. The flux density is given by,\nD = 8.854 X 10-12 X 2.2 X 2(1)(2)(3) = 2.33 X 10-10 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the work done moving a charge 2C having potential V = 24volts is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t96",
            "b)\t24",
            "c)\t36",
            "d)\t48"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: E = -Grad (V) = -Grad(20/(x2 + y2)) = -(-40x i /(x2 + y2)2 – 40(y j)/(x2 + y2)2) = 40(x i + y j)/(x2 + y2)2. Thus the statement is true."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "10.\t If V = 2x2y + 20z – 4/(x2 + y2), find the density at A(6, -2.5, 3) in nC/m2.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.531i – 0.6373j – 0.177k",
            "b)\t0.6373i – 0.177j -0.531k",
            "c)\t0.177i – 0.6373j – 0.531k",
            "d)\t0.531i – 0.177j – 0.6373k"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Given V = 60cos θ/r. For r = 3m and θ = 60, we get V = 60cos 60/3 = 20cos 60 = 10 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "1.\tCalculate the capacitance of a material in air with area 20 units and distance between plates is 5m.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t35.36pF",
            "b)\t3.536pF",
            "c)\t35.36nF",
            "d)\t3.536nF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The capacitance of any material is given by, C = εA/d, where ε = εoεr is the permittivity in air and the material respectively. Thus C = 1 X 8.854 X 10-12 X 20/5 = 35.36pF."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "2.\tThe resistance of a material with conductivity 2millimho/m2, length 10m and area 50m is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t500",
            "b)\t200",
            "c)\t100",
            "d)\t1000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The resistance is given by, R = ρL/A, where ρ is the resistivity, the inverse of conductivity. R = 10/(0.002 X 50) = 100 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "3.\tFind the inductance of a coil with permeability 3.5, turns 100 and length 2m. Assume the area to be thrice the length.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t131.94mH",
            "b)\t94.131mH",
            "c)\t131.94H",
            "d)\t94.131H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The inductance is given by L = μ N2A/l, where μ= μoμr is the permeability of air and the material respectively. N = 100 and Area = 3 X 2 = 6. L = 4π X 10-7 X 1002 X 6/2 = 131.94mH."
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the current density of a material with resistivity 20 units and electric field intensity 2000 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t400",
            "b)\t300",
            "c)\t200",
            "d)\t100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The current density is given by J = σ E, where σ is the conductivity. Thus resistivity ρ = 1/σ. J = E/ρ = 2000/20 = 100 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "5.\tFind the current in a conductor with resistance 2 ohm, electric field 2 units and distance 100cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1A",
            "b)\t10mA",
            "c)\t10A",
            "d)\t100mA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We know that E = V/d. To get potential, V = E X d = 2 X 1 = 2 volts. From Ohm’s law, V = IR and current I = V/R = 2/2 = 1A."
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "6.\tIn electric fields, D= ε E. The correct expression which is analogous in magnetic fields will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tH = μ B",
            "b)\tB = μ H",
            "c)\tA = μ B",
            "d)\tH = μ A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In electric fields, the flux density is a product of permittivity and field intensity. Similarly, for magnetic fields, the magnetic flux density is the product of permeability and magnetic field intensity, given by B= μ H."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "7.\tFind the force on a conductor of length 12m and magnetic flux density 20 units when a current of 0.5A is flowing through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t60",
            "b)\t120",
            "c)\t180",
            "d)\t200"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The force on a conductor is given by F = BIL, where B = 20, I = 0.5 and L = 12. Force F = 20 X 0.5 x 12 = 120 N."
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "9.\tCalculate the power of a material with electric field 100 units at a distance of 10cm with a current of 2A flowing through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t 10",
            "b)\t20",
            "c)\t40",
            "d)\t80"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We know that F = qE = qV/d and W = qV. Thus it is clear that qV = W and qV = Fd. On equating both, we get W = Fd, which is the required proof."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "10.\t Compute the power consumed by a material with current density 15 units in an area of 100 units. The potential measured across the material is 20V.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t100kJ",
            "b)\t250kJ",
            "c)\t30kJ",
            "d)\t15kJ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Power is defined as the product of voltage and current.\nP = V X I, where V = E X d. Thus P = E X d X I = 100 X 0.1 X 2 = 20 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "1.\tChoose the best definition of a dipole.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tA pair of equal and like charges located at the origin",
            "b)\tA pair of unequal and like charges located at the origin",
            "c)\tA pair of equal and unlike charges separated by a small distance",
            "d)\tA pair of unequal and unlike charges separated by a small distance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An electric dipole generally refers to two equal and unlike (opposite signs) charges separated by a small distance. It can be anywhere, not necessarily at origin."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "2.\tThe potential due to a dipole at a point P from it is the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSum of potentials at the charges",
            "b)\tDifference of potentials at the charges",
            "c)\tMultiplication of potentials at the charges",
            "d)\tRatio of potentials at the charges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The total potential at the point P due to the dipole is given by the difference of the potentials of the individual charges.\nV = V1 + (-V2), since both the charges are unlike. Thus V = V1 – V2."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "3.\tCalculate the dipole moment of a dipole with equal charges 2C and -2C separated by a distance of 2cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.02",
            "b)\t0.04",
            "c)\t0.06",
            "d)\t0.08"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The dipole moment of charge 2C and distance 2cm will be,\nM = Q x d. Thus, M = 2 x 0.02 = 0.04 C-m. "
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the angle at which the potential due a dipole is measured, when the distance from one charge is 12cm and that due to other is 11cm, separated to each other by a distance of 2cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t15",
            "b)\t30",
            "c)\t45",
            "d)\t60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Here, the two charges are separated by d = 2cm.\nThe distance from one charge (say Q1) will be R1 = 11cm. The distance from another charge (say Q2) will be R2 = 12cm. If R1 and R2 is assumed to be parallel, then R2 – R1 = d cos θ. We get 1 = 2cos θ and cos θ = 0.5. Then θ =\ncos-1(0.5) = 60."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "5.\tFind the potential due the dipole when the angle subtended by the two charges at the point P is perpendicular.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\tUnity",
            "c)\t∞",
            "d)\t-∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The potential due the dipole is given by, V = m cos θ/(4πεr2). When the angle becomes perpendicular (θ = 90). The potential becomes zero since cos 90 will become zero. "
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "6.\tFor two charges 3C and -3C separated by 1cm and are located at distances 5cm and 7cm respectively from the point P, then the distance between their midpoint and the point P will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t5.91",
            "b)\t12.6",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a distant point P, the R1 and R2 will approximately be equal.\nR1 = R2 = r, where r is the distance between P and the midpoint of the two charges. Thus they are in geometric progression, R1R2=r2\nNow, r2 = 5 x 7 = 35. We get r = 5.91cm."
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "7.\tCalculate the distance between two charges of 4C forming a dipole, with a dipole moment of 6 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t1.5",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t2.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The dipole moment is given by, M = Q x d. To get d, we rearrange the formula d = M/Q = 6/4 = 1.5units."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "8.\tThe potential due to the dipole on the midpoint of the two charges will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\tUnity",
            "c)\t∞",
            "d)\t-∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The potential due a dipole at a point P will be  V = m cos θ/(4πεr2).\nNow it is given that potential on the midpoint, which means P is on midpoint, then the distance from midpoint and P will be zero. When r = 0 is put in the above equation, we get V = ∞. This shows that the potential of a dipole at its midpoint will be maximum/infinity. "
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "9.\tDipoles in any electric field undergo",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMagnetism",
            "b)\tElectromagnetism",
            "c)\tMagnetisation",
            "d)\tPolarisation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Dipoles in any pure electric field will undergo polarisation. It is the process of alignment of dipole moments in accordance with the electric field applied."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "10.\t Dipole moments are used to calculate the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tElectric field intensity",
            "b)\tPolarisation patterns",
            "c)\tStrength of the dipole in the field",
            "d)\tSusceptibility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Dipole moment implicates the strength of the dipole in the electric field. They are then used to compute the polarisation patterns based on the applied field. Once the polarisation is determined we can find its susceptibility. Though all options seem to be correct, the apt answer is to calculate polarisation, provided applied field is known."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "1.\tThe electrostatic energy in an electric field does not depend on which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMagnitude of charges",
            "b)\tPermittivity",
            "c)\tApplied electric field",
            "d)\tFlux lines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The energy in an electric field directly magnitude of charges. Thus electric field and flux density are also dependent. But the applied field affects only the polarisation and it is independent of the energy in the field."
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "2.\tCalculate the energy in an electric field with flux density 6 units and field intensity of 4 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t12",
            "b)\t24",
            "c)\t36",
            "d)\t48"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The energy in an electric field is given by, W = 0.5 x D x E, where D = 6 and E = 4. We get W = 0.5 x 6 x 4 = 12 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "3.\tCalculate the energy in an electric field with permittivity of 56 and field intensity of 36π(in μJ)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3.16",
            "b)\t5.16",
            "c)\t7.16",
            "d)\t9.16"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The energy in an electric field is given by, W = 0.5 x D x E. Since D = εE, we get W = 0.5 x ε x E2. On substituting the data, we get 3.16 microjoule."
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "4.\tEquipotential surface is a",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tReal surface",
            "b)\tComplex surface",
            "c)\tImaginary surface",
            "d)\tNot existing surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Equipotential surface is an imaginary surface in an electric field of a given charge distribution in which all the points on the surface are at the same electric potential."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "7.\tIf the electric potential is given, which of the following cannot be calculated?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tElectrostatic energy",
            "b)\tElectric field intensity",
            "c)\tElectric flux density",
            "d)\tPermittivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since the electric potential in the equipotential surface is the same, the work done will be zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "8.\tSuperconductors exhibit which of the following properties?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tFerromagnetism",
            "b)\tPolarisation",
            "c)\tDiamagnetism",
            "d)\tFerrimagnetism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: By Stoke’s theorem, when curl of a path becomes zero, then\n∫ E.dl = 0. In other words the work done in a closed path will always be zero. Fields having this property is called conservative or lamellar fields."
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "9.\tDebye is the unit used to measure",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPermittivity",
            "b)\tElectric dipole moment",
            "c)\tMagnetic dipole moment",
            "d)\tSusceptibility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Using potential, we can calculate electric field directly by gradient operation. From E, the flux density D can also be calculated. Thus it is not possible to calculate energy directly from potential."
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "10.\t Ceramic materials possess which of the following properties?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBrittle and low dielectric constant",
            "b)\tRigid and low dielectric constant",
            "c)\tBrittle and high dielectric constant",
            "d)\tRigid and high dielectric constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Since superconductors have very good conductivity at low temperatures (σ->∞), they have nearly zero resistivity and exhibit perfect diamagnetism."
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "1.\tThe permittivity is also called",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tElectrostatic energy",
            "b)\tDielectric constant",
            "c)\tDipole moment",
            "d)\tSusceptibility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The term permittivity or dielectric constant is the measurement of electrostatic energy stored within it and therefore depends on the material."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "2.\tDielectric constant will be high in",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConductors",
            "b)\tSemiconductors",
            "c)\tInsulators",
            "d)\tSuperconductors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Materials that have very less conductivity like ceramics, plastics have higher dielectric constants. Due to their low conductivity, the dielectric materials are said to be good insulators."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "4.\tInsulators perform which of the following functions?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConduction",
            "b)\tConvection",
            "c)\tProvide electrical insulation",
            "d)\tAllows current leakage at interfaces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The dielectrics have the ability of storing energy easily when an electric field is applied as their permittivity is relatively higher than any other materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "5.\tWhich of the following properties distinguish a material as conductor, insulator and semiconductor?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tFree electron charges",
            "b)\tFermi level after doping",
            "c)\tEnergy band gap",
            "d)\tElectron density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Insulators is a non-conducting material which prevents the leakage of electric current in unwanted directions. Thus it is used to provide electrical insulation."
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "6.\tSemiconductors possess which type of bonding?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMetallic",
            "b)\tCovalent",
            "c)\tIonic",
            "d)\tMagnetic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The only parameter that classifies the material as conductor or insulator or semiconductor is the band gap energy. It is the energy required to make the electrons conduct. This is low of conductors, average for semiconductors and very high for insulators. This means it requires very high energy to make an insulator conduct. "
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "7.\tFind the susceptibility of a material whose dielectric constant is 2.26.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.26",
            "b)\t3.26",
            "c)\t5.1",
            "d)\t1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Conductors exhibit metallic bonding. Insulators exhibit ionic bonding and semiconductors exhibit covalent bonding due to sharing of atoms."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "8.\tThe bound charge density and free charge density are 12 and 6 units respectively. Calculate the susceptibility.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t0",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t72"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electric susceptibility is the measure of ability of the material to get polarised. It is given by, χe = εr – 1.Thus we get 1.26.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "9.\tThe susceptibility of free space is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t0",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The electric susceptibility is given by, χe = Bound free density/Free charge density. χe = 12/6 = 2. It has no unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "10.\tWhen the electric field becomes zero, which of the following relations hold good?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tE = P",
            "b)\tD = P",
            "c)\tB = P",
            "d)\tH = P"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For free space/air, the relative permittivity is unity i.e, εr = 1. Thus χe = εr – 1 = 0. The susceptibility will become zero in air."
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich of the following are conductors?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCeramics",
            "b)\tPlastics",
            "c)\tMercury",
            "d)\tRubber"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Normally, metals are said to be good conductors. Here mercury is the only metal (which is in liquid form). The other options are insulators."
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "2.\tFind the range of band gap energy for conductors.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t>6 eV",
            "b)\t0.2-0.4 eV",
            "c)\t0.4-2 eV",
            "d)\t2-6 eV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Conductors are materials with least band gap energy. The smallest range in this group is 0.2-0.4 eV."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "3.\tConduction in metals is due to",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tElectrons only",
            "b)\tElectrons and holes",
            "c)\tHoles only",
            "d)\tApplied electric field"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Conduction in metals is only due to majority carriers, which are electrons. Electrons and holes are responsible for conduction in a semiconductor."
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the band gap energy when a light of wavelength 1240nm is incident on it.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1eV",
            "b)\t2eV",
            "c)\t3eV",
            "d)\t4eV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The band gap energy in electron volt when wavelength is given is, Eg = 1.24(μm)/λ = 1.24 x 10-6/1240 x 10-9 = 1eV."
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "5.\tAlternating current measured in a transmission line will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPeak value",
            "b)\tAverage value",
            "c)\tRMS value",
            "d)\tZero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The instantaneous current flowing in a transmission line, when measured using an ammeter, will give RMS current value. This value is 70.7% of the peak value. This is because, due to oscillations in AC, it is not possible to measure peak value. Hence to normalise, we consider current at any time in a line will be the RMS current."
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "6.\tThe current in a metal at any frequency is due to",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConduction current",
            "b)\tDisplacement current",
            "c)\tBoth conduction and displacement current",
            "d)\tNeither conduction nor displacement current"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At any frequency, the current through the metal will be due to conduction current. Only at high frequencies and when medium is air, the conduction is due to displacement current. Thus in general the current in metal is due to conduction current, which depends on the mobility of the carriers."
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "7.\tFor conductors, the free electrons will exist at",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tValence band",
            "b)\tMiddle of valence and conduction band",
            "c)\tWill not exist",
            "d)\tConduction band"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In conductors, the free electrons exist in the conduction band. Since the band gap energy is very low, less energy is required to transport the free electrons to the conduction band, as they are readily available to conduct."
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "8.\tThe current flowing through an insulating medium is called",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConduction",
            "b)\tConvection",
            "c)\tRadiation",
            "d)\tSusceptibility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A beam of electrons in a vacuum tube is called convection current. It occurs when current flows through an insulating medium like liquid, vacuum etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "9.\tFind the conduction current density when conductivity of a material is 500 units and corresponding electric field is 2 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t500",
            "b)\t250",
            "c)\t1000",
            "d)\t2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The conduction current density is given by, J = σE\nJ = 500 X 2 = 1000 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "10.\tCalculate the convection current when electron density of 200 units is travelling at a speed of 12m/s.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t16.67",
            "b)\t2400",
            "c)\t2880",
            "d)\t0.06"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The convection current density is given by, J = ρeV\nJ = 200 X 12= 2400 units. "
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "2.\tIdentify a good dielectric.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIron",
            "b)\tCeramics",
            "c)\tPlastic",
            "d)\tMagnesium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: For a material to be dielectric, its permittivity should be very high. This is seen in insulators. For a material to be insulator, the condition is to have large band gap energy. However, this is not necessary for a dielectric."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "3.\tA dielectric can be made a conductor by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCompression",
            "b)\tHeating",
            "c)\tDoping",
            "d)\tFreezing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Iron and magnesium are metals. Hence they need not be considered. Both ceramics and plastic are insulators. But dielectric constant is more for ceramics always. Hence ceramics is the best dielectric."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the dielectric constant for a material with electric susceptibility of 4.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3",
            "b)\t5",
            "c)\t8",
            "d)\t16"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: On increasing the temperature, the free electrons in an insulator can be promoted from valence to conduction band. Gradually, it can act as a conductor through heating process. This condition is called dielectric breakdown, wherein the insulator loses its dielectric property and starts to conduct."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "5.\tFor a dielectric which of the following properties hold good?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThey are superconductors at high temperatures",
            "b)\tThey are superconductors at low temperatures",
            "c)\tThey can never become a superconductor",
            "d)\tThey have very less dielectric breakdown voltage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The electric susceptibility is given by χe = εr – 1. For a susceptibility of 4, the dielectric constant will be 5. It has no unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "6.\tThe magnetic field which destroys the superconductivity is called",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDiamagnetic field",
            "b)\tFerromagnetic field",
            "c)\tFerrimagnetic field",
            "d)\tCritical field"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Superconductors are characterised by diamagnetism behaviour and zero resistivity, which true for a dielectric. They occur only at low temperature. Thus a dielectric can become a superconductor at low temperatures with very high dielectric breakdown voltage."
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "7.\tThe magnetic susceptibility in a superconductor will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPositive",
            "b)\tNegative",
            "c)\tZero",
            "d)\tInfinity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Critical field is that strong magnetic field which can destroy the superconductivity of a material. The temperature at which this occurs is called transition temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "8.\tThe superconducting materials will be independent of which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMagnetic field",
            "b)\tElectric field",
            "c)\tMagnetization",
            "d)\tTemperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Due to perfect diamagnetism in a superconductor, its magnetic susceptibility will be negative. This phenomenon is called Meissner effect."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "9.\tFind the mean free path of an electron travelling at a speed of 18m/s in 2 seconds.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t9",
            "b)\t36",
            "c)\t0.11",
            "d)\t4.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Superconducting materials depends only on the applied magnetic field, resultant magnetization at the temperature considered. It is independent of the applied electric field and the corresponding polarization."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "1.\tFind the conductivity of a material with conduction current density 100 units and electric field of 4 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t25",
            "b)\t400",
            "c)\t0.04",
            "d)\t1600"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The conduction current density is given by, Jc = σE. To get conductivity, σ = J/E = 100/4 = 25 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "2.\tCalculate the displacement current density when the electric flux density is 20sin 0.5t.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t10sin 0.5t",
            "b)\t10cos 0.5t",
            "c)\t20sin 2t",
            "d)\t20cos 2t"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation: The displacement current density is given by, Jd = dD/dt.\nJd = d(20sin 0.5t)/dt = 20cos 0.5t (0.5) = 10cos 0.5t."
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "3.\tFind the magnitude of the displacement current density in air at a frequency of 18GHz in frequency domain. Take electric field E as 4 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t18",
            "b)\t72",
            "c)\t36",
            "d)\t4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Jd = dD/dt = εdE/dt in time domain. For frequency domain, convert using Fourier transform, Jd = εjωE. The magnitude of\nJd = εωE = ε(2πf)E. On substituting, we get 4 ampere."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "4.\tCalculate the frequency at which the conduction and displacement currents become equal with unity conductivity in a material of permittivity 2.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t18 GHz",
            "b)\t9 GHz",
            "c)\t36 GHz",
            "d)\t24 GHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When Jd = Jc , we get εωE = σE. Thus εo(2∏f) = σ. On substituting conductivity as one and permittivity as 2, we get f = 9GHz."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "5.\tThe ratio of conduction to displacement current density is referred to as",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAttenuation constant",
            "b)\tPropagation constant",
            "c)\tLoss tangent",
            "d)\tDielectric constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Jc /Jd is a standard ratio, which is referred to as loss tangent given by σ /ε ω. The loss tangent is used to determine if the material is a conductor or dielectric."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "6.\tIf the loss tangent is very less, then the material will be a",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConductor",
            "b)\tLossless dielectric",
            "c)\tLossy dielectric",
            "d)\tInsulator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If loss tangent is less, then σ /ε ω <<1. This implies the conductivity is very poor and the material should be a dielectric. Since it is specifically mentioned very less, assuming the conductivity to be zero, the dielectric will be lossless (ideal)."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "7.\tIn good conductors, the electric and magnetic fields will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t45 in phase",
            "b)\t45 out of phase",
            "c)\t90 in phase",
            "d)\t90 out of phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The electric and magnetic fields will be out of phase by 45 in good conductors. This is because their intrinsic impedance is given by η = √(ωμ/σ) X (1+j). In polar form we get 45 out of phase. "
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "8.\tIn free space, which of the following will be zero?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPermittivity",
            "b)\tPermeability",
            "c)\tConductivity",
            "d)\tResistivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In free space, ε = ε0 and μ = μ0. The relative permittivity and permeability will be unity. Since the free space will contain no charges in it, the conductivity will be zero. "
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "9.\tIf the intrinsic angle is 20, then find the loss tangent.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\ttan 20",
            "b)\ttan 40",
            "c)\ttan 60",
            "d)\ttan 80"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The loss tangent is given by tan 2θn, where θn = 20. Thus the loss tangent will be tan 40."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "10.\tThe intrinsic impedance of free space is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t272 ohm",
            "b)\t412 ohm",
            "c)\t740 ohm",
            "d)\t377 ohm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The intrinsic impedance is given by η = √(μo/εo) ohm. Here εo = 8.854 x 10-12 and μo = 4π x 10-7.\nOn substituting the values, we get η = 377 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "1.\tThe best definition of polarisation is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tOrientation of dipoles in random direction",
            "b)\tElectric dipole moment per unit volume",
            "c)\tOrientation of dipole moments",
            "d)\tChange in polarity of every dipole"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The polarisation is defined mathematically as the electric dipole moment per unit volume. It is also referred to as the orientation of the dipoles in the direction of applied electric field."
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "2.\tCalculate the polarisation vector of the material which has 100 dipoles per unit volume in a volume of 2 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t200",
            "b)\t50",
            "c)\t400",
            "d)\t0.02"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Polarisation vector P = N x p, where N = 100 and p = 2. On substituting we get P = 200 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "3.\tPolarizability is defined as the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tProduct of dipole moment and electric field",
            "b)\tRatio of dipole moment to electric field",
            "c)\tRatio of electric field to dipole moment",
            "d)\tProduct of dielectric constant and dipole moment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Polarizability is a constant that is defined as the ratio of elemental dipole moment to the electric field strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "4.\tCalculate the energy stored per unit volume in a dielectric medium due to polarisation when P = 9 units and E = 8 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.77",
            "b)\t2.25",
            "c)\t36",
            "d)\t144"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The energy stored per unit volume in a dielectric medium is given by, W = 0.5 X PE = 0.5 X 9 X 8 = 36 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "5.\tIdentify which type of polarisation depends on temperature.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tElectronic",
            "b)\tIonic",
            "c)\tOrientational",
            "d)\tInterfacial"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The electronic, ionic and interfacial polarisation depends on the atoms which are independent with respect to temperature. Only the orientational polarisation is dependent on the temperature and is inversely proportional to it."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "6.\tCalculate the polarisation vector in air when the susceptibility is 5 and electric field is 12 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3",
            "b)\t2",
            "c)\t60",
            "d)\t2.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The polarisation vector is given by, P = ε0 x χe x E, where χe = 5 and ε0 = 12. On substituting, we get P = 1 x 5 x 12 = 60 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "7.\tIn isotropic materials, which of the following quantities will be independent of the direction?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPermittivity",
            "b)\tPermeability",
            "c)\tPolarisation",
            "d)\tPolarizability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Isotropic materials are those with radiate or absorb energy uniformly in all directions (eg. Isotropic antenna). Thus it is independent of the direction."
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "8.\tThe total polarisation of a material is the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tProduct of all types of polarisation",
            "b)\tSum of all types of polarisation",
            "c)\tOrientation directions of the dipoles",
            "d)\tTotal dipole moments in the material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The total polarisation of a material is given by the sum of electronic, ionic, orientational and interfacial polarisation of the material."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "9.\tIn the given types of polarisation, which type exists in the semiconductor?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tElectronic",
            "b)\tIonic",
            "c)\tOrientational",
            "d)\tInterfacial or space charge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The interfacial type of polarisation occurs due to accumulation of charges at the interface in a multiphase material. This interface or junction is found in a semiconductor material. "
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "10.\t Solids do not have which type of polarisation?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIonic",
            "b)\tOrientational",
            "c)\tInterfacial",
            "d)\tElectronic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Solids possess permanent dipole moments. Moreover they do not have junction like semiconductors. Thus, solids neglect the interfacial and space charge polarisation. They possess only electronic, ionic and orientational polarisations."
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich of the following is not an example of elemental solid dielectric?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDiamond",
            "b)\tSulphur",
            "c)\tSilicon",
            "d)\tGermanium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Elemental solid dielectrics are the materials consisting of single type of atoms. Such materials have neither ions nor permanent dipoles and possess only electronic polarisation. Its examples are diamond, sulphur and germanium. "
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "3.\tCompute the refractive index when the dielectric constant is 256 in air.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2562",
            "b)\t16",
            "c)\t256",
            "d)\t64"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In ionic crystals, the total polarisation is electronic and ionic in nature. Thus, it implies that it contains more than one type of atom and no permanent dipoles."
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "5.\tCurie-Weiss law is applicable to which of the following materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPiezoelectric",
            "b)\tFerroelectric",
            "c)\tPyroelectric",
            "d)\tAnti-ferroelectric"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: By Maxwell relation, εr = n2, where εro is the dielectric constant at optical frequencies and n is the refractive index.For the given dielectric constant we get n = 16. "
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "6.\tCurie-Weiss law is used to calculate which one of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPermittivity",
            "b)\tPermeability",
            "c)\tElectric susceptibility",
            "d)\tMagnetic susceptibility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Based on the dielectric property, a material can be classified as piezoelectric, ferroelectric, pyroelectric and anti-ferroelectric materials under the influence of electric field."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "7.\tCalculate the loss tangent when the dielectric constant in AC field is given by 3 + 2j.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t(2/3)",
            "b)\t(3/2)",
            "c)\t(-3/2)",
            "d)\t(-2/3)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Curie-Weiss law is given by χe = εr -1 = C/(T-θ), where C is the curie constant and θ is the characteristic temperature which is usually a few degrees higher than the curie temperature for ferromagnetic materials. "
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "8.\tWhen a dielectric loses its dielectric property, the phenomenon is called",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDielectric loss",
            "b)\tDielectric breakdown",
            "c)\tPolarisation",
            "d)\tMagnetization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Curie-Weiss law is given by χe = εr -1. Thus it is used to calculate the electric susceptibility of a material."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "9.\tChoose the best definition of dielectric loss.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAbsorption of electric energy by dielectric in an AC field",
            "b)\tDissipation of electric energy by dielectric in a static field",
            "c)\tDissipation of heat by dielectric",
            "d)\tProduct of loss tangent and relative permittivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The AC dielectric constant is given by εr = ε` – jε“, where ε` is the real part of AC dielectric and ε“ is the imaginary part of AC dielectric. The loss tangent is given by tan δ = ε“/ε` = -2/3."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "10.\t Compute the loss factor when the loss tangent is 0.88 and the real part of dielectric is 24.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t12.12",
            "b)\t12.21",
            "c)\t21.21",
            "d)\t21.12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Due to various treatments performed on the dielectric, in order to make it conduct, the dielectric reaches a state, where it loses its dielectric property and starts to conduct. This phenomenon is called as dielectric breakdown."
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "1.\tFind the current when the charge is a time function given by q(t) = 3t + t2 at 2 seconds.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3",
            "b)\t5",
            "c)\t7",
            "d)\t9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The current is defined as the rate of change of charge in a circuit ie, I = dq/dt. On differentiating the charge with respect to time, we get 3 + 2t. At time t = 2s, I = 7A."
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "2.\tThe continuity equation is a combination of which of the two laws?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tOhm’s law and Gauss law",
            "b)\tAmpere law and Gauss law",
            "c)\tOhm’s law and Ampere law",
            "d)\tMaxwell law and Ampere law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: I = ∫ J.ds is the integral form of Ohm’s law and Div (J) = dq/dt is the Gauss law analogous to D. Through these two equations, we get Div(J) = -dρ/dt. This is the continuity equation."
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "3.\tCalculate the charge density for the current density given 20sin x i + ycos z j at the origin.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t20t",
            "b)\t21t",
            "c)\t19t",
            "d)\t-20t"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Using continuity equation, the problem can be solved. Div(J) =\n– dρ/dt. Div(J) = 20cos x + cos z. At origin, we get 20cos 0 + cos 0 = 21. To get ρ, on integrating the Div(J) with respect to t, the charge density will be 21t."
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "Compute the conductivity when the current density is 12 units and the electric field is 20 units. Also identify the nature of the material.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.67, dielectric",
            "b)\t1.67, conductor",
            "c)\t0.6, dielectric",
            "d)\t0.6, conductor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The current density is the product of conductivity and electric field intensity. J = σE. To get σ, put J = 12 and E = 20. σ = 12/20 = 0.6. Since the conductivity is less than unity, the material is a dielectric. "
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "5.\tFind the electron density when convection current density is 120 units and the velocity is 5m/s.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t12",
            "b)\t600",
            "c)\t24",
            "d)\t720"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The convection current density is given by J = ρe x v. To get ρe, put J = 120 and v = 5. ρe = 120/5 = 24 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "6.\tCalculate the electric field when the conductivity is 20 units, electron density is 2.4 units and the velocity is 10m/s. Assume the conduction and convection current densities are same.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2.4",
            "b)\t4.8",
            "c)\t3.6",
            "d)\t1.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The conduction current density is given by J = σE and the convection current density is J = ρe v. When both are equal, ρe v = σE. To get E, put σ = 20, ρe = 2.4 and v = 10, E = 2.4 x 10/20 = 1.2 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "7.\tFind the mobility of the electrons when the drift velocity is 23 units and the electric field is 11 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.1",
            "b)\t2.2",
            "c)\t3.2",
            "d)\t0.9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The mobility is defined as the drift velocity per unit electric field. Thus μe = vd/E = 23/11 = 2.1 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the resistance of a cylinder of area 200 units and length 100m with conductivity of 12 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1/24",
            "b)\t1/48",
            "c)\t1/12",
            "d)\t1/96"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resistance is given by R = ρL/A = L/σA. Put L = 100, σ = 12 and A = 200, we get R = 100/(12 x 200) = 1/24 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "9.\tCalculate the potential when a conductor of length 2m is having an electric field of 12.3units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t26.4",
            "b)\t42.6",
            "c)\t64.2",
            "d)\t24.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The electric field is given by E = V/L. To get V, put E = 12.3 and L = 2.Thus we get V = E x L = 12.3 x 2 = 24.6 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "1.\tThe charge within a conductor will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t-1",
            "c)\t0",
            "d)\t∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: No charges exist in a conductor. An illustration for this statement is that, it is safer to stay inside a car rather than standing under a tree during lightning. Since the car has a metal body, no charges will be possessed by it to get ionized by the lightning."
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "2.\tFor a conservative field which of the following equations holds good?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t∫ E.dl = 0",
            "b)\t∫ H.dl = 0",
            "c)\t∫ B.dl = 0",
            "d)\t∫ D.dl = 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A conservative field implies the work done in a closed path will be zero. This is given by ∫ E.dl = 0."
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "3.\tFind the electric field if the surface density at the boundary of air is 10-9.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t12π",
            "b)\t24π",
            "c)\t36π",
            "d)\t48π"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is the conductor-free space boundary. At the boundary, E = ρ/εo. Put ρ = 10-9 and εo = 10-9/36π. We get E = 36π units."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the flux density at the boundary when the charge density is given by 24 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t12",
            "b)\t24",
            "c)\t48",
            "d)\t96"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At the boundary of a conductor- free space interface, the flux density is equal to the charge density. Thus D = ρv = 24 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "5.\tWhich component of the electric field intensity is always continuous at the boundary?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTangential",
            "b)\tNormal",
            "c)\tHorizontal",
            "d)\tVertical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At the boundary of the dielectric-dielectric, the tangential component of the electric field intensity is always continuous. We get Et1 = Et2."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "6.\tThe normal component of which quantity is always discontinuous at the boundary?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tE",
            "b)\tD",
            "c)\tH",
            "d)\tB"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The normal component of an electric flux density is always discontinuous at the boundary for a dielectric-dielectric boundary. We get Dn1 = Dn2, when we assume the free surface charge exists at the interface."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "7.\t The electric flux density of a surface with permittivity of 2 is given by 12 units. What the flux density of the surface in air?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t24",
            "b)\t6",
            "c)\t1/6",
            "d)\t0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The relation between electric field and permittivity is given by Dt1/Dt2 = ε1/ε2. Put Dt1 = 12, ε1 = 2 and ε2 =1, we get Dt2 = 12 x 1/ 2 = 6 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "8.\tThe electric field intensity of a surface with permittivity 3.5 is given by 18 units. What the field intensity of the surface in air?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t5.14",
            "b)\t0.194",
            "c)\t63",
            "d)\t29"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The relation between flux density and permittivity is given by En1/En2 = ε2/ ε1. Put En1 = 18, ε1 = 3.5 and ε2 = 1. We get En2 = 18 x 3.5 = 63 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "9.\tA wave incident on a surface at an angle 60 degree is having field intensity of 6 units. The reflected wave is at an angle of 30 degree. Find the field intensity after reflection.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t9.4",
            "b)\t8.4",
            "c)\t10.4",
            "d)\t7.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: By Snell’s law, the relation between incident and reflected waves is given by, E1 sin θ1 = E2 sin θ2. Thus 6 sin 60 = E2 sin 30. We get E2 = 6 x 1.732 = 10.4 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "10.\tFind the permittivity of the surface when a wave incident at an angle 60 is reflected by the surface at 45 in air.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.41",
            "b)\t3.5",
            "c)\t2.2",
            "d)\t1.73"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: From the relations of the boundary conditions of a dielectric-dielectric interface, we get tan θ1/tan θ2 = ε1/ε2. Thus tan 60/tan 45 = ε1/1. We get ε1 = tan 60 = 1.73."
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Options": [
            "1.\tThe given equation satisfies the Laplace equation.",
            "V = x2 + y2 – z2. State True/False.",
            "a)\tTrue",
            "b)\tFalse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Grad (V) = 2xi + 2yj – 4zk. Div (Grad (V)) = Del2(V) = 2+2-4 = 0. It satisfies the Laplacian equation. Thus the statement is true."
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "2.\tIn free space, the Poisson equation becomes",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMaxwell equation",
            "b)\tAmpere equation",
            "c)\tLaplace equation",
            "d)\tSteady state equation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Poisson equation is given by Del2(V) = -ρ/ε. In free space, the charges will be zero. Thus the equation becomes, Del2(V) = 0, which is the Laplace equation."
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "3.\tIf Laplace equation satisfies, then which of the following statements will be true?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPotential will be zero",
            "b)\tCurrent will be infinite",
            "c)\tResistance will be infinite",
            "d)\tVoltage will be same"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Laplace equation satisfying implies the potential is not necessarily zero due to subsequent gradient and divergence operations following. Finally, if potential is assumed to be zero, then resistance is zero and current will be infinite."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "4.\tSuppose the potential function is a step function. The equation that gets satisfied is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLaplace equation",
            "b)\tPoisson equation",
            "c)\tMaxwell equation",
            "d)\tAmpere equation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Step is a constant function. The Laplace equation Div(Grad(step)) will become zero. This is because gradient of a constant is zero and divergence of zero vector will be zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "5.\tCalculate the charge density when a potential function x2 + y2 + z2 is in air(in 10-9 order)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1/6π",
            "b)\t6/2π",
            "c)\t12/6π",
            "d)\t10/8π"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Poisson equation is given by Del2(V) = -ρ/ε. To find ρ, put ε = 8.854 x 10-12 in air and Laplacian of the function is 2 + 2 + 2 = 6. Ρ = 6 x 10-9/36π = 1/6π units."
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "7.\tPoisson equation can be derived from which of the following equations?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPoint form of Gauss law",
            "b)\tIntegral form of Gauss law",
            "c)\tPoint form of Ampere law",
            "d)\tIntegral form of Ampere law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Grad (V) = exsin y i + ex cos y j + k. Div(Grad(V)) = exsin y – exsin y + 0= 0.Thus Laplacian equation Div(Grad(V)) = 0 is true."
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the charge density from the function of flux density given by 12x – 7z.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t19",
            "b)\t-5",
            "c)\t5",
            "d)\t-19"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The point of Gauss law is given by, Div (D)= ρv. On putting\nD= ε E and E=- Grad (V) in Gauss law, we get Del2 (V)= -ρ/ε, which is the Poisson equation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "9.\tFind the electric field of a potential function given by 20 log x + y at the point (1,1,0).",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t-20 i – j",
            "b)\t-i -20 j",
            "c)\ti + j",
            "d)\t(i + j)/20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: From point form of Gauss law, we get Div (D) = ρv\nDiv (D) = Div(12x – 7z) = 12-7 = 5, which the charge density ρv. Thus ρv = 5 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "10.\t When a material has zero permittivity, the maximum potential that it can possess is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t∞",
            "b)\t-∞",
            "c)\tUnity",
            "d)\tZero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The electric field is given by E = -Grad(V). The gradient of the given function is 20i/x + j. At the point (1,1,0), we get 20i + j. The electric field E = -(20i + j) = -20i – j."
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "1.\tFind the resistivity of a material having resistance 20kohm, area 2 units and length of 12m.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t6666.6",
            "b)\t3333.3",
            "c)\t1200",
            "d)\t2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The resistance of a material is given by R = ρL/A. To get ρ, put R = 20 x 103, A = 2 and L = 12. We get ρ = 3333.3 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "2.\tA resistor value of colour code orange violet orange will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t37 kohm",
            "b)\t37 Mohm",
            "c)\t48 kohm",
            "d)\t48 Mohm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Orange refers to number 3. Violet refers to number 7. The third colour code orange refers to 103. Thus the resistor value will be 37 kilo ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "3.\tA infinite resistance is considered as a/an",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tClosed path(short circuit)",
            "b)\tOpen path",
            "c)\tNot defined",
            "d)\tAmmeter with zero reading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:b\nExplanation: When there exists infinite resistance in a path, the current flowing will ideally be zero. This is possible only for an open path/circuit."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the time constant in a series R-L circuit when the resistance is 4 ohm and the inductance is 2 H.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.25",
            "b)\t0.2",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t0.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The time constant for an R-L series circuit will be τ = L/R. Put R = 4 and L = 2. We get τ = 2/4 = 0.5 second."
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "5.\tFind the time constant for a R-C circuit for resistance R = 24 kohm and C = 16 microfarad.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.5 millisecond",
            "b)\t0.6 nanosecond",
            "c)\t384 millisecond",
            "d)\t384 microsecond"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The time constant for R-C circuit is τ = RC. Put R = 24 kilo ohm and C = 16 micro farad. We get τ = 24 x 103 x 16 x 10-6 = 0.384 = 384 millisecond."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "6.\tFind the capacitance when charge is 20 C has a voltage of 1.2V.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t32.67",
            "b)\t16.67",
            "c)\t6.67",
            "d)\t12.33"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Capacitance is related to Q and V as C = Q/V. Put C = 20C and V = 1.2V, we get Q = 20/1.2 = 16.67 farad. "
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "7.\tCalculate the capacitance of two parallel plates of area 2 units separated by a distance of 0.2m in air(in picofarad)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t8.84",
            "b)\t88.4",
            "c)\t884.1",
            "d)\t0.884"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Capacitance is given by, C = εo A/d. Put A = 2, d = 0.2, εo = 8.854 x 10-12, we get C = 8.841 x 10-11 = 88. 41 pF."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "8.\tCompute the capacitance between two concentric shells of inner radius 2m and the outer radius is infinitely large.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.111 nF",
            "b)\t0.222 nF",
            "c)\t4.5 nF",
            "d)\t5.4 nF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The concentric shell with infinite outer radius is considered to be an isolated sphere. The capacitance C = 4πε/(1/a – 1/b). If b->∞, then C = 4πεa. Put a = 2m, we get C = 4π x 8.854 x 10-12 x 2 = 0.222 nF."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "9.\tThe capacitance of a material refers to",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAbility of the material to store magnetic field",
            "b)\tAbility of the material to store electromagnetic field",
            "c)\tAbility of the material to store electric field",
            "d)\tPotential between two charged plates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The capacitance of a material is a measure of the ability of the material to store electric field. It is the ratio of charge stored to the voltage across the parallel plates."
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "10.\t A cable of core radius 1.25cm and impregnated paper insulation of thickness 2.13cm and relative permittivity 3.5. Compute the capacitance of the cable/km(in nF)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t195.7",
            "b)\t179.5",
            "c)\t157.9",
            "d)\t197.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Capacitance between coaxial cylinders of inner radius 1.25cm and outer radius 1.25 + 2.13 = 3.38cm will be C = 2πεL/ ln(b/a). Put b = 3.38, a = 1.25 and L = 1000m, we get C = 1.957 x 10-7 = 195.7 nF."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "1.\tIdentify the advantage of using method of images.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tEasy approach",
            "b)\tBoundaries are replaced by charges",
            "c)\tBoundaries are replaced by images",
            "d)\tCalculation using Poisson and Laplace equation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electrostatic boundary value problems are difficult if Poisson and Laplace equation is solved directly. But method of images helps us to solve problems without the equations. This is done by replacing boundary surfaces with appropriate image charges."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "2.\tCalculate the electric field intensity of a line charge of length 2m and potential 24V.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t24",
            "b)\t12",
            "c)\t0.083",
            "d)\t12.67"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The electric field intensity is given by the ratio of potential to distance or length. E = V/d = 24/2 = 12 V/m."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "3.\tCalculate potential of a metal plate of charge 28C and capacitance 12 mF.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3.33 kohm",
            "b)\t2.33 kohm",
            "c)\t3.33 Mohm",
            "d)\t2.33 Mohm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Potential is given by V = Q/C. Put Q = 28C and C = 12 mF. We get V = 28/12 x 10-3 = 2.333 x 103 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the dissipation factor when series resistance is 5 ohm and capacitive resistance is 10 unit.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t0.5",
            "c)\t1",
            "d)\t0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The dissipation factor is nothing but the tangent of loss angle of loss tangent. Tan δ = Series resistance/Capacitive resistance = 5/10 = 0.5. "
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "5.\tA material with zero resistivity is said to have",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tZero conductance",
            "b)\tInfinite conductance",
            "c)\tZero resistance",
            "d)\tInfinite resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Since resistivity is directly proportional to the resistance, when the resistivity is zero, resistance is also zero. Thus we get zero resistance. The option infinite conductance is also possible ideally, but it is not possible practically. As there is always some loss in the form of heat, thus infinite conductance is impossible, but a short circuit (zero resistance) is practically possible."
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "6.\tFind the energy stored by the capacitor 3F having a potential of 12V across it.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t432",
            "b)\t108",
            "c)\t216",
            "d)\t54"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The energy stored in a capacitor is given by, E = 0.5 CV2.\nE = 0.5 x 3 x 122 = 0.5 x 432 = 216 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "7.\tBy method of images, the problem can be easily calculated by replacing the boundary with which polygon?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRectangle",
            "b)\tTrapezoid",
            "c)\tSquare",
            "d)\tTriangle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When any field or potential needs to be calculated for either line charge or coaxial cable or concentric cylinder, the method of images uses a triangle which converts the three dimensional problem to one dimensional analysis. From this, the result can be calculated. "
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "8.\tCalculate the electric field due to a surface charge of 20 units on a plate in air(in 1012 order)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2.19",
            "b)\t1.12",
            "c)\t9.21",
            "d)\t2.91"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The electric field due to plate of charge will be E = ρs/2εo. Put ρs = 20, we get E = 20/(2 x 8.854 x 10-12) = 1.129 x 1012 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "9.\tFind the electric field due to charge density of 1/18 and distance from a point P is 0.5 in air(in 109 order)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The electric field for this case is given by, E = ρl/2πεd. Put ρl = 1/18 and d = 0.5. We get E = 2 x 109 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "10.\t Find the total capacitances when two capacitors 2F and 5F are in series.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t5/7",
            "b)\t12/7",
            "c)\t2/5",
            "d)\t10/7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Two capacitances in series gives C = C1C2/C1 + C2 = 2 x 5/2 + 5 = 10/7 farad."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "1.\tBiot Savart law in magnetic field is analogous to which law in electric field?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGauss law",
            "b)\tFaraday law",
            "c)\tCoulomb’s law",
            "d)\tAmpere law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Biot Savart law states that the magnetic flux density H = I.dl sinθ/4πr2, which is analogous to the electric field F = q1q2/4πεr2, which is the Coulomb’s law."
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "2.\tWhich of the following cannot be computed using the Biot Savart law?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMagnetic field intensity",
            "b)\tMagnetic flux density",
            "c)\tElectric field intensity",
            "d)\tPermeability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Biot Savart law is used to calculate magnetic field intensity. Using which we can calculate flux density and permeability by the formula B = μH."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "3.\tFind the magnetic field of a finite current element with 2A current and height 1/2π is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t2",
            "c)\t1/2",
            "d)\t1/4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The magnetic field due to a finite current element is given by H = I/2πh. Put I = 2 and h = 1/2π, we get H = 1 unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "4.\tCalculate the magnetic field at a point on the centre of the circular conductor of radius 2m with current 8A.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t2",
            "c)\t3",
            "d)\t4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The magnetic field due to a point in the centre of the circular conductor is given by H = I/2a. Put I = 8A and a = 2m, we get H = 8/4 = 2 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "5.\tThe current element of the solenoid of turns 100, length 2m and current 0.5A is given by,",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t100 dx",
            "b)\t200 dx",
            "c)\t25 dx",
            "d)\t50 dx"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The current element of the solenoid is given by NI dx/L. Put N = 100, I = 0.5 and L = 2 to get, I dx = 100 x 0.5 x dx/2 = 25 dx."
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "6.\tFind the magnetic field intensity at the centre O of a square of the sides equal to 5m and carrying 10A of current.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.2",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t1.6",
            "d)\t1.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The magnetic field is given by H = 4I/√2πω. Put I = 10 and ω = 5m. Thus H = 4 x 10/√2π(5) = 1.8 unit. "
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "7.\tFind the magnetic flux density when a point from a finite current length element of current 0.5A and radius 100nm.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t0.5",
            "c)\t1",
            "d)\t2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The magnetic flux density is B = μH, where H is given by I/2πr. Put μ = 4π x 10-7, I = 0.5 and r = 10-7, we get B = 4π x 10-7 x 0.5/2π x 10-7 = 1 unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "10.\t Find the magnetic field when a circular conductor of very high radius is subjected to a current of 12A and the point P is at the centre of the conductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t∞",
            "c)\t0",
            "d)\t-∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From Gauss law for magnetic field, we get divergence of the magnetic flux density is always zero (ie, Div(B) = 0). This implies the non-existence of magnetic monopole."
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "1.\tFor time varying currents, the field or waves will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tElectrostatic",
            "b)\tMagneto static",
            "c)\tElectromagnetic",
            "d)\tElectrical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For stationary charges, the field is electrostatic. For steady currents, the field is magneto static. But for time varying currents, the field or waves will be electromagnetic."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "2.\tAccording to Faraday’s law, EMF stands for",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tElectromagnetic field",
            "b)\tElectromagnetic force",
            "c)\tElectromagnetic friction",
            "d)\tElectromotive force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The force in any closed circuit due to the change in the flux linkage of the circuit is called as electromotive force EMF. This phenomenon is called as Faraday’s law."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "3.\tCalculate the emf when the flux is given by 3sin t + 5cos t",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3cos t – 5sin t",
            "b)\t-3cos t + 5sin t",
            "c)\t-3sin t – 5cos t",
            "d)\t3cos t + 5sin t"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The electromotive force is given by Vemf = -dλ/dt. Thus Vemf = -dλ/dt = -(3cos t – 5sin t) = -3cos t + 5sin t."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "5.\tCalculate the emf when a coil of 100 turns is subjected to a flux rate of 0.3 tesla/sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3",
            "b)\t30",
            "c)\t-30",
            "d)\t-300"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to Lenz law, the induced voltage acts in such a way that it opposes the flux producing it. This is indicated by a negative sign."
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "6.\tFind the displacement current when the flux density is given by t3 at 2 seconds.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3",
            "b)\t6",
            "c)\t12",
            "d)\t27"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The induced emf is given by Vemf = -dλ/dt = -Ndψ/dt. Thus emf will be -100 x 0.3 = -30 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "7.\tFind the force due to a current element of length 2cm and flux density of 12 tesla. The current through the element will be 5A.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1 N",
            "b)\t1.2 N",
            "c)\t1.4 N",
            "d)\t1.6 N"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The displacement current is given by Jd = dD/dt. Thus Jd = 3t2. At time t = 2, we get Jd = 3(2)2= 12A."
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "8.\tWhich of the following statements is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tE is the cross product of v and B",
            "b)\tB is the cross product of v and E",
            "c)\tE is the dot product of v and B",
            "d)\tB is the dot product of v and E"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The force due to a current element is given by F = BI x L. Thus F = 12 x 5 x 0.02 = 1.2 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "10.\tWhen the conduction current density and displacement current density are same, the dissipation factor will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tZero",
            "b)\tMinimum",
            "c)\tMaximum",
            "d)\tUnity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The electric field is the cross product of the velocity and the magnetic field intensity. This is given by Lorentz equation."
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "1.\tThe point form of Ampere law is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCurl(B) = I",
            "b)\tCurl(D) = J",
            "c)\tCurl(V) = I",
            "d)\tCurl(H) = J"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ampere law states that the line integral of H about any closed path is exactly equal to the direct current enclosed by that path. ∫ H.dl = I The point form will be Curl (H) = J."
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "2.\tThe Ampere law is based on which theorem?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGreen’s theorem",
            "b)\tGauss divergence theorem",
            "c)\tStoke’s theorem",
            "d)\tMaxwell theorem"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The proof of the Ampere’s circuital law is obtained from Stoke’s theorem for H and J only."
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the magnetic flux density of a finite length conductor of radius 12cm and current 3A in air( in 10-6 order)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t4",
            "b)\t5",
            "c)\t6",
            "d)\t7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At the conductor-free space boundary, electric field will be maximum and magnetic field will be minimum. This implies electric field is zero inside the conductor and increases as the radius increases and the magnetic field is zero outside the conductor and decreases as it approaches the conductor."
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "5.\tCalculate the magnetic field intensity due to a toroid of turns 50, current 2A and radius 159mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t50",
            "b)\t75",
            "c)\t100",
            "d)\t200"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The magnetic field intensity is given by H = I/2πr, where I = 3A and r = 0.12. The magnetic flux density in air B = μ H, where μ = 4π x 10-7.Thus B = 4π x 10-7 x 3/2π x 0.12 = 5x 10-6 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "6.\tFind the magnetic field intensity due to an infinite sheet of current 5A and charge density of 12j units in the positive y direction and the z component is above the sheet.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t-6",
            "b)\t12k",
            "c)\t60",
            "d)\t6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The magnetic field intensity is given by H = NI/2πrm, where N = 50, I = 2A and rm = 1/2π. Thus H = 50 x 2/2π x 0.159 = 100 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "7.\tFind the magnetic field intensity due to an infinite sheet of current 5A and charge density of 12j units in the positive y direction and the z component is below the sheet.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t6",
            "b)\t0",
            "c)\t-6",
            "d)\t60k"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The magnetic field intensity when the normal component is above the sheet is Hx = 0.5 K, where K = 12. Thus we get H = 0.5 x 12 = 6 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the current density on the conductor surface when a magnetic field H = 3cos x i + zcos x j A/m, for z>0 and zero, otherwise is applied to a perfectly conducting surface in xy plane.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tcos x i",
            "b)\t–cos x i",
            "c)\tcos x j",
            "d)\t–cos x j"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The magnetic intensity when the normal component is below the sheet is Hy = -0.5 K, where K = 12.Thus we get H = -0.5 x 12 = -6 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "9.\tWhen the rotational path of the magnetic field intensity is zero, then the current in the path will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t0",
            "c)\t∞",
            "d)\t0.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: By Ampere law, Curl (H) = J. The curl of H will be i(-cos x) – j(0) + k(-z sin x) = -cos x i – zsin x k. In the xy plane, z = 0. Thus Curl(H) = J = -cos x i."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "10.\tFind the magnetic field intensity when the current density is 0.5 units for an area up to 20 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t10",
            "b)\t5",
            "c)\t20",
            "d)\t40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: By Ampere law, Curl(H) = J. The rotational path of H is zero, implies the curl of H is zero. This shows the current density J is also zero. The current is the product of the current density and area, which is also zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "1.\tThe divergence of which quantity will be zero?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tE",
            "b)\tD",
            "c)\tH",
            "d)\tB"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The divergence of the magnetic flux density is always zero. This is because of the non existence of magnetic monopoles in a magnetic field."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "2.\tFind the charge density when the electric flux density is given by 2x i + 3y j + 4z k.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t10",
            "b)\t9",
            "c)\t24",
            "d)\t0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The charge density is the divergence of the electric flux density by Maxwell’s equation. Thus ρ = Div (D) and Div (D) = 2 + 3 + 4 = 9. We get ρ = 9 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "3.\tFind the Maxwell equation derived from Faraday’s law.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDiv(H) = J",
            "b)\tDiv(D) = I",
            "c)\tCurl(E) = -dB/dt",
            "d)\tCurl(B) = -dH/dt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: From the Faraday’s law and Lenz law, using Stoke’s theorem, we get Curl(E) = -dB/dt. This is the Maxwell’s first law of electromagnetics."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the Maxwell law derived from Ampere law.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDiv(I) = H",
            "b)\tDiv(H) = J",
            "c)\tCurl(H) = J",
            "d)\tCurl(B) = D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: From the current density definition and Ohm’s law, the Ampere circuital law Curl(H) = J can be derived. This is Maxwell’s second law of electromagnetics."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "5.\tThe Faraday’s law states about which type of EMF?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTransformer EMF",
            "b)\tBack EMF",
            "c)\tGenerator EMF",
            "d)\tSecondary EMF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The stationary loop in a varying magnetic field results in an induced emf due to the change in the flux linkage of the loop. This emf is called as induced or transformer EMF."
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "6.\tIn which of the following forms can Maxwell’s equation not be represented?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tStatic",
            "b)\tDifferential",
            "c)\tIntegral",
            "d)\tHarmonic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maxwell equations can be represented in differential/point form and integral form alternatively. Sometimes, it can be represented by time varying fields called harmonic form."
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "7.\tThe charge build up in the capacitor is due to which quantity?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConduction current",
            "b)\tDisplacement current",
            "c)\tConvection current",
            "d)\tDirect current"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The charge in the capacitor is due to displacement current. It is the current in the presence of the dielectric placed between two parallel metal plates."
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "8.\tIn metals which of the following equation will hold good?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCurl(H) = J",
            "b)\tCurl(J) = dD/dt",
            "c)\tCurl(H) = D",
            "d)\tCurl(J) = dB/dt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Generally, the Curl(H) is the sum of two currents- conduction and displacement. In case of metals, it constitutes conduction J and in case of dielectrics, it constitutes the displacement current dD/dt. "
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "9.\tFind the flux enclosed by a material of flux density 12 units in an area of 80cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t9.6",
            "b)\t12/80",
            "c)\t80/12",
            "d)\t12/0.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The total flux in a material is the product of the flux density and the area. It is given by flux = 12 x 0.8= 9.6 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "10.\tFind the electric flux density of a material with charge density 16 units in unit volume.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1/16",
            "b)\t16t",
            "c)\t16",
            "d)\t162"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The electric flux density from Maxwell’s equation is given by D = ∫ ρ dv. On substituting ρ = 16 and ∫dv = 1, we get D = 16 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "1.\tThe H quantity is analogous to which component in the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tB",
            "b)\tD",
            "c)\tE",
            "d)\tV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The H quantity refers to magnetic field intensity in the magnetic field. This is analogous to the electric field intensity E in the electric field."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "3.\tAmpere law states that,",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDivergence of H is same as the flux",
            "b)\tCurl of D is same as the current",
            "c)\tDivergence of E is zero",
            "d)\tCurl of H is same as the current density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The magnetic field intensity is directly proportional to the magnetic field intensity for a particular material (Permeability). It is given by B = μH."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "4.\tGiven the magnetic field is 2.4 units. Find the flux density in air(in 10-6 order).",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t3",
            "c)\t4",
            "d)\t5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ampere circuital law or Ampere law states that the closed integral of the magnetic field intensity is same as the current enclosed by it. It is given by Curl(H) = J."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "5.\tFind the electric field when the magnetic field is given by 2sin t in air.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t8π x 10-7 cos t",
            "b)\t4π x 10-7 sin t",
            "c)\t-8π x 10-7 cos t",
            "d)\t-4π x 10-7 sin t"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: We know that B = μH. On substituting μ = 4π x 10-7 and H = 2.4, we get B = 4π x 10-7 x 2.4 = 3 x 10-6 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "6.\tFind the height of an infinitely long conductor from point P which is carrying current of 6.28A and field intensity is 0.5 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.5",
            "b)\t2",
            "c)\t6.28",
            "d)\t1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Given H = 2sin t. We get B = μH = 4π x 10-7 x 2sin t = 8πx10-7sin t.\nTo get E, integrate B with respect to time, we get 8πx10-7cos t."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "7.\tFind the magnetic field intensity due to a solenoid of length 12cm having 30 turns and current of 1.5A.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t250",
            "b)\t325",
            "c)\t175",
            "d)\t375"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The magnetic field intensity of an infinitely long conductor is given by H = I/2πh. Put I = 6.28 and H = 0.5, we get h = 1/0.5 = 2 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the magnetic field intensity at the radius of 6cm of a coaxial cable with inner and outer radii are 1.5cm and 4cm respectively. The current flowing is 2A.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2.73",
            "b)\t3.5",
            "c)\t0",
            "d)\t1.25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The magnetic field intensity of a solenoid is given by H = NI/L = 30 X 1.5/0.12 = 375 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "9.\tFind the magnetic field intensity of a toroid of turns 40 and radius 20cm. The current carried by the toroid be 3.25A.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t103.45",
            "b)\t102",
            "c)\t105.7",
            "d)\t171"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The inner radius is 1.5cm and the outer radius is 4cm. It is clear that the magnetic field intensity needs to be calculated outside of the conductor ie, r>4cm. This will lead to zero, since H outside the conductor will be zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "10.\t The magnetic field intensity of an infinite sheet of charge with charge density 36.5 units in air will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t18.25",
            "b)\t11.25",
            "c)\t73",
            "d)\t1/36.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The magnetic field intensity of a toroid is given by H = NI/2πrm. Put N = 40, I = 3.25 and rm = 0.2, we get H = 40 x 3.25/2π x 0.2 = 103.45 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "1.\tIdentify which of the following is the unit of magnetic flux density?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tWeber",
            "b)\tWeber/m",
            "c)\tTesla",
            "d)\tWeber-1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The unit of magnetic flux density is weber/m2. It is also called as tesla."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "2.\tThe divergence of H will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t-1",
            "c)\t∞",
            "d)\t0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: We know that the divergence of B is zero. Also B = μH. Thus divergence of H is also zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "3.\tFind the flux contained by the material when the flux density is 11.7 Tesla and the area is 2 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t23.4",
            "b)\t12.3",
            "c)\t32.4",
            "d)\t21.3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The total flux is given by φ = ∫ B.ds, where ∫ds is the area. Thus φ = BA. We get φ = 11.7 x 2 = 23.4 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the current when the magnetic field intensity is given by 2L and L varies as 0->1.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t0.5",
            "d)\t0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From Ampere law, we get ∫ H.dL = I. Put H = 2L and L = 0->1. On integrating H with respect to L, the current will be 1A."
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "5.\tFind the magnetic field intensity when the flux density is 8 x 10-6 Tesla in the medium of air.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t6.36",
            "b)\t3.66",
            "c)\t6.63",
            "d)\t3.36"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We how that, B = μH. To get H = B/μ, put B = 8 x 10-6 and μ = 4π x 10-7. Thus H = 8 x 10-6/ 4π x 10-7 = 6.36 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "6.\tIf ∫ H.dL = 0, then which statement will be true?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tE = -Grad(V)",
            "b)\tB = -Grad(D)",
            "c)\tH = -Grad(Vm)",
            "d)\tD = -Grad(A)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The given condition shows that the magnetic field intensity will be the negative gradient of the magnetic vector potential."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "7.\tFind the magnetic flux density of the material with magnetic vector potential A = y i + z j + x k.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\ti + j + k",
            "b)\t–i – j – k",
            "c)\t–i-j",
            "d)\t–i-k"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The magnetic flux density is the curl of the magnetic vector potential. B = Curl(A). Thus Curl(A) = i(-1) – j(1) + k(-1) = -i – j – k. We get B = -i – j – k."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the magnetic flux density when a flux of 28 units is enclosed in an area of 15cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t178.33",
            "b)\t186.67",
            "c)\t192.67",
            "d)\t124.33"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The total flux is the product of the magnetic flux density and the area. Total flux = B x A. To get B, put flux/area. B = 28/0.15 = 186.67 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "9.\tFind the magnetic flux density B when E is given by 3sin y i + 4cos z j + ex k.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t∫(4sin z i – ex j – 3cos y k)dt",
            "b)\t-∫(4sin z i – ex j – 3cos y k)dt",
            "c)\t∫(4sin y i – ex j + 3cos y k)dt",
            "d)\t-∫(4sin y i + ex j + 3cos y k)dt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  We know that Curl (E) = -dB/dt. The curl of E is (4sin z i – ex j – 3cos y k). To get B, integrate the -curl(E) with respect to time to get B = -∫(4sin z i – ex j – 3cos y k)dt."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "10.\t Find current density J when B = 50 x 10-6 units and area dS is 4 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t9.94",
            "b)\t8.97",
            "c)\t7.92",
            "d)\t10.21"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: To get H, H = B/μ = 50 x 10-6/ 4π x 10-7 = 39.78 units. Also H = ∫ J.dS, where H = 39.78 and ∫ dS = 4. Thus J = 39.78/4 = 9.94 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "2.\tFind the magnetic field intensity when the magnetic vector potential x i + 2y j + 3z k.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t6",
            "b)\t-6",
            "c)\t0",
            "d)\t1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The magnetic vector potential could be learnt as a scalar. But it is actually a vector quantity, which means it has both magnitude and direction."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "3.\tThe value of ∫ H.dL will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tJ",
            "b)\tI",
            "c)\tB",
            "d)\tH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The magnetic field intensity is given by H = -Grad(Vm). The gradient of Vm is 1 + 2 + 3 = 6. Thus H = -6 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "4.\tGiven the vector potential is 16 – 12sin y j. Find the field intensity at the origin.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t28",
            "b)\t16",
            "c)\t12",
            "d)\t4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: By Stoke’s theorem, ∫ H.dL = ∫ Curl(H).dS and from Ampere’s law, Curl(H) = J. Thus ∫ H.dL = ∫ J.dS which is nothing but current I."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "5.\tFind the vector potential when the field intensity 60x2 varies from (0,0,0) to (1,0,0).",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t120",
            "b)\t-20",
            "c)\t-180",
            "d)\t60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The field intensity is given by H = – Grad(V). The gradient is given by 0 – 12cos y. At the origin, the gradient will be -12 cos 0 = -12. Thus the field intensity will be 12 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "6.\tFind the flux density B when the potential is given by x i + y j + z k in air.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t12π x 10-7",
            "b)\t-12π x 10-7",
            "c)\t6π x 10-7",
            "d)\t-6π x 10-7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The field intensity H = -Grad(V). To get V, integrate H with respect to the variable. Thus V = -∫H.dl = -∫60x2 dx = -20x3 as x = 0->1 to get -20."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "7.\t The Laplacian of the magnetic vector potential will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t–μ J",
            "b)\t– μ I",
            "c)\t–μ B",
            "d)\t–μ H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The field intensity H = -Grad(V). Since the given potential is a position vector, the gradient will be 3 and H = -3. Thus the flux density B = μH = 4π x 10-7 x (-3) = -12π x 10-7 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "8.\tThe magnetic vector potential for a line current will be inversely proportional to",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tdL",
            "b)\tI",
            "c)\tJ",
            "d)\tR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Laplacian of the magnetic vector potential is given by Del2(A) = -μ J, where μ is the permeability and J is the current density."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "9.\tThe current element of the magnetic vector potential for a surface current will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tJ dS",
            "b)\tI dL",
            "c)\tK dS",
            "d)\tJ dV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The magnetic vector potential for the line integral will be A = ∫ μIdL/4πR. It is clear that the potential is inversely proportional to the distance or radius R."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "10.\t The relation between flux density and vector potential is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tB = Curl(A)",
            "b)\tA = Curl(B)",
            "c)\tB = Div(A)",
            "d)\tA = Div(B)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The magnetic vector potential for the surface integral is given by A = ∫ μKdS/4πR. It is clear that the current element is K dS."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "1.\tFind the induced EMF in an inductor of 2mH and the current rate is 2000 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t4",
            "b)\t-4",
            "c)\t1",
            "d)\t-1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The induced emf is given by e = -Ldi/dt. Put L = 2 x 10-3 and di/dt = 2000 in the equation. We get e = -2 x 10-3 x 2000 = -4 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "2.\tFind the work done in an inductor of 4H when a current 8A is passed through it?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t256",
            "b)\t128",
            "c)\t64",
            "d)\t512"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The work done in the inductor will be W = 0.5 x LI2. On substituting L = 4 and I = 8, we get, W = 0.5 x 4 x 82 = 128 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "3.\tFind the inductance of a material with 100 turns, area 12 units and current of 2A in air.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.75mH",
            "b)\t7.5mH",
            "c)\t75mH",
            "d)\t753mH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The inductance of any material(coil) is given by L = μ N2A/I. On substituting N = 100, A = 0.12 and I = 2, we get L = 4π x 10-7 x 1002 x 0.12/2 = 0.75 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "4.\tCalculate the magnetic energy when the magnetic intensity in air is given as 14.2 units(in 10-4 order)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.26",
            "b)\t2.61",
            "c)\t6.12",
            "d)\t1.62"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The magnetic energy is given by E = 0.5 μ H2. Put H = 14.2 and in air μ = 4π x 10-7, we get E = 0.5 x 4π x 10-7 x 14.22 = 1.26 x 10-4 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "5.\tCalculate the magnetic energy when the magnetic flux density is given by 32 units(in 108 order)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t4.07",
            "b)\t7.4",
            "c)\t0.47",
            "d)\t7.04"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The magnetic energy is given by E = 0.5 μ H2 and we know that μH = B. On substituting we get a formula E = 0.5 B2/μ. Put B = 32 and in air μ = 4π x 10-7, we get E = 0.5 x 322/4π x 10-7 = 4.07 x 108 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "6.\tCalculate the energy when the magnetic intensity and magnetic flux density are 15 and 65 respectively.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t755",
            "b)\t487.5",
            "c)\t922",
            "d)\t645"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The magnetic energy can also be written as E = 0.5 μH2 = 0.5 BH, since B = μH. On substituting B = 65 and H = 15 we get E = 0.5 x 65 x 15 = 487.5 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "7.\tFind the inductance when the energy is given by 2 units with a current of 16A.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t15.6mH",
            "b)\t16.5mH",
            "c)\t16.8mH",
            "d)\t15.8mH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The energy stored in an inductor is given by E = 0.5 LI2. To get L, put E = 2 and I = 16 and thus L = 2E/I2 = 2 x 2/162 = 15.6mH."
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the power of an inductor of 5H and current 4.5A after 2 seconds.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t25.31",
            "b)\t50.62",
            "c)\t102.4",
            "d)\t204.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The energy stored in an inductor is given by E = 0.5 LI2. Thus, put L = 5 and I = 4.5 and we get E = 0.5 x 5 x 4.52 = 50.625 units To get power P = E/t = 50.625/2 = 25.31 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "9.\tFind the turns in an solenoid of inductance 23.4mH , current 2A and area 15cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t900",
            "b)\t400",
            "c)\t498",
            "d)\t658"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The inductance of any material(coil) is given by L = μ N2A/I.\nPut L = 23.4 x 10-3, I = 2 and A = 0.15, we get N as 498 turns."
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "1.\tThe magnetostatics highly relies on which property?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tResistance",
            "b)\tCapacitance",
            "c)\tInductance",
            "d)\tMoment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The magnetostatics highly relies on the inductance of the magnetic materials, which decides its behavior in the influence of magnetic field."
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "2.\tThe inductance is the measure of",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tElectric charges stored by the material",
            "b)\tEmf generated by energising the coil",
            "c)\tMagnetic field stored by the material",
            "d)\tMagnetization of dipoles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The inductance is a property of an electric conductor/coil which measures the amount of emf generated by passing current through the coil."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "3.\tFind the total flux in a coil of magnetic flux density 12 units and area 7 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.84",
            "b)\t0.96",
            "c)\t8.4",
            "d)\t9.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The total flux in a coil is defined by φ = BA, where B = 12 and A = 0.07. On substituting these values, we get φ = 12 x 0.07 = 0.84 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the energy of a coil of inductance 18mH and current passing through it 1.25A.(in 10-3 order)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t14.06",
            "b)\t61",
            "c)\t46.1",
            "d)\t28.12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The magnetic energy possessed by a coil is given by E = 0.5 x LI2. Put L = 18 x 10-3 and I = 1.25, thus we get E = 0.5 x 18 x 10-3 x 1.252 = 14.06 x 10-3 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "5.\tUsing Maxwell equation which of the following cannot be calculated directly?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tB",
            "b)\tD",
            "c)\tA",
            "d)\tH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Maxwell equations can be used to compute E,H,D,B and J directly. It is not possible to find the magnetic vector potential A directly."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "6.\tWhich of the following relation will hold good?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tD = μ H",
            "b)\tB = ε E",
            "c)\tE = ε D",
            "d)\tB = μ H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The magnetic flux density is the product the permeability and the magnetic field intensity. This statement is always true for any material (permeability)."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "8.\tChoose the best relation.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tA = -Div(V)",
            "b)\tV = Curl(A)",
            "c)\tH = -Grad(V)",
            "d)\tV = Div(E)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The permeability and permittivity of free space or air is always unity. This implies that the air is always ready to store electric or magnetic charges subjected to it."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "9.\tFind the magnetic field when the magnetic vector potential is a unit vector.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t-1",
            "c)\t0",
            "d)\t2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For any magnetic field, the magnetic field intensity will be the negative gradient of the potential of the field. This is given by H = -Grad(V)."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "10.\t Find the force experienced by an electromagnetic wave in a conductor?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tElectrostatic force",
            "b)\tMagneto static force",
            "c)\tElectro motive force",
            "d)\tLorentz force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We know that H = -Grad(V), where is a unit vector. The gradient of a constant/unit vector will be zero. Thus the magnetic field intensity will be zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "1.\tCalculate the capacitance of a material in air with area 20 units and distance between plates is 5m.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t35.36pF",
            "b)\t3.536pF",
            "c)\t35.36nF",
            "d)\t3.536nF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The capacitance of any material is given by, C = εA/d, where ε = εoεr is the permittivity in air and the material respectively. Thus C = 1 X 8.854 X 10-12 X 20/5 = 35.36pF."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "2.\tThe resistance of a material with conductivity 2millimho/m2, length 10m and area 50m is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t500",
            "b)\t200",
            "c)\t100",
            "d)\t1000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The resistance is given by, R = ρL/A, where ρ is the resistivity, the inverse of conductivity. R = 10/(0.002 X 50) = 100 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "3.\tFind the inductance of a coil with permeability 3.5, turns 100 and length 2m. Assume the area to be thrice the length.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t131.94mH",
            "b)\t94.131mH",
            "c)\t131.94H",
            "d)\t94.131H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The inductance is given by L = μ N2A/l, where μ= μoμr is the permeability of air and the material respectively. N = 100 and Area = 3 X 2 = 6. L = 4π X 10-7 X 1002 X 6/2 = 131.94mH."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the current density of a material with resistivity 20 units and electric field intensity 2000 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t400",
            "b)\t300",
            "c)\t200",
            "d)\t100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The current density is given by J = σ E, where σ is the conductivity. Thus resistivity ρ = 1/σ. J = E/ρ = 2000/20 = 100 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "5.\tFind the current in a conductor with resistance 2 ohm, electric field 2 units and distance 100cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1A",
            "b)\t10mA",
            "c)\t10A",
            "d)\t100mA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We know that E = V/d. To get potential, V = E X d = 2 X 1 = 2 volts. From Ohm’s law, V = IR and current I = V/R = 2/2 = 1A."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "6.\tIn electric fields, D= ε E. The correct expression which is analogous in magnetic fields will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tH = μ B",
            "b)\tB = μ H",
            "c)\tA = μ B",
            "d)\tH = μ A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In electric fields, the flux density is a product of permittivity and field intensity. Similarly, for magnetic fields, the magnetic flux density is the product of permeability and magnetic field intensity, given by B= μ H."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "7.\tFind the force on a conductor of length 12m and magnetic flux density 20 units when a current of 0.5A is flowing through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t60",
            "b)\t120",
            "c)\t180",
            "d)\t200"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The force on a conductor is given by F = BIL, where B = 20, I = 0.5 and L = 12. Force F = 20 X 0.5 x 12 = 120 N."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "9.\tCalculate the power of a material with electric field 100 units at a distance of 10cm with a current of 2A flowing through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t 10",
            "b)\t20",
            "c)\t40",
            "d)\t80"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We know that F = qE = qV/d and W = qV. Thus it is clear that qV = W and qV = Fd. On equating both, we get W = Fd, which is the required proof."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "10.\t Compute the power consumed by a material with current density 15 units in an area of 100 units. The potential measured across the material is 20V.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t100kJ",
            "b)\t250kJ",
            "c)\t30kJ",
            "d)\t15kJ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Power is defined as the product of voltage and current.\nP = V X I, where V = E X d. Thus P = E X d X I = 100 X 0.1 X 2 = 20 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "1.\tFind the electric force when the charge of 2C is subjected to an electric field of 6 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t6",
            "b)\t3",
            "c)\t12",
            "d)\t24"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The electric force is given by F = qE, where q = 2C and E = 6 units. Thus we get F = 2 x 6 = 12 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "2.\tFind the magnetic force when a charge 3.5C with flux density of 4 units is having a velocity of 2m/s.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t14",
            "b)\t28",
            "c)\t7",
            "d)\t32"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The magnetic force is given by F = q(v x B), where q = 3.5C, v = 2m/s and B = 4 units. Thus we get F = 3.5(2 x 4) = 28 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "3.\tFind the electric field when the velocity of the field is 12m/s and the flux density is 8.75 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t510",
            "b)\t105",
            "c)\t150",
            "d)\t165"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The electric field intensity is the product of the velocity and the magnetic flux density ie, E = v x B = 12 x 8.75 = 105 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the Lorentz force of a charge 2.5C having an electric field of 5 units and magnetic field of 7.25 units with a velocity 1.5m/s.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t39.68",
            "b)\t68.39",
            "c)\t86.93",
            "d)\t93.68"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Lorentz force is given by F = qE + q(v x B), it is the sum of electric and magnetic force. On substituting q = 2.5, E = 5, v = 1.5 and B = 7.25, F = 2.5(5) + 2.5(1.5 x 7.25) = 39.68 units.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "5.\tThe force on a conductor of length 12cm having current 8A and flux density 3.75 units at an angle of 300 is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.6",
            "b)\t2",
            "c)\t1.4",
            "d)\t1.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The force on a conductor is given by F = BIL sin θ, where B = 3.75, I = 8, L = 0.12 and θ = 300. We get F = 3.75 x 8 x 0.12 sin 30 = 1.8 units.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "6.\tThe force per unit length of two conductors carrying equal currents of 5A separated by a distance of 20cm in air(in 10-6 order)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t25",
            "b)\t35",
            "c)\t40",
            "d)\t50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The force per unit length of two conductors is given by\nF = μ I1xI2/2πD, where I1 = I2 = 5 and D = 0.2. Thus F = 4π x 10-7 x 52/ 2π x 0.2 = 25 x 10-6 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "7.\tWhen currents are moving in the same direction in two conductors, then the force will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAttractive",
            "b)\tRepulsive",
            "c)\tRetracting",
            "d)\tOpposing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When two conductors are having currents moving in the same direction then the forces of the two conductors will be moving towards each other or attractive."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the flux density due to a conductor of length 6m and carrying a current of 3A(in 10-7 order)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t10",
            "c)\t100",
            "d)\t0.1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The flux density is B = μH, where H = I/2πR. Put I = 3 and R = 6, we get B = 4π x 10-7 x 3/2π x 6 = 1 x 10-7 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "9.\tFind the maximum force of the conductor having length 60cm, current 2.75A and flux density of 9 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t14.85",
            "b)\t18.54",
            "c)\t84.25",
            "d)\t7.256"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The force on a conductor is given by F = BIL sin θ, where B = 3.75, I = 8, L = 0.12 and θ = 90 for maximum force. We get F\n= BIL= 9 x 2.75 x 0.6 sin 90 = 14.85 units.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "1.\tFind the force that exists in an electromagnetic wave.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tElectrostatic force",
            "b)\tMagnetostatic force",
            "c)\tLorentz force",
            "d)\tElectromotive force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In an electromagnetic wave, the force of the electric and magnetic field both coexist. This is given by F = qE + q(v x B). It is called Lorentz force."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "2.\tIn an field having a force of 12N and distance 20cm, the torque will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.24",
            "b)\t2.4",
            "c)\t24",
            "d)\t12/20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The torque is defined as the product of the force and distance in a field. Thus T = F x d = 12 x 0.2 = 2.4 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "3.\tFind the torque in a conductor having current 2A, flux density 50 units, length 15cm and distance of 8m.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t120",
            "b)\t240",
            "c)\t800",
            "d)\t350"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The torque on a conductor is given by T = BILd, where L x d is the area of the conductor. Thus the torque will be, T = 50 x 2 x 0.15 x 8 = 120 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "4.\tThe distance of the conductor when the area and length of the conductor is 24m2 and 13.56m.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.76",
            "b)\t2.67",
            "c)\t1.52",
            "d)\t2.15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We know that the surface integral is the area component which is the product of two dimensions given by length and distance in a conductor. Thus A = L x d. To get d, d = A/L = 24/13.56 = 1.76 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "5.\tThe torque on a conductor with flux density 23 units, current 1.6A and area 6.75 units will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t248.4",
            "b)\t192.6",
            "c)\t175.4",
            "d)\t256.9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum torque on a conductor will be at perpendicular angle ie, at 90. The torque will be given as T = BIA, where B = 23, I = 1.6 and A = 6.75.Thus we get, T = 23 x 1.6 x 6.75 = 248.4 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "6.\tConsider the conductor to be a coil of turns 60 and the flux density to be 13.5 units, current 0.12A and area 16units. The torque will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1555.2",
            "b)\t1222.5",
            "c)\t525.1",
            "d)\t255.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a single turn or loop, the torque will be BIA. For N turns, the torque will be T = NBIA, where N = 60, B = 13.5, I = 0.12 and A = 16. Thus T = 60 x 13.5 x 0.12 x 16 = 1555.2 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "7.\tThe torque of a conductor is defined only in the case when",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe field is perpendicular to the loop",
            "b)\tThe plane of the loop is parallel to the field",
            "c)\tThe plane of the loop is perpendicular to the current direction",
            "d)\tThe field and the current direction are same"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The torque of a conductor is given by T = NBIA. This equation of the conductor is valid only when the plane of the loop is parallel to the magnetic field applied to it."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the angle at which the torque is minimum.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t30",
            "b)\t45",
            "c)\t60",
            "d)\t90"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The torque of a conductor loop is given by T = BIA cos θ. The torque is minimum refers to zero torque. This is possible only when the angle is 90 or perpendicular."
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "9.\tThe magnetic moment and torque are related as follows",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tT = BM",
            "b)\tB = TM",
            "c)\tM = TB",
            "d)\tT = M"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The torque is defined as the product of the magnetic flux density and the magnetic moment. It is given by T = BM, where M = IA is the magnetic moment."
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "10.\tCalculate the magnetic moment when a field of B= 51 units is subjected to a torque of 20 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.39",
            "b)\t4.2",
            "c)\t2.55",
            "d)\t3.21"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The magnetic moment is given by the ratio of the torque and the magnetic flux density. Thus M = T/B, where T = 20 and B = 51 units. We get M = 20/51 = 0.39 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "1.\tThe magnetic moment of a field with current 12A and area 1.6 units is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t19.2",
            "b)\t12.9",
            "c)\t21.9",
            "d)\t91.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The magnetic moment is the product of current and the area of the conductor. It is given by M = IA, where I = 12 and A = 1.6.Thus we get, M = 12 x 1.6 = 19.2 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "2.\tFind the torque of a loop with magnetic moment 12.5 and magnetic flux density 7.65 units is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t95.625",
            "b)\t65.925",
            "c)\t56.525",
            "d)\t65.235"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The torque is defined as the product of the magnetic moment and the magnetic flux density given by T = MB, where M = 12.5 and B = 7.65. Thus we get T = 12.5 x 7.65 = 95.625 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "3.\tThe magnetization is defined by the ratio of",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMagnetic moment to area",
            "b)\tMagnetic moment to volume",
            "c)\tMagnetic flux density to area",
            "d)\tMagnetic flux density to volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The magnetization refers to the amount of dipole formation in a given volume when it is subjected to a magnetic field. It is given by the ratio of the magnetic moment to the volume. Thus Pm = M/V."
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the orbital dipole moment in a field of dipoles of radius 20cm and angular velocity of 2m/s(in 10-22 order)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t64",
            "b)\t76",
            "c)\t54",
            "d)\t78"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The orbital dipole moment is given by M = 0.5 x eVangx r2, where e = 1.6 x 10-19 is the charge of the electron, Vang = 2 and r = 0.2. On substituting, we get M = 0.5 x 1.6 x 10-19x 2 x 0.22= 64 x 10-22 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "5.\tFind the orbital angular moment of a dipole with angular velocity of 1.6m/s and radius 35cm(in 10-31 order)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.78",
            "b)\t8.71",
            "c)\t7.18",
            "d)\t2.43"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The orbital angular moment is given by Ma = m x Vangx r2,where m = 9.1 x 10-31, Vang = 1.6 and r = 0.35. On substituting, we get, Ma = 9.1 x 10-31 x 1.6 x 0.352 = 1.78 x 10-31 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "6.\tThe ratio of the orbital dipole moment to the orbital angular moment is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\te/m",
            "b)\t–e/m",
            "c)\te/2m",
            "d)\t–e/2m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The orbital dipole moment is given by M = 0.5 x eVangx r2 and the orbital angular moment is given by Ma = m x Vangx r2. Their ratio M/Ma is given by –e/2m, the negative sign indicates the charge of electron."
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "7.\tCalculate the Larmer angular frequency for a magnetic flux density of 12.34 x 10-10.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t108.36",
            "b)\t810.63",
            "c)\t368.81",
            "d)\t183.36"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Larmer angular frequency is the product of magnitude of the ratio of orbital dipole moment to orbital angular moment and the magnetic flux density. It is given by fL = B e/2m, where is the charge of electron and m is the mass of the electron. On substituting, we get fL = 12.34 x 10-10 x 1.6 x 10-19/(2 x 9.1 x 10-31) = 108.36 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "8.\tThe Bohr magneton is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\teh/2m",
            "b)\teh/2πm",
            "c)\teh/4m",
            "d)\teh/4πm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In atomic physics, the Bohr magneton (symbol μB) is a physical constant and the natural unit for expressing the magnetic moment of an electron caused by either its orbital or spin angular momentum. It is given by eh/4πm, where h is the Planck’s constant, e is the charge of the electron and m is the mass of the electron."
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "9.\tFind the magnetization of the field which has a magnetic moment 16 units in a volume of 1.2 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t16.67",
            "b)\t13.33",
            "c)\t15.56",
            "d)\t18.87"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The magnetization is the ratio of the magnetic moment to the volume. Thus M = m/v, where m = 16 and v = 1.2. We get M = 16/1.2 = 13.33 units. "
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "10.\t Which of the following is true regarding magnetic lines of force?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tReal",
            "b)\tImaginary",
            "c)\tDoes not exist",
            "d)\tParallel to field"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Magnetic Lines of Force is a an imaginary line representing the direction of magnetic field such that the tangent at any point is the direction of the field vector at that point."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "1.\tThe presence of parallel alignment of magnetic dipole moment is given by which materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDiamagnetic",
            "b)\tFerromagnetic",
            "c)\tParamagnetic",
            "d)\tFerromagnetic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ferromagnetic materials are characterized by parallel alignment of magnetic dipole moments. Their susceptibility is very large."
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "2.\tThe magnetic materials follow which law?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tFaraday’s law",
            "b)\tAmpere law",
            "c)\tLenz law",
            "d)\tCurie Weiss law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Generally, the ferromagnetic, paramagnetic and diamagnetic materials follow the Curie Weiss law, which relates the magnetization and the applied field."
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "3.\tFind the internal field when the applied field is 12 units, molecular field constant is 0.1 units and the magnetization is 74 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t86",
            "b)\t62",
            "c)\t752",
            "d)\t19.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: From Curie law, the internal field of a magnetic material is given by H = Ho + χ M, where χ is the molecular field constant. Put χ = 0.1, M = 74 and Ho = 12, we get H = 12 + (0.1)74 = 19.4 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "4.\tIn which materials the magnetic anisotropy is followed?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDiamagnetic",
            "b)\tParamagnetic",
            "c)\tFerromagnetic",
            "d)\tFerromagnetic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In materials like iron, the magnetic properties depend on the direction in which they are measured. This is magnetic anisotropy. The material iron is a ferromagnetic material type."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "5.\tPiezoelectric effect is analogous to which phenomenon?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tElectrostriction",
            "b)\tMagnetostriction",
            "c)\tAnisotropy",
            "d)\tMagnetization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The piezoelectric effect is the mechanical strain caused on a material like quartz when subjected to an electric field. The same is observed in a ferromagnetic material called magnetostriction.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "6.\tThe converse of magnetostriction is called the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMagnetization",
            "b)\tMagnetic anisotropy",
            "c)\tVillari effect",
            "d)\tCurie effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When a strain is applied, the change in magnetic field is observed. This is the converse of the magnetostriction phenomenon and is called Villari effect."
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "7.\tThe materials having very small susceptibility at all temperatures are",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAntiferromagnetic",
            "b)\tDiamagnetic",
            "c)\tFerromagnetic",
            "d)\tParamagnetic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In antiferromagnetic materials, the susceptibility will decrease with increase in temperature. They have relatively small susceptibility at all temperatures."
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the susceptibility when the curie constant is 0.2 and the difference in critical temperature and paramagnetic curie temperature is 0.01.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t20",
            "c)\t0.02",
            "d)\t200"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The susceptibility in magnetic materials is given by χm = C/(T-θ), where C is the curie constant, T is the critical temperature and θ is the paramagnetic curie temperature. Put C = 0.2 and T-θ = 0.01, thus we get susceptibility as 0.2/0.01 = 20."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "9.\tThe susceptibility is independent of temperature in which material?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tParamagnetic",
            "b)\tFerromagnetic",
            "c)\tDiamagnetic",
            "d)\tFerromagnetic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the diamagnetic materials, the susceptibility is very small and negative. Thus the susceptibility will be independent of the temperature. The atoms of solids having closed shells and metals like gold have this property."
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "1.\tFind the Lorentz force due to a conductor of length 2m carrying a current of 1.5A and magnetic flux density of 12 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t24",
            "b)\t36",
            "c)\t32",
            "d)\t45"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Lorentz is given by the product of the current, differential length and the magnetic flux density. Put B = 12, I = 1.5 and L = 2, thus we get F = BIL = 12 x 1.5 x 2 = 36 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "2.\tCalculate the flux density due to a circular conductor of radius 100nm and current 5A in air.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t10",
            "b)\t100",
            "c)\t0.1",
            "d)\t1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The field intensity of this conductor is I/2πR and since B = μH, the flux density will be B = μI/2πR. Put I = 5 and R = 100 x 10-9, thus we get B = 4π x 10-7x 5/(2π x 100 x 10-9) = 10 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "3.\tThe torque expression of a current carrying conductor is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tT = BIA cos θ",
            "b)\tT = BA cos θ",
            "c)\tT = BIA sin θ",
            "d)\tT = BA sin θ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The torque is given by the product of the flux density, magnetic moment IA and the sine angle of the conductor held by the field. This gives T = BIA sin θ."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the current in a dipole with a moment of 16 units and area of 9 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.78",
            "b)\t2.78",
            "c)\t1.87",
            "d)\t2.34"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The dipole moment is given by M = IA. To get I, put M = 16 and A = 9, we get I = M/A = 16/9 = 1.78 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "5.\tThe expression for magnetization is given by(I-current, A-area, V-volume)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tM = IAV",
            "b)\tM = IA/V",
            "c)\tM = V/IA",
            "d)\tM = 1/IAV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The magnetization is defined as the magnetic moment per unit volume and the magnetic moment is IA. Thus M = IA/V is the expression."
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "6.\tFind the permeability of a medium whose susceptibility is 100.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t-100",
            "b)\t99",
            "c)\t-99",
            "d)\t101"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The susceptibility is given by χm = μr-1. To get permeability, μr = χm + 1 = 100 + 1 = 101 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "7.\tCalculate the magnetization of a material with susceptibility of 50 and field intensity of 0.25 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t12.5",
            "b)\t25",
            "c)\t75",
            "d)\t37.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The magnetization is the product of the susceptibility and the field intensity given by M = χmH. Put χm = 50 and H = 0.25, then M = 50 x 0.25 = 12.5 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "8.\t Very small and positive susceptibility is found in",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tFerromagnetic",
            "b)\tDiamagnetic",
            "c)\tParamagnetic",
            "d)\tAntiferromagnetic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Paramagnetic materials are characterized by a small and positive susceptibility. The susceptibility and the temperature are directly related."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "9.\tWhich of the following materials is ferrimagnetic?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tFe",
            "b)\tSn",
            "c)\tFe2O3",
            "d)\tFeCl"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fe is iron and a ferromagnetic material. Sn and FeCl are not magnetic materials. The oxides of iron like ferric oxide Fe2O3 is said to be a ferrimagnetic material."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "10.\tIdentify the diamagnetic material.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSilicon",
            "b)\tGermanium",
            "c)\tSilver",
            "d)\tCobalt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The diamagnetic materials are characterised by very small or negative susceptibility. Also the susceptibility is independent of the temperature. The material having these properties is germanium from the given options. Metals like gold and atoms with closed shells are also diamagnetic.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "1.\tFind the correct relation between current density and magnetization.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tJ = Grad(M)",
            "b)\tJ = Div(M)",
            "c)\tJ = Curl(M)",
            "d)\tM = Curl(J)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The curl of the magnetization gives the magnetic field intensity theoretically. From Maxwell equation, we can correlate that with the current density (Ampere law)"
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "4.\tThe flux density of medium 1 has a normal component of 2.4 units, then the normal component of the flux density in the medium 2 will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.2",
            "b)\t4.8",
            "c)\t2.4",
            "d)\t0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For two medium of separation, the tangential component of the magnetic field intensity will be continuous. This is analogous to the fact that the tangential component of the electric field intensity is continuous at the boundary."
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "5.\tThe normal component of magnetic field intensity at the boundary of separation of the medium will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSame",
            "b)\tDifferent",
            "c)\tNegative",
            "d)\tInverse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since the tangential component of the magnetic field intensity will be continuous and B = μH, in air, the tangential component of the flux density will also be continuous."
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "6.\tThe line integral of the magnetic field intensity is the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCurrent density",
            "b)\tCurrent",
            "c)\tMagnetic flux density",
            "d)\tMagnetic moment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Unlike the electric fields, the magnetic flux density has normal component same in both the mediums. This gives Bn1 = Bn2."
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "7.\tFind the magnetization of the material with susceptibility of 6 units and magnetic field intensity of 13 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2.16",
            "b)\t6.2",
            "c)\t78",
            "d)\t1.3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The normal component and tangential components of the magnetic flux density will be same. This holds good for any medium."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the ratio of permeability of the two media when the wave is incident on the boundary at 45 degree and reflected by the boundary at 60 degree.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1:1",
            "b)\t√3:1",
            "c)\t1:√3",
            "d)\t1:√2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The line integral of the magnetic field intensity is given by ∫H.dl. This is same as the current component. From this relation, the Ampere law can be deduced."
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "9.\tFind the magnetic moment of a material with magnetization 5 units in a volume of 35 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t7",
            "b)\t1/7",
            "c)\t15",
            "d)\t175"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The magnetization is the product of the susceptibility and the magnetic field intensity. Thus M = 6 x 13 = 78 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "10.\tA boundary of separation between two magnetic materials is identified by which factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tChange in the permeability",
            "b)\tChange in permittivity",
            "c)\tChange in magnetization",
            "d)\tConduction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: From the magnetic boundary conditions, the ratio of permeability μ1/μ2 = tan θ1/tan θ2 and θ1 = 45, θ2 = 60. Thus we get μ1/μ2 = 1/√3. The ratio will be 1:√3."
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "1.\tCalculate the emf of a coil with turns 100 and flux rate 5 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t20",
            "b)\t-20",
            "c)\t500",
            "d)\t-500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The emf is the product of the turns of the coil and the flux rate. Thus e = -N dφ/dt, where the negative sign indicates that the emf induced is opposing the flux. Thus e = -100 x 5 = -500 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "2.\tThe equivalent inductances of two coils 2H and 5H in series aiding flux with mutual inductance of 3H is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t10",
            "b)\t30",
            "c)\t1",
            "d)\t 13"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The equivalent inductance of two coils in series is given by L = L1 + L2 + 2M, where L1 and L2 are the self inductances and M is the mutual inductance. Thus L = 2 + 5 + 2(3) = 13H."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "3.\tThe expression for the inductance in terms of turns, flux and current is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tL = N dφ/di",
            "b)\tL = -N dφ/di",
            "c)\tL = Niφ",
            "d)\tL = Nφ/i"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We know that e = -N dφ/dt and also e = -L di/dt. On equating both we get, L = Ndφ/di is the expression for inductance. "
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "4.\tThe equivalent inductance of two coils with series opposing flux having inductances 7H and 2H with a mutual inductance of 1H.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t10",
            "b)\t7",
            "c)\t11",
            "d)\t13"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The equivalent inductance of two coils in series with opposing flux is L = L1 + L2 – 2M, where L1 and L2 are the self inductances and M is the mutual inductance. Thus L = 7 + 2 – 2(1) = 7H."
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "5.\tA coil is said to be loosely coupled with which of the following conditions?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tK>1",
            "b)\tK<1",
            "c)\tK>0.5",
            "d)\tK<0.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: k is the coefficient of coupling. It lies between 0 and 1. For loosely coupled coil, the coefficient of coupling will be very less. Thus the condition K<0.5 is true."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "6.\tWith unity coupling, the mutual inductance will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tL1 x L2",
            "b)\tL1/L2",
            "c)\t√(L1 x L2)",
            "d)\tL2/L1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The expression for mutual inductance is given by M = k √(L1 x L2),  where k is the coefficient of coupling. For unity coupling, k = 1, then M = √(L1 x L2)."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "8.\tCalculate the mutual inductance of two tightly coupled coils with inductances 49H and 9H.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t21",
            "b)\t58",
            "c)\t40",
            "d)\t49/9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The expression is given by L = Ndφ/di. It can be seen that L is proportional to the ratio of flux to current. Thus the statement is true."
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "9.\tFind the inductance of a coil with turns 50, flux 3 units and a current of 0.5A",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t150",
            "b)\t300",
            "c)\t450",
            "d)\t75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For tightly coupled coils, the coefficient of coupling is unity. Then the mutual inductance will be M = √(L1 x L2)= √(49 x 9) = 21 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "10.\tThe inductance of a coaxial cable with inner radius a and outer radius b, from a distance d, is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tL = μd ln(b/a)/2π",
            "b)\tL = 2π μd ln(b/a)",
            "c)\tL = πd/ln(b/a)",
            "d)\tL = 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The self inductance of a coil is given by L = Nφ/I, where N = 50, φ = 3 and I = 0.5. Thus L = 50 x 3/0.5 = 300 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "1.\tThe magnetic energy of a magnetic material is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBH/2",
            "b)\tB/2H",
            "c)\tH/2B",
            "d)\tB/H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The magnetic energy of a material is given by half of the product of the magnetic flux density and the magnetic field intensity. It is represented as BH/2. Since B = μH, we can also write as μH2 or B2/2μ."
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "2.\tThe induced emf in a material opposes the flux producing it. This is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tFaraday law",
            "b)\tAmpere law",
            "c)\tLenz law",
            "d)\tCurie law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The induced emf in a material under the influence of a magnetic field will oppose the flux that produces it. This is indicated by a negative sign in the emf equation. This phenomenon is called Lenz law."
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "3.\tThe energy in a magnetic material is due to which process?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tEmf",
            "b)\tMagnetization",
            "c)\tMagnetostriction",
            "d)\tPolarization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The energy in a magnetic material is due to the formation of magnetic dipoles which are held together due to magnetic force. This gives energy to the material. Hence it is due to magnetization process."
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "4.\tThe flux lines of two energised coils overlapping on each other will give",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSeries aiding",
            "b)\tShunt aiding",
            "c)\tSeries opposing",
            "d)\tShunt opposing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Flux lines are the magnetic lines of force of a magnetic material. Since the flux is overlapping, the total flux of the two coils together will be high. Thus it is an aiding flux. Also this type of overlapping is possible only when the two coils are back to back or in series connection."
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "5.\tThe resistance in a magnetic material is called as",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCapacitance",
            "b)\tInductance",
            "c)\tReluctance",
            "d)\tMagnetic resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The reluctance of a magnetic material is the ability of the material to oppose the magnetic flux. It is the ratio of the magnetic motive force mmf to the flux."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "6.\tCalculate the reluctance of the material with a mmf of 3.5 units and flux of  7units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t32.5",
            "b)\t10.5",
            "c)\t0.5",
            "d)\t2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The reluctance is defined as the ratio of the mmf and the flux. It is given by S = mmf/φ. On substituting mmf = 3.5 and φ = 7, we get S = 3.5/7 = 0.5 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "7.\tWhich of the following relations is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tNI = Sφ",
            "b)\tNS = Iφ",
            "c)\tNφ = SI",
            "d)\tNI = S/φ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The reluctance is also defined by the ratio of the current element to the flux. In other words, mmf = NI. Thus S = NI/φ. We get the relation NI = Sφ. "
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "8.\tCalculate the reluctance of a material with length 2π x 10-4 in air with area 0.5.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t10",
            "c)\t100",
            "d)\t1000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The reluctance is given by S = L/μ A, where L is the length, A is the area and μ is the permeability. On substituting L = 2π x 10-4, A = 0.5 and μ = 4π x 10-7, we get S = 103/(2×0.5) = 1000 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "9.\tAmpere turn is equivalent to which element?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSφ",
            "b)\tS/φ",
            "c)\tφ/S",
            "d)\tS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ampere turn refers to the current element, which is the product of the turns and the current. It is given by NI. From the definition of reluctance, S = NI/φ. Thus NI = Sφ is the best equivalent."
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "10.\tThe line integral of the magnetic field intensity is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTurns",
            "b)\tFlux density",
            "c)\tMMF",
            "d)\tCurrent element"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The line integral of H is given by ∫H. dl. From Ampere law it can be related to the current density and hence the current element NI for a coil of N turns. Thus, ∫H. dl = NI.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "1.\tThe first Maxwell law is based on which law?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAmpere law",
            "b)\tFaraday law",
            "c)\tLenz law",
            "d)\tFaraday and Lenz law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The first Maxwell equation states that Curl(E) = -dB/dt. It is based on the emf concept. Thus it is derived from the Faraday and Lenz law."
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "2.\tThe benefit of Maxwell equation is that",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAny parameter can be calculated",
            "b)\tAntenna can be designed",
            "c)\tPolarisation of the wave can be calculated",
            "d)\tTransmission line constants can be found"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Maxwell equation relates the parameters E, D, H, B. When one parameter is known the other parameters can be easily calculated. In other words, it is used to relate an electric field parameter with its equivalent magnetic field."
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "3.\tThe correct sequence to find H, when D is given is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tD-E-B-H",
            "b)\tD-B-E-H",
            "c)\tIt cannot be computed from the data given",
            "d)\tD-H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There is no direct relation between D and H, so the option D-H is not possible. Using the formula D = εE, the parameter E can be computed from D. By Maxwell equation, Curl(E) = -dB/dt, the parameter B can be calculated. Using the formula B = μH, the parameter H can be calculated. Thus the sequence is D-E-B-H."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "4.\tThe curl of the electric field intensity is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConservative",
            "b)\tRotational",
            "c)\tDivergent",
            "d)\tStatic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The curl of electric field intensity is Curl(E). From Maxwell law, the curl of E is a non-zero value. Thus E will be rotational."
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "5.\tWhich of the following identities is always zero for static fields?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGrad(Curl V)",
            "b)\tCurl(Div V)",
            "c)\tDiv(Grad V)",
            "d)\tCurl(Grad V)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The curl of gradient of a vector is always zero. This is because the gradient of V is E and the curl of E is zero for static fields."
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "6.\tFind the Maxwell first law value for the electric field intensity is given by A sin wt az",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t-1",
            "d)\tA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of Maxwell first equation is Curl(E). The curl of E is zero. Thus for the given field, the value of Maxwell equation is zero. Thus the field is irrotational."
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "7.\tFind the electric field applied on a system with electrons having a velocity 5m/s subjected to a magnetic flux of 3.6 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t15",
            "b)\t18",
            "c)\t1.38",
            "d)\t0.72"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The electric field intensity is the product of the velocity and the magnetic flux density. Thus E = v x B, on substituting v = 5 and B = 3.6, we get E = 5 x 3.6 = 18 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "8.\tWhich of the following relations holds good?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBq = ILE",
            "b)\tE = ILBq",
            "c)\tEq = ILB",
            "d)\tB = ILEq"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The force of a electrostatic field in given by F = Eq. The force on a conductor is given by F = BIL. In the case when a charge exists on a conductor, both the forces can be equated. Thus Eq = BIL is true."
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "9.\tWhen the Maxwell equation is expressed in frequency domain, then which substitution is possible?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\td/dt = w/j",
            "b)\td/dt = j/w",
            "c)\td/dt = jw",
            "d)\tExpression in frequency domain is not possible"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The conversion of time to frequency domain in Maxwell equation is given by the Fourier Transform. Differentiation in time gives jw in frequency domain. Thus d/dt = jw in frequency domain."
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "10.\tCalculate the emf of a material having a flux linkage of 2t2 at time t = 1second.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t4",
            "c)\t8",
            "d)\t16"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The emf of a material is given by Vemf = -dλ/dt. On substituting λ = 2t2, the emf is 4t. At t = 1 sec, the emf will be 4 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "11.\tCalculate the emf of a material having flux density 5sin t in an area of 0.5 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2.5 sin t",
            "b)\t-2.5 cos t",
            "c)\t-5 sin t",
            "d)\t5 cos t"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The emf can be written as Vemf = -d(∫B.ds)/dt. It can be written as Vemf = -B= -5sin t, since the integration and differentiation gets cancelled."
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "12.\tTo find D from B, sequence followed will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tB-E-D",
            "b)\tB-H-D",
            "c)\tE-H-D",
            "d)\tE-B-D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Using Maxwell equation, from B we can calculate E by Curl(E) = -dB /dt. From E, D can be calculated by D = εE. Thus the sequence is B->E->D."
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "1.\tMaxwell second equation is based on which law?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAmpere law",
            "b)\tFaraday law",
            "c)\tLenz law",
            "d)\tCoulomb law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The second Maxwell equation is based on Ampere law. It states that the field intensity of a system is same as the current enclosed by it, i.e, Curl(H) = J."
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "2.\tThe Maxwell second equation that is valid in any conductor is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCurl(H) = Jc",
            "b)\tCurl(E) = Jc",
            "c)\tCurl(E) = Jd",
            "d)\tCurl(H) = Jd"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For conductors, the conductivity parameter σ is significant and only the conduction current density exists. Thus the component J = Jc and Curl(H) = Jc."
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "3.\tIn dielectric medium, the Maxwell second equation becomes",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCurl(H) = Jd",
            "b)\tCurl(H) = Jc",
            "c)\tCurl(E) = Jd",
            "d)\tCurl(E) = Jd"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In dielectric medium conductivity σ will be zero. So the current density has only the displacement current density. Thus the Maxwell equation will be Curl(H) = Jd."
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "4.\t Find the displacement current density of a material with flux density of 5sin t",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2.5cos t",
            "b)\t2.5sin t",
            "c)\t5cos t",
            "d)\t5sin t"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The displacement current density is the derivative of the flux density. Thus Jd = dD/dt. Put D = 5sin t in the equation, we get Jd = 5cos t units."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "5.\tFind the conduction current density of a material with conductivity 200units and electric field 1.5 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t150",
            "b)\t30",
            "c)\t400/3",
            "d)\t300"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The conduction current density is given by Jc = σE, where σ = 200 and E = 1.5. Thus we get, Jc = 200 x 1.5 = 300 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "6.\tCalculate the conduction density of a material with resistivity of 0.02 units and electric intensity of 12 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t300",
            "b)\t600",
            "c)\t50",
            "d)\t120"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The conduction density is given by Jc = σE, where σ is the inverse of resistivity and it is 1/0.02 = 50. Thus we get, Jc = 50 x 12 = 600 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "7.\tIn the conversion of line integral of H into surface integral, which theorem is used?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGreen theorem",
            "b)\tGauss theorem",
            "c)\tStokes theorem",
            "d)\tIt cannot be converted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To convert line integral to surface integral, i.e, in this case from line integral of H to surface integral of J, we use the Stokes theorem. Thus the Maxwell second equation can be written as ∫H.dl = ∫∫J.ds."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "8.\tAn implication of the continuity equation of conductors is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tJ = σ E",
            "b)\tJ = E/σ",
            "c)\tJ = σ/E",
            "d)\tJ = jwEσ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The continuity equation indicates the current density in conductors. This is the product of the conductivity of the conductor and the electric field subjected to it. Thus J = σE is the implication of the continuity equation for conductors."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "9.\tFind the equation of displacement current density in frequency domain.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tJd = jwεE",
            "b)\tJd = jwεH",
            "c)\tJd = wεE/j",
            "d)\tJd = jεE/w"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The displacement current density is Jd = dD/dt. Since D = εE and in frequency domain d/dt = jw, thus we get Jd = jwεE."
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "10.\tThe total current density is given as 0.5i + j – 1.5k units. Find the curl of the magnetic field intensity.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.5i – 0.5j + 0.5k",
            "b)\t0.5i + j -1.5k",
            "c)\ti – j + k",
            "d)\ti + j – k"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: By Maxwell second equation, the curl of H is same as the sum of conduction current density and displacement current density. Thus Curl(H) = J = 0.5i + j – 1.5k units."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "11.\tAt dc field, the displacement current density will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\tJc",
            "d)\t∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The DC field refers to zero frequency. The conduction current is independent of the frequency, whereas the displacement current density is dependent on the frequency, i.e, Jd = jwεE. Thus at DC field, the displacement current density will be zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "12.\tBoth the conduction and displacement current densities coexist in which medium?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tOnly conductors in air",
            "b)\tOnly dielectrics in air",
            "c)\tConductors placed in any dielectric medium",
            "d)\tBoth the densities can never coexist"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Conduction density exists only for good conductors and displacement density is for dielectrics in any medium at high frequency. Thus both coexist when a conductor is placed in a dielectric medium."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "1.\tThe charge density of a electrostatic field is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCurl of E",
            "b)\tDivergence of E",
            "c)\tCurl of D",
            "d)\tDivergence of D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: From the Gauss law for electric field, the volume charge density is the divergence of the electric flux density of the field. Thus Div(D) = ρv."
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "2.\tIn the medium of free space, the divergence of the electric flux density will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t0",
            "c)\t-1",
            "d)\tInfinity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In free space or air, the charge density will be zero. In other words, the conduction is possible in mere air medium. By gauss law, since the charge density is same as the divergence of D, the Div(D) in air/free space will be zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "3.\tIn a medium other than air, the electric flux density will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSolenoidal",
            "b)\tCurl free",
            "c)\tIrrotational",
            "d)\tDivergent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In any medium other than the air, the conduction is possible, due to the charge carriers. Thus charge density is also non-zero. We can write from Gauss law that Div(D) is non-zero. When the divergence is said to be non-zero, the field is not solenoidal or called as divergent field."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "4.\tFor a solenoidal field, the surface integral of D will be,",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a solenoidal field, the divergence will be zero. By divergence theorem, the surface integral of D and the volume integral of Div(D) is same. So as the Div(D) is zero for a solenoidal field, the surface integral of D is also zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "5.\tIn a dipole, the Gauss theorem value will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t0",
            "c)\t-1",
            "d)\t2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Gauss theorem for an electric field is given by Div(D)= ρ. In a dipole only static charge exists and the divergence will be zero. Thus the Gauss theorem value for the dipole will be zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "6.\tFind the electric flux density of a material whose charge density is given by 12 units in a volume region of 0.5 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t12",
            "b)\t24",
            "c)\t6",
            "d)\t48"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: By Gauss law, Div(D) = ρv. To get D, integrate the charge density given. Thus D = ∫ρv dv, where ρv = 12 and ∫dv = 0.5. We get, D = 12 x 0.5 = 6 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "7.\tFrom the Gauss law for electric field, we can compute which of the following parameters?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tB",
            "b)\tH",
            "c)\tE",
            "d)\tA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: From the Gauss law for electric field, we can find the electric flux density directly. On substituting, D= ε E, the electric field intensity can be calculated."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "8.\tThe charge density of a system with the position vector as electric flux density is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The divergence of the electric flux density is the charge density. For a position vector xi + yj + zk, the divergence will be 1 + 1 + 1 = 3. Thus by Gauss law, the charge density is also 3."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "9.\tThe sequence for finding E when charge density is given is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tE-D-ρv",
            "b)\tE-B-ρv",
            "c)\tE-H-ρv",
            "d)\tE-V-ρv"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From the given charge density ρv, we can compute the electric flux density by Gauss law. Since, D = εE, the electric field intensity can also be computed. Thus the sequence is  E-D-ρv."
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "10.\tThe Gauss law employs which theorem for the calculation of charge density?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGreen theorem",
            "b)\tStokes theorem",
            "c)\tGauss theorem",
            "d)\tMaxwell equation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Gauss divergence theorem is given by ∫ D.ds = ∫Div(D).dv. From the theorem value, we can compute the charge density. Thus Gauss law employs the Gauss divergence theorem."
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich quantity is solenoidal in the electromagnetic theory?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tElectric field intensity",
            "b)\tElectric flux density",
            "c)\tMagnetic field intensity",
            "d)\tMagnetic flux density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The divergence of the magnetic flux density is zero. This is the Maxwell fourth equation. As the divergence is zero, the quantity will be solenoidal or divergent less."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "2.\tWhich equation will be true, if the medium is considered to be air?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCurl(H) = 0",
            "b)\tDiv(H) = 0",
            "c)\tGrad(H) = 0",
            "d)\tDiv(H) = 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From the Gauss law for magnetic field, the divergence of the magnetic flux density is zero. Also B = μH. Thus divergence of H is also zero, i.e, Div(H) = 0 is true."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "3.\tFind the sequence to find B when E is given.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tE-D-H-B",
            "b)\tB-E-D",
            "c)\tH-B-E-D",
            "d)\tV-E-B"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From E, D can be computed as D = εE. Using the Ampere law, H can be computed from D. Finally, B can be calculated from H by B = μH."
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "4.\tThe Gauss law for magnetic field is valid in",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAir",
            "b)\tConductor",
            "c)\tDielectric",
            "d)\tAll cases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Gauss law for magnetic field states that the divergence of B is always zero. This is valid for all cases like free space, dielectric medium etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "5.\tThe sequence for finding H from E is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tE-B-H",
            "b)\tE-V-H",
            "c)\tE-D-H",
            "d)\tE-A-H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From E, we can compute B using the Maxwell first law. Using B, the parameter H can be found since B = μH. Thus the sequence is E-B-H is true."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "6.\tThe reason for non existence of magnetic monopoles is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe magnetic field cannot be split",
            "b)\tDue to permeability",
            "c)\tDue to magnetization",
            "d)\tDue to magnetostriction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Practically monopoles do not exist, due to the connection between north and south poles. But theoretically, they exist. The reason for their non- existence practically is that, the magnetic field confined to two poles cannot be split or confined to a single pole."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "7.\tThe non existence of the magnetic monopole is due to which operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGradient",
            "b)\t Divergence",
            "c)\tCurl",
            "d)\tLaplacian"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Maxwell fourth law or the Gauss law for magnetic field states that the divergence of B is zero, implies the non existence of magnetic monopoles. Thus the operation involved is divergence. "
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "9.\tWhich equation will hold good for a magnetic material?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLine integral of H is zero",
            "b)\tSurface integral of H is zero",
            "c)\tLine integral of B is zero",
            "d)\tSurface integral of B is zero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When dielectric breakdown occurs, the material loses its dielectric property and becomes a conductor. When it is subjected to a magnetic field, north and south flux lines coexists, giving magnetic force. Thus there exists magnetic dipole. Suppose if the conductor is broken into very small pieces, still there exist a magnetic dipole in every broken part. In other words, when a piece is broken into half, there cannot exist a north pole in one half and a south pole in the other. Thus monopoles never exist."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "10.\t The dipole formation in a magnet is due to",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tInteraction between the north and south poles together",
            "b)\tInteraction between the north pole with the air",
            "c)\tInteraction between the south pole with the air",
            "d)\tInteraction of north and south pole separately with air"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: We know that the divergence of B is zero. From Stokes theorem, the surface integral of B is equal to the volume integral of divergence of B. Thus surface integral of B is also zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "1.\tCalculate the emf in a material with flux linkage of 3.5t2 at 2 seconds.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3.5",
            "b)\t-7",
            "c)\t-14",
            "d)\t28"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The emf induced in a material with flux linkage is given by Vemf  = -dλ/dt. On substituting λ= 3.5t2, we get emf = -7t. At time t = 2sec, the emf will be -14 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "2.\tFind the emf induced in a coil of 60 turns with a flux rate of 3 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t-60",
            "b)\t-180",
            "c)\t60",
            "d)\t180"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The emf induced is the product of the turns and the flux rate. Thus Vemf = -Ndφ/dt. On substituting N = 60 and dφ/dt = 3, we get emf as -60 x 3 = -180 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "3.\tFind the electric field intensity of a charge 2.5C with a force of 3N.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t-7.5",
            "b)\t7.5",
            "c)\t2.5/3",
            "d)\t3/2.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The electric field intensity is the electric force per unit charge. It is given by E = F/q. On substituting F = 2.5 and q = 3, we get E = 3/2.5 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "4.\tThe electric field intensity of a field with velocity 10m/s and flux density of 2.8 units is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.28",
            "b)\t28",
            "c)\t280",
            "d)\t10/2.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The electric field is the product of the velocity and the magnetic flux density given by E = v x B. On substituting v = 10 and B = 2.8, we get E = 10 x 2.8 = 28 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "5.\tThe line integral of the electric field intensity is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMmf",
            "b)\tEmf",
            "c)\tElectric potential",
            "d)\tMagnetic potential"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From the Maxwell first law, the transformer emf is given by the line integral of the electric field intensity. Thus the emf is given by ∫ E.dl."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "6.\tWhich of the following relations is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMMF = ∫ B.dl",
            "b)\tMMF = ∫ H.dl",
            "c)\tEMF = ∫ E.dl",
            "d)\tEMF = ∫ D.dl"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The emf induced in a material is given by the line integral of the electric field intensity. Thus EMF = ∫ E.dl is the correct relation."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "7.\tFor static fields, the curl of E will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRotational",
            "b)\tIrrotational",
            "c)\tSolenoidal",
            "d)\tDivergent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For static fields, the charges will be constant and the field is constant. Thus curl of the electric field intensity will be zero. This implies the field is irrotational."
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "8.\tThe line integral of which parameter is zero for static fields?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tE",
            "b)\tH",
            "c)\tD",
            "d)\tB"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The field is irrotational for static fields. Thus curl of E is zero. From Stokes theorem, the line integral of E is same as the surface integral of the curl of E. Since it is zero, the line integral of E will also be zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "9.\tThe magnitude of the conduction current density for a magnetic field intensity of a vector yi + zj + xk will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.414",
            "b)\t1.732",
            "c)\t-1.414",
            "d)\t-1.732"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From the Ampere circuital law, the curl of H is the conduction current density. The curl of H = yi + zj + xk is –i – j – k. Thus conduction current density is –i – j – k. The magnitude will be √(1 + 1 + 1) = √3 = 1.732 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "10.\tThe charge density of a field with a position vector as electric flux density is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Gauss law for electric field states that the divergence of the electric flux density is the charge density. Thus Div(D) = ρ. For D as a position vector, the divergence of the position vector D will be always 3. Thus the charge density is also 3. "
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "1.\tFind the curl of E when B is given as 15t.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t15",
            "b)\t-15",
            "c)\t7.5",
            "d)\t-7.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From Maxwell first law, we get Curl of E as the negative derivative of B with respect to time. Thus Curl(E) = -dB/dt. On substituting B= 15t and differentiating, Curl(E) = -15 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "2.\tThe charge build up in a capacitor is due to",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConduction current density",
            "b)\tDisplacement current density",
            "c)\tPolarisation",
            "d)\tMagnetization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The capacitor consists of a dielectric placed between two conducting plates, subjected to a field. The current due to a dielectric is always due to the displacement current density."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "3.\tThe surface integral of which parameter is zero?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tE",
            "b)\tD",
            "c)\tB",
            "d)\tH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The divergence of the magnetic flux density is always zero. By Stokes theorem, the surface integral of B is same as the volume integral of the divergence of B. Thus the surface integral of B is also zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "5.\tWhen electric potential is null, then the electric field intensity will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\tdA/dt",
            "d)\t–dA/dt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fields that varying sinusoidally with respect to time are called as harmonic fields. An example for harmonic fields is A sin wt."
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "6.\tThe gradient of the magnetic vector potential can be expressed as",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t–με dV/dt",
            "b)\t+με dE/dt",
            "c)\t–με dA/dt",
            "d)\t+με dB/dt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The electric field intensity is given by E = -Grad(V)- dA/dt, where V is the electric potential and A is the magnetic vector potential. When V is zero, then E = -dA/dt."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "7.\tFind the time constant of a capacitor with capacitance of 2 microfarad having an internal resistance of 4 megaohm.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t0.5",
            "c)\t8",
            "d)\t0.25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The gradient of A is the ratio of the negative gradient of electric potential to the speed of light c. We can write c = 1/√(με). Thus grad(A) = -με dV/dt is the required expression."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "8.\tWhich components exist in an electromagnetic wave?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tOnly E",
            "b)\tOnly H",
            "c)\tBoth E and H",
            "d)\tNeither E or H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The time constant of capacitor is given by T = RC, where R = 4×106 and C = 2×10-6. Thus T = 4×106 x2x10-6 = 8 seconds. "
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "9.\tThe propagation of the electromagnetic waves can be illustrated by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tFaraday law",
            "b)\tAmpere law",
            "c)\tFlemming rule",
            "d)\tCoulomb law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In an electromagnetic wave, the electric and magnetic components coexist. They propagate perpendicular to each other and to the direction of propagation in space."
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "10.\t Which one of the following laws will not contribute to the Maxwell’s equations?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGauss law",
            "b)\tFaraday law",
            "c)\tAmpere law",
            "d)\tCurie Weiss law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: By Flemming’s rule, when the thumb and the middle finger represent the inputs (say current and field respectively), then the fore finger represents the output (force, in this case). The EM propagation can be illustrated by this rule."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "1.\tThe loss tangent refers to the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPower due to propagation in conductor to that in dielectric",
            "b)\tPower loss",
            "c)\tCurrent loss",
            "d)\tCharge loss"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The loss tangent is the tangent angle formed by the plot of conduction current density vs displacement current density. It is the ratio of Jc by Jd. It represents the loss of power due to propagation in a dielectric, when compared to that in a conductor."
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "2.\tCalculate the conduction current density when the resistivity of a material with an electric field of 5 units is 4.5 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t22.5",
            "b)\t4.5/5",
            "c)\t5/4.5",
            "d)\t9.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The conduction current density is the product of the conductivity and the electric field. The resistivity is the reciprocal of the conductivity. Thus the required formula is Jc = σ E = E/ρ = 5/4.5 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "3.\tAt high frequencies, which parameter is significant?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConduction current",
            "b)\tDisplacement current",
            "c)\tAttenuation constant",
            "d)\tPhase constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The conduction current occurs in metals and is independent of the frequency. The attenuation and phase constant highly depend on the varying frequency. The displacement current occurs due to dielectrics and is significant only at very high frequencies."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the loss tangent of a material with conduction current density of 5 units and displacement current density of 10 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t0.5",
            "c)\t5",
            "d)\t10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The loss tangent is the ratio of Jc by Jd. On substituting for Jc = 5 and Jd = 10, the loss tangent, tan δ = 5/10 = 0.5. It is to be noted that it is tangent angle, so that the maxima and minima lies between 1 and -1 respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "5.\tThe loss tangent is also referred to as",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAttenuation",
            "b)\tPropagation",
            "c)\tDissipation factor",
            "d)\tPolarization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The loss tangent is the measure of the loss of power due to propagation in a dielectric, when compared to that in a conductor. Hence it is also referred to as dissipation factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "6.\tThe loss tangent of a wave propagation with an intrinsic angle of 20 degree is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTan 20",
            "b)\tTan 40",
            "c)\tTan 60",
            "d)\tTan 80"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The angle of the loss tangent δ is twice the intrinsic angle θn. Thus tan δ = tan 2θn = tan 2(20) = tan 40."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "7.\tThe expression for the loss tangent is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tσ/ωε",
            "b)\tωε/σ",
            "c)\tσ/ω",
            "d)\tω/ε"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The conduction current density is Jc = σ E and the displacement current density is Jd = jωεE. Its magnitude will be ωεE. Thus the loss tangent tan δ = Jc /Jd = σ/ωε is the required expression."
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the loss angle in degrees when the loss tangent is 1.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t30",
            "c)\t45",
            "d)\t90"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The loss tangent is tan δ, where δ is the loss angle. Given that loss tangent tan δ = 1. Thus we get δ = tan-1(1) = 450."
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "9.\tThe complex permittivity is given by 2-j. Find the loss tangent.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1/2",
            "b)\t-1/2",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t-2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The loss tangent for a given complex permittivity of ε = ε’ – jε’’ is given by tan δ = ε’’/ ε’. Thus the loss tangent is 1/2."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "10.\tThe intrinsic angle of the wave with a loss angle of 60 is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t120",
            "b)\t60",
            "c)\t90",
            "d)\t30"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The angle of the loss tangent δ is twice the intrinsic angle θn. Thus tan δ = tan 2θn. We get θn = δ/2 = 60/2 = 30 degrees."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "1.\tFor a dielectric, the condition to be satisfied is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tσ/ωε > 1",
            "b)\tσ/ωε < 1",
            "c)\tσ = ωε",
            "d)\tωε = 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a dielectric, the conductivity will be very less. Thus the loss tangent will be less than unity. This implies σ/ωε < 1 is true."
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "2.\tFor a perfect dielectric, which parameter will be zero?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConductivity",
            "b)\tFrequency",
            "c)\tPermittivity",
            "d)\tPermeability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The conductivity will be minimum for a dielectric. For a perfect dielectric, the conductivity will be zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "3.\tCalculate the phase constant of a wave with frequency 12 rad/s and velocity 3×108 m/s(in 10-8 order)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.5",
            "b)\t72",
            "c)\t4",
            "d)\t36"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The phase constant is given by β = ω√(με), where ω is the frequency in rad/s and 1/√(με) is the velocity of wave. On substituting √(με) = 3×108 and ω = 12, we get β = 12/(3×108) = 4 x 10-8m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "4.\tFor a lossless dielectric, the attenuation will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t0",
            "c)\t-1",
            "d)\tInfinity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The attenuation is the loss of power of the wave during its propagation. In a lossless dielectric, the loss of power will not occur. Thus the attenuation will be zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "5.\tCalculate the velocity of a wave with frequency 2 x109 rad/s and phase constant of 4 x 108 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.5",
            "b)\t5",
            "c)\t0.2",
            "d)\t2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The velocity of a wave is the ratio of the frequency to the phase constant. Thus V = ω/β. On substituting the given values, we get V = 2 x109/ 4 x 108 = 5 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "6.\tWhich of the following is the correct relation between wavelength and the phase constant of a wave?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPhase constant = 2π/wavelength",
            "b)\tPhase constant = 2π x wavelength",
            "c)\tPhase constant = 1/(2π x wavelength)",
            "d)\tPhase constant = wavelength/2π"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The phase constant is the ratio of 2π to the wavelength λ. Thus β = 2π/λ is the correct relation."
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "7.\tIn lossy dielectric, the phase difference between the electric field E and the magnetic field H is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t90",
            "b)\t60",
            "c)\t45",
            "d)\t0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In a lossy dielectric, the E and H component will be in phase. This implies that the phase difference between E and H will be 0."
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "8.\tThe intrinsic impedance is the ratio of square root of",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPermittivity to permeability",
            "b)\tPermeability to permittivity",
            "c)\tPhase constant to wavelength",
            "d)\tWavelength to phase constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The intrinsic impedance is the impedance of a particular material. It is the ratio of square root of the permeability to permittivity. For air, the intrinsic impedance is 377 ohm or 120π."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "9.\tCalculate the skin depth of a material with attenuation constant of 2 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t0.5",
            "d)\t4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The skin depth of a material is the reciprocal of the attenuation constant. Thus δ = 1/α. On substituting for α = 2, we get δ = ½ = 0.5 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "10.\tCalculate the phase constant of a wave with skin depth of 2.5 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t5/2",
            "b)\t5",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t2/5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The skin depth is the reciprocal of the phase constant and the attenuation constant too. Thus δ = 1/β. On substituting for δ = 2.5, we get β = 1/δ = 1/2.5 = 2/5 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "11.\tAn example for lossless propagation is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDielectric waveguide propagation",
            "b)\tConductor propagation",
            "c)\tCavity resonator propagation",
            "d)\tIt is not possible"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are many techniques employed to achieve zero attenuation or maximum propagation. But it is not achievable practically. Thus lossless propagation is not possible practically."
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "12.\tSkin depth phenomenon is found in which materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tInsulators",
            "b)\tDielectrics",
            "c)\tConductors",
            "d)\tSemiconductors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Skin depth is found in pure conductors. It the property of the conductor to allow a small amount of electromagnetic energy into its skin, but not completely. This is the reason why EM waves cannot travel inside a good conductor."
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "1.\tIn conductors, which condition will be true?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tσ/ωε > 1",
            "b)\tσωε > 1",
            "c)\tσ/ωε < 1",
            "d)\tσωε < 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For conductors, the conductivity will be maximum. Thus the loss tangent is greater than unity. This is given by σ/ωε >1."
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "2.\tFor metals, the conductivity will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t-1",
            "d)\tInfinity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Metals are pure conductors. Examples are iron, copper etc. Their conductivity will be very high. Thus the metal conductivity will be infinity. Practically the conductivity of conductors will be maximum."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "3.\tIn conductors, which two parameters are same?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tWavelength and phase constant",
            "b)\tPhase and attenuation constant",
            "c)\tAttenuation constant and skin depth",
            "d)\tSkin depth and wavelength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In conductors, which are considered to be lossy, the attenuation and the phase constant are the same. It is given by α=β= √(ωμσ/2)."
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "4.\tCalculate the velocity of wave propagation in a conductor with frequency 5 x 108 rad/s and phase constant of 3 x 108 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3/5",
            "b)\t15",
            "c)\t5/3",
            "d)\t8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The velocity of wave propagation is the ratio of the frequency to the phase constant. It is given by V = ω/β. On substituting the given values, we get V = 5/3 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "5.\tCalculate the wavelength of the wave with phase constant of 3.14 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t2",
            "c)\t0.5",
            "d)\t4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The wavelength is the ratio of 2π to the phase constant β. On substituting for β = 3.14, we get λ = 2π/β = 2π/3.14 = 2 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "6.\tFor dielectrics, which two components will be in phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tE and wave direction",
            "b)\tH and wave direction",
            "c)\tWave direction and E x H",
            "d)\tE and H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In dielectrics, the electric and magnetic components E and H will be in phase with each other. This is due the variation in the permittivities and the permeabilities of the dielectric surfaces. The phase difference between E and H will be 0."
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "7.\tIn perfect conductors, the phase shift between the electric field and magnetic field will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t30",
            "c)\t45",
            "d)\t90"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For perfect conductors, the electric and magnetic field E and H respectively vary by a phase of 45 degree. This is due to the polarisation phenomenon in the conductors, unlike dielectrics. "
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "8.\tThe expression for phase constant is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPhase constant β = ωμε",
            "b)\tPhase constant ω = με",
            "c)\tPhase constant β = ω√(με)",
            "d)\tPhase constant β = 1/ωμε"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The phase constant is represented as β. It is a complex quantity representing the constant angle of the wave propagated. It is given by  β = ω√(με)."
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "9.\tIn waveguides, which of the following conditions will be true?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tV > c",
            "b)\tV < c",
            "c)\tV = c",
            "d)\tV >> c"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In waveguides, the phase velocity will always be greater than the speed of light. This enables the wave to propagate through the waveguide. Thus V > c is the required condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "10.\tThe attenuation constant in lossless dielectrics will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t-1",
            "d)\t∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In lossless dielectrics, the attenuation constant will not be same as the phase constant, unlike conductors. Also, due to the lossless behaviour, the attenuation will be nearly zero. Practically, zero attenuation is not possible.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "1.\tIn free space, the charge carriers will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t100",
            "d)\tInfinity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Free space is not a conductor. Thus the charge carrier in free space is assumed to be zero. But the free space consists of particles or ions that get ionized during conduction."
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "2.\tIn free space, which parameter will be unity?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPermittivity",
            "b)\tAbsolute permittivity",
            "c)\tRelative permittivity",
            "d)\tPermeability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The relative permittivity is a constant for a particular material. It is unity for free space or air. The absolute permittivity is a constant given by 8.854 x 10-12 C/m2."
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "3.\tWhich parameter is unity in air medium?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPermittivity",
            "b)\tAbsolute permeability",
            "c)\tRelative permeability",
            "d)\tPermeability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In free space or air medium, the relative permeability is also unity, like relative permittivity. The absolute permeability is given by 4π x 10-7 units. "
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "4.\tThe conductivity in free space medium is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tInfinity",
            "b)\tUnity",
            "c)\tZero",
            "d)\tNegative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the charge carriers are not available in free space, the conductivity will be very low. For ideal cases, the conductivity can be taken as zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "5.\tZero permeability/permittivity implies which state?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tNo ions are allowed in the medium",
            "b)\tNo current is generated in the medium",
            "c)\tNo magnetic or electric energy is permitted in the medium",
            "d)\tNo resistivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The zero permittivity in an electric field refers to the ability of the field/medium to permit electric charges in it. Similarly, zero permeability in a magnetic field refers to the ability of the field/medium to permit the magnetic energy into the field."
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "6.\tThe intrinsic impedance of free space is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t489",
            "b)\t265",
            "c)\t192",
            "d)\t377"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The intrinsic impedance is the square root of ratio of the permeability to the permittivity. In free space, the permeability and the permittivity is same as the absolute permeability and permittivity respectively. This is due to unity permeability and permittivity in free space. Thus η = √(μ/ε), where absolute permeability is given by 4π x 10-7 and absolute permittivity is given by 8.854 x 10-12. The intrinsic impedance will be 377 ohms."
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "7.\tIn free space, the condition that holds good is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMinimum attenuation and propagation",
            "b)\tMinimum attenuation and maximum propagation",
            "c)\tMaximum attenuation and minimum propagation",
            "d)\tMaximum attenuation and propagation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The free space does not have any barrier for attenuation. Thus it enables minimum attenuation and maximum propagation. This technique is employed in line of sight communication."
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "9.\tThe velocity of a wave travelling in the air medium without transmission lines or waveguides(wireless) is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t6 x 108",
            "b)\t3 x 108",
            "c)\t1.5 x 108",
            "d)\t9 x 108"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The phase constant is given by the ratio of the frequency in radian/sec to the velocity of the wave propagating. In free space, the velocity is considered to be the velocity of light. Thus the statement is true."
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "10.\t The vectors of the electromagnetic wave propagation can be expressed in",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDot product",
            "b)\tCross product",
            "c)\tUnit vector",
            "d)\tPerpendicular vector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In free space or air medium, the velocity of the wave propagating will be same as that of the light. Thus the velocity is the speed of light, V = c. It is given by 3 x 108m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "1.\tFor conductors, the loss tangent will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tZero",
            "b)\tUnity",
            "c)\tMaximum",
            "d)\tMinimum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In conductors, the conductivity will be more. Thus the loss tangent σ/ωε will be maximum."
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "2.\tIn metals, the total permittivity is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAbsolute permittivity",
            "b)\tRelative permittivity",
            "c)\tProduct of absolute and relative permittivity",
            "d)\tUnity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The total permittivity is the product of the absolute and the relative permittivity. For metals or conductors, the relative permittivity is unity. Thus the permittivity is simply the absolute permittivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "3.\tThe total permeability in a conductor is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAbsolute permeability",
            "b)\tRelative permeability",
            "c)\tProduct of absolute and relative permeability",
            "d)\tUnity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The total permeability is the product of the absolute and the relative permeability. For metals or conductors, the relative permittivity is not unity. Thus the permittivity is the product of absolute and relative permeability."
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "4.\tCalculate the phase constant of a conductor with attenuation constant given by 0.04 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.02",
            "b)\t0.08",
            "c)\t0.0016",
            "d)\t0.04"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The phase constant and the attenuation constant are both the same in the case of conductors. Given that the attenuation constant is 0.04, implies that the phase constant is also 0.04."
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "5.\tCalculate the attenuation constant of a conductor of conductivity 200 units, frequency 1M radian/s in air.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t11.2",
            "b)\t1.12",
            "c)\t56.23",
            "d)\t5.62"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The attenuation constant of a conductor is given by α = √(ωμσ/2). On substituting ω = 106, σ = 200 and μ = 4π x 10-7, we get α = 11.2 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "6.\tThe skin depth of a conductor with attenuation constant of 7 neper/m is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t14",
            "b)\t49",
            "c)\t7",
            "d)\t1/7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The skin depth is the measure of the depth upto which an EM wave can penetrate through the conductor surface. It is the reciprocal of the attenuation constant. On substituting for α = 7, we get δ = 1/α = 1/7 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "7.\tThe expression for velocity of a wave in the conductor is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tV = √(2ω/μσ)",
            "b)\tV = √(2ωμσ)",
            "c)\tV = (2ω/μσ)",
            "d)\tV = (2ωμσ)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The velocity is the ratio of the frequency to the phase constant. In conductors, the phase constant is given by √(ωμσ/2). On substituting for β,ω in v, we get v = √(2ω/μσ) units."
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "8.\tIn conductors, the E and H vary by a phase difference of",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t30",
            "c)\t45",
            "d)\t60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The electric and magnetic component, E and H respectively have a phase difference of 45 degrees. This is due to the wave propagation in conductors in the air medium."
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "The propagation constant of the wave in a conductor with air as medium is",
        "Options": [
            "a) √(ωμσ)",
            "b) ωμσ",
            "c) √(ω/μσ)",
            "d) ω/μσ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The conductors or metals do not support EM wave propagation onto them due the skin effect. This is the reason why mobile phones cannot be used inside lifts."
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "An example for electromagnetic wave propagation is",
        "Options": [
            "a) refrigerator",
            "b) electric fan",
            "c) mobile transponder",
            "d) relays in actuators"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The propagation constant is the sum of the attenuation constant and the phase constant. In conductors, the attenuation and phase constant both are same and it is given by √(ωμσ/2). Their sum will be √(ωμσ), is the propagation constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "The phase shift in the electric and magnetic fields in an EM wave is given by which parameter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) phase constant",
            "b) attenuation constant",
            "c) propagation constant",
            "d) intrinsic impedance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The refrigerator, electric fan and relays are electrical devices. They do not use electromagnetic energy as medium of energy transfer. The mobile transponder is an antenna, which uses the EM waves for communication with the satellites."
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "1.\tThe loss tangent of a perfect dielectric will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tZero",
            "b)\tUnity",
            "c)\tMaximum",
            "d)\tMinimum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Dielectrics have poor conductivity. The loss tangent σ/ωε will be low in dielectrics. For perfect dielectrics, the loss tangent will be minimum."
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "2.\tIn pure dielectrics, the parameter that is zero is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAttenuation",
            "b)\tPropagation",
            "c)\tConductivity",
            "d)\tResistivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are no free charge carriers available in a dielectric. In other words, the charge carriers are present in the valence band, which is very difficult to start to conduct. Thus conduction is low in dielectrics. For pure dielectrics, the conductivity is assumed to be zero. "
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "3.\tThe total permittivity of a dielectric transformer oil (relative permittivity is 2.2) will be (in order 10-11)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.94",
            "b)\t19.4",
            "c)\t0.194",
            "d)\t194"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The total permittivity is the product of the absolute and the relative permittivity. The absolute permittivity is 8.854 x 10-12 and the relative permittivity(in this case for transformer oil) is 2.2. Thus the total permittivity is 8.854 x 10-12 x 2.2 = 1.94 x 10-11 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "4.\tThe permeability of a dielectric material in air medium will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAbsolute permeability",
            "b)\tRelative permeability",
            "c)\tProduct of absolute and relative permeability",
            "d)\tUnity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The total permeability is the product of the absolute and the relative permeability. In air medium, the relative permeability will be unity. Thus the total permeability is equal to the absolute permeability given by 4π x 10-7 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "6.\tCalculate the phase constant of a dielectric with frequency 6 x 106 in air.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t0.2",
            "c)\t0.02",
            "d)\t0.002"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Good dielectrics attenuate the electromagnetic waves than any other material. Thus the attenuation constant of the dielectric will be non-zero, positive and large."
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "7.\tThe frequency in rad/sec of a wave with velocity of that of light and phase constant of 20 units is (in GHz)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t6",
            "b)\t60",
            "c)\t600",
            "d)\t0.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The phase constant of a dielectric is given by β = ω√(με). On substituting for ω = 6 x 106 , μ = 4π x 10-7, ε = 8.854 x 10-12 in air medium, we get the phase constant as 0.02 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "8.\tThe relation between the speed of light, permeability and permittivity is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tC = 1/√(με)",
            "b)\tC = με",
            "c)\tC = μ/ε",
            "d)\tC = 1/με"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The velocity of a wave is given by V = ω/β. To get ω, put v = 3 x 108 and β = 20. Thus ω = vβ = 3 x 108 x 20 = 60 x 108 = 6 GHz."
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "9.\tThe phase constant of a wave with wavelength 2 units is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t6.28",
            "b)\t3.14",
            "c)\t0.5",
            "d)\t2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The standard relation between speed of light, permeability and permittivity is given by c = 1/√(με). The value in air medium is 3 x 108 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "10.The expression for intrinsic impedance is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) √(με)",
            "b) (με)",
            "c) √(μ/ε)",
            "d) (μ/ε)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The phase constant is given by β = 2π/λ. On substituting λ = 2 units, we get β = 2π/2 = π = 3.14 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "The skin depth of a wave with phase constant of 12 units inside a conductor is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12",
            "b) 1/12",
            "c) 24",
            "d) 1/24"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The intrinsic impedance is given by the ratio of square root of the permittivity to the permeability. Thus η = √(μ/ε) is the intrinsic impedance. In free space or air medium, the intrinsic impedance will be 120π or 377 ohms."
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "1.\tThe power of the electromagnetic wave with electric and magnetic field intensities given by 12 and 15 respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t180",
            "b)\t90",
            "c)\t45",
            "d)\t120"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Poynting vector gives the power of an EM wave. Thus P = EH/2. On substituting for E = 12 and H = 15, we get P = 12 x 15/2 = 90 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "2.\tThe power of a wave of with voltage of 140V and a characteristic impedance of 50 ohm is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.96",
            "b)\t19.6",
            "c)\t196",
            "d)\t19600"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The power of a wave is given by P = V2/2Zo, where V is the generator voltage and Zo is the characteristic impedance. on substituting the given data, we get P = 1402/(2×50) = 196 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "3.\tThe power reflected by a wave with incident power of 16 units is(Given that the reflection coefficient is 0.5)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t8",
            "c)\t6",
            "d)\t4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The fraction of the reflected to the incident power is given by the reflection coefficient. Thus Pref = R2xPinc. On substituting the given data, we get Pref = 0.52 x 16 = 4 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": "4.\tThe power transmitted by a wave with incident power of 16 units is(Given that the reflection coefficient is 0.5)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t12",
            "b)\t8",
            "c)\t16",
            "d)\t4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The fraction of the transmitted to the incident power is given by the reflection coefficient. Thus Pref = (1-R2) Pinc. On substituting the given data, we get Pref = (1- 0.52) x 16 = 12 units. In other words, it is the remaining power after reflection."
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "5.\tThe incident and the reflected voltage are given by 15 and 5 respectively. The transmission coefficient is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1/3",
            "b)\t2/3",
            "c)\t1",
            "d)\t3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ratio of the reflected to the incident voltage is the reflection coefficient. It is given by R = 5/15 = 1/3. To get the transmission coefficient, T = 1 – R = 1 – 1/3 = 2/3."
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "6.\tThe current reflection coefficient is given by -0.75. Find the voltage reflection coefficient.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t-0.75",
            "b)\t0.25",
            "c)\t-0.25",
            "d)\t0.75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The voltage reflection coefficient is the negative of the current reflection coefficient. For a current reflection coefficient of -0.75, the voltage reflection coefficient will be 0.75."
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "7.\tThe attenuation is given by 20 units. Find the power loss in decibels.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t13.01",
            "b)\t26.02",
            "c)\t52.04",
            "d)\t104.08"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The attenuation refers to the power loss. Thus the power loss is given by 20 units. The power loss in dB will be 10 log 20 = 13.01 decibel."
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "8.\tThe reflection coefficient is 0.5. Find the return loss.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t12.12",
            "b)\t-12.12",
            "c)\t6.02",
            "d)\t-6.02"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The return loss is given by RL = -20log R, where is the reflection coefficient. It is given as 0.5. Thus the return loss will be RL = -20 log 0.5 = 6.02 decibel."
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "9.\tThe radiation resistance of an antenna having a power of 120 units and antenna current of 5A is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t4.8",
            "b)\t9.6",
            "c)\t3.6",
            "d)\t1.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The power of an antenna is given by Prad = Ia2 Rrad, where Ia is the antenna current and Rrad is the radiation resistance. On substituting the given data, we get Rrad = Prad/Ia2 = 120/52 = 4.8 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "10.\tThe transmission coefficient is given by 0.65. Find the return loss of the wave.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t9.11",
            "b)\t1.99",
            "c)\t1.19",
            "d)\t9.91"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The transmission coefficient is the reverse of the reflection coefficient, i.e, T + R = 1. When T = 0.65, we get R = 0.35. Thus the return loss RL = -20log R = -20log 0.35 = 9.11 decibel."
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "11.\tThe return loss is given as 12 decibel. Calculate the reflection coefficient.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.35",
            "b)\t0.55",
            "c)\t0.25",
            "d)\t0.75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The return loss is given by RL = -20log R. The reflection coefficient can be calculated as R = 10(-RL/20), by anti logarithm property. For the given return loss RL = 12, we get R = 10(-12/20) = 0.25."
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "12.\tFind the transmission coefficient of a wave, when the return loss is 6 decibel.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.498",
            "b)\t0.501",
            "c)\t0.35",
            "d)\t0.65"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The return loss is given by RL = -20log R. The reflection coefficient can be calculated as R = 10(-RL/20), by anti logarithm property. For the given return loss RL = 6, we get R = 10(-6/20) = 0.501. The transmission coefficient will be T = 1 – R = 1-0.501 = 0.498."
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "1.\tThe expression for refractive index is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tN = v/c",
            "b)\tN = c/v",
            "c)\tN = cv",
            "d)\tN = 1/cv"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The refractive index is defined as the ratio of the velocity of light in a vacuum to its velocity in a specified medium. It is given by n = c/v. It is constant for a particular material."
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "2.\tNumerical aperture is expressed as the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tNA = sin θa",
            "b)\tNA = cos θa",
            "c)\tNA = tan θa",
            "d)\tNA = sec θa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The numerical aperture is the measure of how much light the fiber can collect. It is the sine of the acceptance angle, the angle at which the light must be transmitted in order to get maximum reflection. Thus it is given by NA = sin θa."
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "3.\tFor total internal reflection to occur, which condition must be satisfied?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tN1 = N2",
            "b)\tN1 > N2",
            "c)\tN1 < N2",
            "d)\tN1 x N2=1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The refractive of the transmitting medium should be greater than that of the receiving medium. In other words, the light must flow from denser to rarer medium, for total internal reflection to occur."
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the refractive index of a medium having a velocity of 1.5 x 108.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.5",
            "b)\t5",
            "c)\t0.2",
            "d)\t2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The refractive index is given by the ratio of the speed of light to the velocity in a particular medium. It is given by n = c/v. On substituting for v = 1.5 x 108 and c = 3 x 108, we get n = 3/1.5 = 2. The quantity has no unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "5.\tThe refractive index of water will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t2.66",
            "c)\t5",
            "d)\t1.33"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The velocity of light in water as medium will be 2.25 x 108. On substituting for the speed of light, we get refractive index as n = 3/2.25 = 1.33(no unit)."
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "7.\tThe numerical aperture of a coaxial cable with core and cladding indices given by 2.33 and 1.4 respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3.73",
            "b)\t0.83",
            "c)\t3.46",
            "d)\t1.86"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The velocity of light in the air medium and the speed of light are both the same. Since light travels at maximum velocity in air only. Thus the refractive index n = c/v will be unity."
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the acceptance angle of a material which has a numerical aperture of 0.707 in air.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t30",
            "b)\t60",
            "c)\t45",
            "d)\t90"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The numerical aperture is given by NA = √(n12 – n22), where n1 and n2 are the refractive indices of core and cladding respectively. On substituting for n1 = 2.33 and n2 = 1.4, we get NA = √(2.332-1.42) = 1.86."
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "9.\tThe numerical aperture of a material with acceptance angle of 60 degree in water will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.15",
            "b)\t2.15",
            "c)\t5.21",
            "d)\t1.52"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The numerical aperture is given by NA = n sin θa, where n is the refractive index. It is unity in air. Thus NA = sin θa. To get θ= sin-1(NA), put NA = 0.707, thus θa = sin-1(0.707) = 45 degree."
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "11.\t The refractive index is 2.33 and the critical angle is 350. Find the numerical aperture.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t1.9",
            "c)\t2.33",
            "d)\t12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The numerical aperture is given by NA = n sin θa, where n is the refractive index. It is 1.33 for water medium. Given that the acceptance angle is 60, we get NA = 1.33 sin 60 = 1.15."
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "12.\t Choose the optical fibre material from the given materials.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGlass",
            "b)\tPlastic",
            "c)\tSilica",
            "d)\tQuartz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The light should pass through the core region only, for effective transmission. When light passes through cladding, losses will occur, as cladding is meant for protection. Thus core refractive index must be greater than the cladding refractive index."
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "1.\tBrewster angle is valid for which type of polarisation?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPerpendicular",
            "b)\tParallel",
            "c)\tS polarised",
            "d)\tP polarised"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The parallel polarisation of the electromagnetic waves is possible only when the transmission occurs at the Brewster angle.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "2.\tThe Brewster angle is expressed as",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTan-1(n)",
            "b)\tTan-1(n1/n2)",
            "c)\tTan-1(n2/n1)",
            "d)\tTan (n)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The tangent of the Brewster angle is the ratio of the refractive indices of the second medium to that of the first medium. It is given by tan θb= n2/n1. Thus the Brewster angle will be θb = tan-1(n2/n1)."
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "3.\tThe refractive index of a material with permittivity 16 is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t16",
            "b)\t256",
            "c)\t4",
            "d)\t8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The refractive index is the square root of the permittivity. Thus n = √ε. Given that ε = 16, we get refractive index as n = 4. It has no unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "4.\tThe reflection coefficient in the wave propagation when it is transmitted with the Brewster angle is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t-1",
            "d)\tInfinity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Brewster angle propagation refers to complete transmission. The wave transmitted at the Brewster angle will be completely transmitted without reflection. Thus the reflection coefficient will be zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "5.\tThe transmission coefficient of a wave propagating in the Brewster angle is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t-1",
            "d)\tInfinity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The transmission coefficient is the reverse of the reflection coefficient. At Brewster angle, the reflection will be zero. Thus the transmission is T = 1-R. Since R = 0, T = 1. It is to be noted that T and R lies in the range of 0 to 1. "
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the Brewster angle of a wave transmitted from a medium of permittivity 4 to a medium of permittivity 2.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t35.26",
            "b)\t53.62",
            "c)\t26.35",
            "d)\t62.53"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Brewster angle is said to be the polarisation angle. When a circularly polarised wave is incident at the Brewster angle, the resultant wave will be linearly polarised."
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "9.\tFind the ratio of refractive index of medium 2 to that of medium 1, when the Brewster angle is 60 degree.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.707",
            "b)\t1.5",
            "c)\t0.866",
            "d)\t1.732"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Any polarised wave transmitted at the Brewster angle will be linearly polarised. It can be a parallel, perpendicular, circular or elliptical polarisation. The resultant wave is always linearly polarised. This is the reason why the Brewster angle is called polarisation angle."
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "10.\tThe Brewster angle is the angle of",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIncidence",
            "b)\tReflection",
            "c)\tRefraction",
            "d)\tTransmission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Brewster angle is given by θb = tan-1(n2/n1), where n = √ε. Thus we can express the formula in terms of permittivity as θb = tan-1√ (ε 2/ε 1). Here ε1 = 4 and ε2 = 2. Thus we get θb = tan-1√ (2/4) = tan-1(0.707) = 35.26 degree."
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "1.\tThe Snell’s law can be derived from which type of incidence?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIncidence angle",
            "b)\tReflected angle",
            "c)\tRefracted angle",
            "d)\tOblique incidence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The oblique incidence refers to the interface between dielectric media. Consider a planar interface between two dielectric media. A plane wave is incident at an angle from medium 1 and reflected from medium 2. The interface plane defines the boundary between the media. This is the oblique medium."
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "2.\tThe Snell’s law is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tN1 sin θi = N2 sin θt",
            "b)\tN2 sin θi = N1 sin θt",
            "c)\tsin θi = sin θt",
            "d)\tN1 cos θi = N2 cos θt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Snell law states that in an oblique medium, the product of the refractive index and sine of incidence angle in medium 1 is same as that of medium 2. Thus it is given by N1 sin θi = N2 sin θt."
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "3.\tCalculate the ratio of sine of incident angle to the sine of reflected angle when the refractive indices of medium 1 and 2 are given as 2.33 and 1.66 respectively.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.71",
            "b)\t1.4",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t3.99"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Snell law is given by N1 sin θi = N2 sin θt. To get sin θi/sin θt, the ratio is N2/N1. On substituting for N1 = 2.33 and N2 = 1.66, we get 1.66/2.33 = 0.71."
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "4.\tFind the ratio of the refractive index of medium 1 to that of medium 2, when the incident and reflected angles are given by 300 and 450 respectively.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.5",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  The Snell law is given by N1 sin θi = N2 sin θt. For getting N1/N2, the ratio is sin θt/sin θi. On substituting for θi = 30 and θt = 45, we get sin 45/sin 30 = 2."
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "5.\tThe refractive index of a medium with permittivity of 2 and permeability of 3 is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3.56",
            "b)\t2.45",
            "c)\t3.21",
            "d)\t1.78"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The refractive index is given by n = c √(με), where c is the speed of light. Given that relative permittivity and relative permeability are 2 and 3 respectively. Thus n = 3 x 108 √(2 x 4π x 10-7 x 3 x 8.854 x 10-12) = 2.45."
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "7.\tThe critical angle for two media of refractive indices of medium 1 and 2 given by 2 and 1 respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t30",
            "c)\t45",
            "d)\t60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The critical angle is the minimum angle of incidence which is required for the total internal reflection to occur. This is the angle that relates the refractive index with the angle of reflection in an oblique incidence medium."
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "8.\tThe critical angle for two media with permittivities of 16 and 9 respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t48.59",
            "b)\t54.34",
            "c)\t60",
            "d)\t45"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The sine of the critical angle is the ratio of refractive index of medium 2 to that in medium 1. Thus sin θc = n2/n1. To get θc, put n1 = 2 and n2 = 1. Thus we get θc = sin-1(n2/n1) = sin-1(1/2) = 30 degree."
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "10.\tThe angle of incidence of a wave of a wave with angle of transmission 45 degree and the refractive indices of the two media given by 2 and 1.3 is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t41.68",
            "b)\t61.86",
            "c)\t12.23",
            "d)\t27.89"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sine of the critical angle is the ratio of refractive index of medium 2 to that in medium 1. Thus sin θc = n2/n1. Also n = √ε, thus sin θc = √ε2/√ε1. Put ε1 = 16 and ε2 = 9, we get θc = sin-1(3/4) = 48.59 degree."
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "11.\t The angle at which the wave must be transmitted in air media if the angle of reflection is 45 degree is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t45",
            "b)\t30",
            "c)\t60",
            "d)\t90"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For complete wave reflection, the angle of incidence should be same as the angle of the reflection. In such cases, the reflection coefficient is unity and the transmission coefficient is zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "12.\tFor a critical angle of 60 degree and the refractive index of the first medium is 1.732, the refractive index of the second medium is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t1.5",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t1.66"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Snell law is given by N1 sin θi = N2 sin θt. To get θi, put N1 = 2, N2 = 1.3, θt = 45 degree. Thus we get θi = sin-1(1.3 sin 45)/2 = 41.68 degree."
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "1.\tWhen the phase angle between the Ex and Ey component is 00 or 1800, the polarisation is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tElliptical",
            "b)\tCircular",
            "c)\tLinear",
            "d)\tPerpendicular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The phase angle between the Ex and Ey component is 00 and 1800 for linearly polarised wave. The wave is assumed to be propagating in the z direction."
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "2.\tThe magnitude of the Ex and Ey components are same in which type of polarisation?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLinear",
            "b)\tCircular",
            "c)\tElliptical",
            "d)\tPerpendicular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In circular polarisation, the magnitude of the Ex and Ey components are the same. This is a form of the elliptical polarisation in which the major and minor axis are the same."
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "3.\tWhen the Ex and Ey components of a wave are not same, the polarisation will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLinear",
            "b)\tElliptical",
            "c)\tCircular",
            "d)\tParallel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In elliptical polarisation, the magnitude of Ex and Ey components are not same. This is due to the variation in the major and minor axes of the waves representing its magnitude."
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "4.\tIdentify the polarisation of the wave given, Ex = Exo cos wt and Ey = Eyo sin wt. The phase difference is +900.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLeft hand circularly polarised",
            "b)\tRight hand circularly polarised",
            "c)\tLeft hand elliptically polarised",
            "d)\tRight hand elliptically polarised"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The magnitude of the Ex and Ey components are not same. Thus it is elliptical polarisation. For +90 phase difference, the polarisation is left handed. In other words, the rotation is in clockwise direction. Thus the polarisation is left hand elliptical."
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "5.\tIdentify the polarisation of the wave given, Ex = 2 cos wt and Ey = sin wt. The phase difference is -900.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLeft hand circularly polarised",
            "b)\tRight hand circularly polarised",
            "c)\tLeft hand elliptically polarised",
            "d)\tRight hand elliptically polarised"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The magnitude of the Ex and Ey components are not same. Thus it is elliptical polarisation. For -90 phase difference, the polarisation is right handed. In other words, the rotation is in anti-clockwise direction. Thus the polarisation is right hand elliptical."
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "6.\tIdentify the polarisation of the wave given, Ex = 2 cos wt and Ey = 2 sin wt. The phase difference is +900.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLeft hand circularly polarised",
            "b)\tRight hand circularly polarised",
            "c)\tLeft hand elliptically polarised",
            "d)\tRight hand elliptically polarised"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The magnitude of the Ex and Ey components are the same. Thus it is circular polarisation. For +90 phase difference, the polarisation is left handed. In other words, the rotation is in clockwise direction. Thus the polarisation is left hand circular."
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "7.\tIdentify the polarisation of the wave given, Ex = cos wt and Ey = sin wt. The phase difference is -900.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLeft hand circularly polarised",
            "b)\tRight hand circularly polarised",
            "c)\tLeft hand elliptically polarised",
            "d)\tRight hand elliptically polarised"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The magnitude of the Ex and Ey components are the same. Thus it is circular polarisation. For -90 phase difference, the polarisation is right handed. In other words, the rotation is in anti-clockwise direction. Thus the polarisation is right hand circular."
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "8.\tFor a non-zero Ex component and zero Ey component, the polarisation is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tParallel",
            "b)\tPerpendicular",
            "c)\tElliptical",
            "d)\tCircular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the Ex is non-zero and the Ey is zero, the polarisation is parallel. The parallel polarisation is classified under the linear polarisation type."
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "9.\tIdentify the polarisation of the wave given that, Ex = 2 cos wt and Ey = cos wt.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tElliptical",
            "b)\tCircular",
            "c)\tParallel",
            "d)\tLinear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The magnitude of the Ex and Ey components are not the same. Thus it cannot be circular polarisation. For a phase difference of 0, the polarisation is linear. In other words, the waves are in phase. Thus the polarisation is linear."
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "11.\tWhen the polarisation of the receiving antenna is unknown, to ensure that it receives atleast half the power, the transmitted wave should be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLinearly polarised",
            "b)\tElliptically polarised",
            "c)\tCircularly polarised",
            "d)\tNormally polarised"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Snell law is calculated from the oblique incidence media. Thus it is applicable for perpendicular polarisation. The Brewster law is applicable for perpendicular polarisation."
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "12.\tIdentify the polarisation of the wave given that, Ex = 2 sin wt and Ey = 3 sin wt.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLinear",
            "b)\tElliptical",
            "c)\tCircular",
            "d)\tParallel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The polarisation of the transmitting and receiving antenna has to be the same. This is the condition for maximum power transfer to occur. This is possible only when the polarisation is circular."
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "1.\tThe resultant electric field of a wave with Ex = 3 and Ey = 4 will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t7",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t25",
            "d)\t5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The resultant electric field of two electric components Ex and Ey is E = √(Ex2 + Ey2). On substituting for Ex = 3 and Ey = 4, we get E = 5 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "4.\tThe group delay of a wave with phase constant 2.5 units and frequency of 1.2 radian/sec is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3.7",
            "b)\t1.3",
            "c)\t3",
            "d)\t2.08"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the EM wave propagation, the electric and magnetic fields are perpendicular to each other. The S polarised wave is similar to the transverse magnetic (TM) wave, the electric field lies in the plane perpendicular to that of the interface."
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "5.\tThe Brewster angle is valid for which type of polarisation?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tS polarised",
            "b)\tP polarised",
            "c)\tElliptical",
            "d)\tLinear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the EM wave propagation, the electric and magnetic fields are perpendicular to each other. The P polarised wave is similar to the transverse electric (TE) wave, the magnetic field lies in the plane perpendicular to that of the interface or the electric field lies in the same plane as the interface."
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": "6.\tFind the reflection coefficient of a wave with an incident electric field of 5 units and reflected electric field of 2 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2.5",
            "b)\t0.4",
            "c)\t0.8",
            "d)\t1.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The group delay is given by td = β/ω. On substituting for β = 2.5 and ω = 1.2, we get the group delay as td = 2.5/1.2 = 2.08 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "7.\tThe transmission coefficient of a wave with incident and transmitted electric field of 5 and 5 respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t10",
            "d)\t5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Brewster angle is valid for perpendicular polarisation. The P polarised wave is also a type of perpendicular polarisation. In P polarisation, the electric field lies in the plane of the interface."
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the relative permittivity of the medium having a refractive index of 1.6",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.4",
            "b)\t2.56",
            "c)\t3.2",
            "d)\t4.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The reflection coefficient is the ratio of the reflected electric field to the incident electric field. Thus τ = Er/Ei. On substituting for Ei = 5 and Er = 2, we get τ = 2/5 = 0.4(no unit)."
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "9.\tCalculate the transmission coefficient of a wave with a reflection coefficient of 0.6",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.6",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t0",
            "d)\t0.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The transmission coefficient is the ratio of the transmitted electric field to the incident electric field. Thus T = Et/Ei. On substituting for Et = 5 and Ei = 5, we get T = 5/5 = 1(no unit). Simply, when the incident and transmitted field are same, no reflection occurs and the transmission is unity."
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "10.The phase constant of a wave propagation with frequency of 35 radian/sec and time delay of 7.5 sec is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.66",
            "b) 262.5",
            "c) 46.6",
            "d) 26.25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The refractive index is the square root of the relative permittivity. It is given by n = √εr. To get εr, put n = 1.6. We get εr = n2 = 1.62 = 2.56(no unit)."
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich of the following parameters is not a primary parameter?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tResistance",
            "b)\tAttenuation constant",
            "c)\tCapacitance",
            "d)\tConductance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The primary parameters of a transmission line are the resistance, inductance, capacitance and conductance. The attenuation, phase and propagation constant are secondary parameters. Thus the odd one out is the attenuation constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "2.\tThe networks in which the R, L, C parameters are individually concentrated or lumped at discrete points in the circuit are called",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLumped",
            "b)\tDistributed",
            "c)\tParallel",
            "d)\tPaired"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The networks in which the R, L, C parameters are individually concentrated or lumped at discrete points in the circuit are called lumped networks. These networks can be identified definitely as representing a particular parameter. An example is the filters."
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "3.\tThe lines having R, L, C distributed along the circuit are called",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLumped",
            "b)\tDistributed",
            "c)\tParallel",
            "d)\tPaired"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In distributed lines, the primary parameters are distributed along the circuit with each elemental length having its own values and the concentration of the individual parameters is not possible. An example is the transmission of power."
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "4.\tWhich primary parameter is uniformly distributed along the length of the conductor?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tG",
            "b)\tC",
            "c)\tL",
            "d)\tR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The resistance is a primary parameter that is uniformly distributed along the length of the conductor. It depends on the cross section area and the length of the conductor."
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "5.\tThe primary parameter that is associated with the magnetic flux linkage is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tR",
            "b)\tL",
            "c)\tC",
            "d)\tG"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the conductors carry current, the conductor will be surrounded and linked by magnetic flux. The flux linkages per ampere of current gives rise to the effect of inductance. It is denoted by L."
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "6.\tThe primary parameter that is associated with the electric charges is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tG",
            "b)\tR",
            "c)\tC",
            "d)\tL"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Conductors separated by insulating dielectrics in order to store electric charges, gives rise to the capacitance effect. The capacitance is distributed in the whole conductor length."
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "7.\tThe leakage current in the transmission lines is referred to as the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tResistance",
            "b)\tRadiation",
            "c)\tConductance",
            "d)\tPolarisation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The dielectrics or insulators of the open wire line may not be perfect and a leakage current will flow. This leakage conductance exists between the conductors."
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the receiving impedance of a transmission line having a voltage of 24V and a conduction current of 1.2A is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t25.2",
            "b)\t22.8",
            "c)\t28.8",
            "d)\t20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: By Ohm’s law, the impedance is the ratio of the voltage to the current. On substituting for V = 24 and I = 1.2, we get Z = V/I = 24/1.2 = 20 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "9.\tThe characteristic impedance of a transmission line with impedance and admittance of 16 and 9 respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t25",
            "b)\t1.33",
            "c)\t7",
            "d)\t0.75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The characteristic impedance is given by Zo = √(Z/Y), where Z is the impedance and Y is the admittance. On substituting for Z = 16 and Y = 9, we get the characteristic impedance as √(16/9) = 1.33 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "10.\tThe propagation constant of a transmission line with impedance and admittance of 9 and 16 respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t25",
            "b)\t144",
            "c)\t12",
            "d)\t7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The propagation constant is given by γ = √(ZY), where Z is given by 9 and Y is 16. On substituting the given values, the propagation constant will be γ = √(ZY) = √(9 x 16) = 12 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "11.\tFind the characteristic impedance expression in terms of the inductance and capacitance parameters.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tZo = √(LC)",
            "b)\tZo = LC",
            "c)\tZo = √(L/C)",
            "d)\tZo = L/C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The characteristic impedance is given by the square root of the ratio of the inductance to the capacitance. Thus Zo = √(L/C) is the required expression."
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": "12.\tWhen a transmission line has a load impedance same as that of the characteristic impedance, the line is said to be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tParallel",
            "b)\tPerpendicular",
            "c)\tPolarized",
            "d)\tMatched"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When a transmission line load impedance is same as that of the characteristic impedance, the line is said to be matched. In such cases, full transmission of power will occur, with minimal losses. "
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "1.\tThe wavelength of a line with a phase constant of 6.28 units is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t0.5",
            "d)\t3.14"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The wavelength and the phase constant are related by λ = 2π/β, where β is given as 6.28. On substituting for β, we get λ = 2π/6.28 = 1 unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "2.\tThe wavelength of a wave with a frequency of 6 GHz in air is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t50",
            "b)\t5",
            "c)\t0.5",
            "d)\t0.05"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The wavelength is given by the ratio of the velocity to the frequency of the wave. In air medium, the velocity can be assumed as the speed of light. On substituting for v and f, we get λ = v/f = 3×108/6×109 = 0.05 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Question": "3.\tThe phase constant of a wave with a wavelength of 2 units is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t3.14",
            "c)\t6.28",
            "d)\t1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The phase constant is given by β = 2π/λ. On substituting for λ = 2, we get β = 2π/2 = 3.14 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 687,
        "Question": "4.\tThe frequency of a wave travelling in a transmission line with velocity 4 x 108 and wavelength 3 units is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.75 GHz",
            "b)\t0.133 GHz",
            "c)\t7.5 GHz",
            "d)\t1.33 GHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The frequency and wavelength relation is given by f = v/λ. On substituting for v and λ, we get f = 4 x 108/3 = 0.133 GHz."
    },
    {
        "id": 688,
        "Question": "5.\tThe velocity and phase constant relation is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tV = ω/β",
            "b)\tV = ωβ",
            "c)\tV = β/ω",
            "d)\tVωβ = 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The velocity of a wave is the ratio of the frequency in radian/second to the phase constant. It is given by V = ω/β. "
    },
    {
        "id": 689,
        "Question": "6.\tFind the phase constant of a wave travelling with a velocity of 1.2 x 108 and a frequency of 7.5 giga radian/sec",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t62.5",
            "b)\t26.5",
            "c)\t56.2",
            "d)\t52.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The phase constant is given by β = ω/v, from the definition of phase constant and velocity. On substituting for ω = 7.5 x 109 and v = 1.2 x 108, we get the phase constant β = 7.5 x 109/1.2 x 108 = 62.5 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 690,
        "Question": "7.\tThe electrical length in a transmission line refers to the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tProduct of attenuation constant and length",
            "b)\tRatio of attenuation constant and length",
            "c)\tProduct of phase constant and length",
            "d)\tRatio of phase constant and length"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The electrical length in a transmission line refers to the product of the attenuation constant α and the length of the line l. It is given by αl."
    },
    {
        "id": 691,
        "Question": "8.\tThe unit of attenuation constant is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDecibel",
            "b)\tBel",
            "c)\tNeper",
            "d)\tNo unit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Attenuation constant is the measure of the power loss of the wave during its transmission. It is expressed in terms of neper and 1 neper= 8.686 decibel/m."
    },
    {
        "id": 692,
        "Question": "10.\tThe propagation constant of a wave with attenuation and phase constant given by 2 and 3 respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2 – 3j",
            "b)\t3 – 2j",
            "c)\t2 + 3j",
            "d)\t3 + 2j"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are always some distortions, even in the perfect transmission line. This is due to the variation of the secondary parameters. The attenuation constant causes the frequency distortion, whereas the phase constant causes the phase distortion."
    },
    {
        "id": 693,
        "Question": "11.\tThe velocity of wave in the air medium is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1 x 108",
            "b)\t1.5 x 108",
            "c)\t3 x 108",
            "d)\t1 x 109"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The propagation constant is given by γ = α + jβ. Given that α = 2 and β = 3. Thus we get the propagation constant as γ = 2 + 3j."
    },
    {
        "id": 694,
        "Question": "12.\tIdentify the secondary parameter from the options given below.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tResistance",
            "b)\tConductance",
            "c)\tPhase constant",
            "d)\tCapacitance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The light is travelling at its fastest speed in air medium. Thus the velocity of a wave in the air medium is assumed to have the speed of light. It is given by c = 3 x 108."
    },
    {
        "id": 695,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich of the following parameters does not exist in the transmission line equation?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tR",
            "b)\tZo",
            "c)\tZL",
            "d)\tPropagation constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The transmission line equation consists of secondary parameters only, which are derived from the primary parameters. The propagation constant, load impedance and the characteristic impedance are related in the transmission line equation."
    },
    {
        "id": 696,
        "Question": "2.\tFor an infinite transmission line, the characteristic impedance is given by 50 ohm. Find the input impedance.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t25",
            "b)\t100",
            "c)\t2500",
            "d)\t50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: From the transmission line equation, the infinite line will have an input impedance same as that of the characteristic impedance. Thus Zin = Zo for l->∞. This shows that the line will be matched. The input impedance for the given case is 50 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 697,
        "Question": "3.\tThe best transmission length for effective transmission of power is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tL = λ/4",
            "b)\tL = λ/8",
            "c)\tL = λ/2",
            "d)\tL = ∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Maximum transmission of power will occur, when the transmission line is matched. This implies that the input and characteristic impedances are the same. This condition is possible for l = λ/8 and l = ∞. Since l = ∞ is not feasible, the best option is l = λ/8."
    },
    {
        "id": 698,
        "Question": "4.\tWhen the length of the transmission line is same as that of the wavelength, then which condition holds good?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tZin = Zo",
            "b)\tZ = Zo",
            "c)\tZL = Zo",
            "d)\tZin = ZL"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When the transmission line has a length same as that of the wavelength of the wave propagating through it, the input impedance will be same as the load impedance. This is the case where the wave is not amplified. The transmission line acts as a buffer."
    },
    {
        "id": 699,
        "Question": "5.\tThe input impedance of a half wave transmission line with a load impedance of 12.5 ohm is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t25",
            "b)\t50",
            "c)\t6.25",
            "d)\t12.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For a half wave transmission line L = λ/2, the input and the load impedances will be the same. Thus for the given data, the input impedance will be 12.5 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 700,
        "Question": "6.\tThe condition for a quarter wave transformer is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tZo2 = Zin ZL",
            "b)\tZo = Zin ZL",
            "c)\tZL2 = Zin Zo",
            "d)\tZo = Zin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The quarter wave transformer represents L = λ/4. In this case, the characteristic impedance is the geometric mean of the input and load impedances. Thus Zo2 = Zin ZL is the required condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 701,
        "Question": "7.\tFind the characteristic impedance of a quarter wave with input and load impedances given by 50 and 25 respectively.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t50",
            "b)\t25",
            "c)\t75",
            "d)\t35.35"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For a quarter line wave, the characteristic impedance is the geometric mean of input and load impedances. Thus Zo2 = Zin ZL. On substituting for Zin = 50 and ZL = 25, we get Zo2 = 50 x 25. The characteristic impedance will be 35.35 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 702,
        "Question": "8.\tFind the load impedance in a quarter line transformer with characteristic impedance of 75 ohm and input impedance of 200 ohm.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t28.125",
            "b)\t12.285",
            "c)\t52.185",
            "d)\t85.128"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a quarter line wave, the characteristic impedance is the geometric mean of input and load impedances. Thus Zo2 = Zin ZL. On substituting for Zo = 75 and Zin = 200,  we get ZL = Zo2/Zin = 752/200 = 28.125 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 703,
        "Question": "9.\tThe reflection coefficient of a perfectly matched transmission line is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t-1",
            "c)\t0",
            "d)\t∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In a perfectly matched line, maximum power transfer will occur. Losses will be minimal. This implies unity transmission coefficient and zero reflection coefficient."
    },
    {
        "id": 704,
        "Question": "10.\tThe purpose of the transmission line equation is to",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tFind primary parameters",
            "b)\tFind secondary parameters",
            "c)\tFind the reflection cofficient",
            "d)\tImpedance matching"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The transmission line equation is useful in finding the length of the line which gives maximum power transfer. Thus it is useful for impedance matching.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 705,
        "Question": "11.\tThe quarter wave transformer can be considered as a",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tImpedance inverter",
            "b)\tImpedance doubler",
            "c)\tImpedance tripler",
            "d)\tImpedance quadrupler"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A quarter wave transformer may be considered as an impedance inverter as it can transform a low impedance into a high impedance and vice-versa."
    },
    {
        "id": 706,
        "Question": "12.\tWhich transmission line is called as one to one transformer?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tL = λ",
            "b)\tL = λ/2",
            "c)\tL = λ/4",
            "d)\tL = λ/8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The half wave transformer line repeats its terminating impedance. In other words, when l = λ/2, Zin = ZL. Thus it is considered to be one to one transformer."
    },
    {
        "id": 707,
        "Question": "1.\tThe characteristic impedance of a quarter wave transformer with load and input impedances given by 30 and 75 respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t47.43",
            "b)\t37.34",
            "c)\t73.23",
            "d)\t67.45"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In quarter wave transformer, the characteristic impedance will be the geometric mean of the input impedance and the load impedance. Thus Zo2 = ZIN ZL. On substituting for ZIN = 75 and ZL = 30, we get the characteristic impedance as 47.43 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 708,
        "Question": "2.\tThe input impedance of a quarter wave line 50 ohm and load impedance of 20 ohm is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t50",
            "b)\t20",
            "c)\t1000",
            "d)\t125"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The characteristic impedance will be the geometric mean of the input impedance and the load impedance. Thus Zo2 = Zin ZL. On substituting for Zo = 50 and ZL = 20, we get the input impedance as 502/20 = 125 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 709,
        "Question": "3.\tFor a matched line, the input impedance will be equal to",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLoad impedance",
            "b)\tCharacteristic impedance",
            "c)\tOutput impedance",
            "d)\tZero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A matched line refers to the input and characteristic impedance being the same. In such condition, maximum transmission will occur with minimal losses. The reflection will be very low."
    },
    {
        "id": 710,
        "Question": "4.\tThe reflection coefficient lies in the range of",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0 < τ < 1",
            "b)\t-1 < τ < 1",
            "c)\t1 < τ < ∞",
            "d)\t0 < τ < ∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The reflection coefficient lies in the range of 0 < τ < 1. For full transmission, the reflection will be zero. For no transmission, the reflection will be unity."
    },
    {
        "id": 711,
        "Question": "5.\tWhen the ratio of load voltage to input voltage is 5, the ratio of the characteristic impedance to the input impedance is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1/5",
            "b)\t5",
            "c)\t10",
            "d)\t25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From the transmission line equation, the ratio of the load voltage to the input voltage is same as the ratio of the characteristic impedance to the input impedance. Thus the required ratio is 5."
    },
    {
        "id": 712,
        "Question": "6.\tThe power of the transmitter with a radiation resistance of 12 ohm and an antenna current of 3.5A is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t147",
            "b)\t741",
            "c)\t174",
            "d)\t471"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The power in a transmitter is given by Prad = Iant2 Rrad. On substituting Irad = 3.5 and Rrad =12, we get Prad = 3.52 x 12 = 147 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 713,
        "Question": "7.\tThe group delay of the wave with phase constant of 62.5 units and frequency of 4.5 radian/sec is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t13.88",
            "b)\t31.88",
            "c)\t88.13",
            "d)\t88.31"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The group delay is given by td = β/ω. Given that β = 62.5 and ω = 4.5, we get the group delay as td = 62.5/4.5 = 13.88 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 714,
        "Question": "8.\tThe maximum impedance of a transmission line 50 ohm and the standing wave ratio of 2.5 is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t20",
            "b)\t125",
            "c)\t200",
            "d)\t75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The maximum impedance of a line is given by Zmax = SZo. On substituting for S = 2.5 and Zo = 50, we get Zmax = 2.5 x 50 = 125 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 715,
        "Question": "9.\tThe minimum impedance of a transmission line 75 ohm with a standing wave ratio of 4 is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t75",
            "b)\t300",
            "c)\t18.75",
            "d)\t150"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The minimum impedance of a line is given by Zmin = Zo/S. On substituting for Zo = 75 and S = 4, we get Zmin = 75/4 = 18.75 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 716,
        "Question": "The average power in an electromagnetic wave is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) propagation constant",
            "b) poynting vector",
            "c) phase constant",
            "d) attenuation constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Poynting vector is the cross product of the electric field and magnetic field intensities. It gives the total power of an electromagnetic wave."
    },
    {
        "id": 717,
        "Question": "The characteristic impedance of a transmission line is normally chosen to be",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50",
            "b) 75",
            "c) 50 or 75",
            "d) 100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The characteristic impedance is always 50 ohm or 75 ohm for a transmission line. This is because of the GHz range of operation and the load impedences employed."
    },
    {
        "id": 718,
        "Question": "Identify the material which is not present in a transmission line setup.",
        "Options": [
            "a) waveguides",
            "b) cavity resonator",
            "c) antenna",
            "d) oscillator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The transmission line setup consists of antennae for transmitting and receiving power. It consists of waveguides and cavity resonator for guided transmission of electromagnetic waves. Thus oscillator is the odd one out. "
    },
    {
        "id": 719,
        "Question": "1.\tThe reflection coefficient of a wave with transmission coefficient 0.35 is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.35",
            "b)\t0.65",
            "c)\t0.35",
            "d)\t0.7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The reflection coefficient is the reverse of the transmission coefficient. Thus T + R = 1. On substituting for T = 0.35, the reflection coefficient R will be 1 – 0.35 = 0.65 (no unit)."
    },
    {
        "id": 720,
        "Question": "2.\tThe incident wave amplitude is 24 units. Find the reflected wave amplitude if the reflection coefficient is 0.6.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t14.4",
            "b)\t16.6",
            "c)\t13.3",
            "d)\t11.1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The reflection coefficient is the ratio of the reflected amplitude to the incident amplitude. Thus R = Er/Ei. On substituting for Ei = 24 and R = 0.6, we get Er = R Ei = 0.6 X 24 = 14.4 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 721,
        "Question": "3.\tFind the reflection coefficient of the wave passing through two media having intrinsic impedances of 4 and 9 respectively.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.5",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t0.38",
            "d)\t0.1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The reflection coefficient in terms of intrinsic impedances is given by R = η2 – η1/η2 + η1. On substituting for η1 = 4 and η2 = 9, we get R = 9 – 4/9 + 4 = 5/13 = 0.38."
    },
    {
        "id": 722,
        "Question": "4.\tThe reflection coefficient of a wave travelling through two media having permittivities 4 and 9 respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t0.5",
            "c)\t0.25",
            "d)\t0.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The reflection coefficient in terms of permittivity is given by R = √ε2 – √ε1/√ε2 + √ε1. On substituting for ε1 = 4 and ε2 = 9, we get R = 3 – 2/3 + 2 = 1/5 = 0.2."
    },
    {
        "id": 723,
        "Question": "5.\tCalculate the transmission coefficient, when the incident and transmitted amplitudes are 10 and 7 respectively.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t17",
            "b)\t3",
            "c)\t10/7",
            "d)\t0.7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The transmission coefficient is defined as the ratio of the transmitted amplitude to the incident amplitude. Thus T = Et/Ei. On substituting for Ei = 10 and Et = 7, we get T = 7/10 = 0.7."
    },
    {
        "id": 724,
        "Question": "6.\tThe transmission coefficient in a wave travelling through two media having intrinsic impedances of 5.5 and 1.33 is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t 0.389",
            "b)\t0.55",
            "c)\t0.133",
            "d)\t0.42"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The transmission coefficient is terms of the intrinsic impedance is given by T = 2η2/η1 + η2. On substituting for η1 = 5.5 and η2 = 1.33, we get T = 2 x 1.33/1.33 + 5.5 = 2.66/6.83 = 0.389."
    },
    {
        "id": 725,
        "Question": "7.\tThe transmission coefficient in a wave travelling through two media having permittivities 4 and 1 is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1/4",
            "b)\t3/2",
            "c)\t3/4",
            "d)\t2/3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The transmission coefficient in terms of the permittivity is given by T= 2√ε2/√ε1 + √ε2. On substituting for ε1 = 4 and ε2 = 1, we get T= 2(1)/1 + 2 = 2/3."
    },
    {
        "id": 726,
        "Question": "8.\tThe reflection coefficient of a transmission line having characteristic and load impedances as 50 and 30 ohm respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1/4",
            "b)\t1/8",
            "c)\t1/2",
            "d)\t 3/4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The reflection coefficient of a transmission line is given  by, R = ZL – Zo/ZL + Zo, where ZL and Zo is the load and characteristic impedances respectively. On substituting ZL = 30 and Zo = 50, the reflection coefficient R = 50 – 30/50 + 30 = 20/80 = 1/4."
    },
    {
        "id": 727,
        "Question": "9.\tIn matched line, the transmission coefficient is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t-1",
            "d)\tInfinity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In matched line, the maximum power is transferred from transmitter to receiver. Such reflection coefficient will be zero and transmission coefficient is unity."
    },
    {
        "id": 728,
        "Question": "10.\tFind the power reflected in a transmission line, when the reflection coefficient and input power are 0.45 and 18V respectively.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3.645",
            "b)\t6.453",
            "c)\t4.563",
            "d)\t5.463"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ratio of the reflected to incident amplitudes gives the reflection. Similarly, the ratio of reflected to incident power gives square of the reflection coefficient. Thus Prefl = R2Pinc. On substituting for R = 0.45 and Pinc = 18, we get Prefl = 0.452 x 18 = 3.645 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 729,
        "Question": "11.\tThe transmitted power in a transmission line, when the reflection coefficient and the incident power are 0.6 and 24V respectively, is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t15.36",
            "b)\t51.63",
            "c)\t15.63",
            "d)\t51.36"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The transmitted power in terms of the reflection coefficient and the incident power is Ptr = (1-R2)Pinc, where R = 0.6 and Pinc = 24, from the given data. Thus Ptr = (1- 0.62) x 24 = 15.36 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 730,
        "Question": "1.\tStanding waves occurs due to",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tImpedance match",
            "b)\tImpedance mismatch",
            "c)\tReflection",
            "d)\tTransmission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Impedance mismatches result in standing waves along the transmission line. It shows the variation of the wave amplitudes due to mismatching."
    },
    {
        "id": 731,
        "Question": "2.\tStanding wave ratio is defined as the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRatio of voltage maxima to voltage minima",
            "b)\tRatio of current maxima to current minima",
            "c)\tProduct of voltage maxima and voltage minima",
            "d)\tProduct of current maxima and current minima"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: SWR is defined as the ratio of the partial standing wave’s amplitude at an antinode (maximum) to the amplitude at a node (minimum) along the line. It is given by S = VMAX/VMIN."
    },
    {
        "id": 732,
        "Question": "3.\tGiven that the reflection coefficient is 0.6. Find the SWR.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t4",
            "c)\t6",
            "d)\t8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The relation between reflection coefficient and SWR is given by S = 1 + R/1 – R. On substituting for R = 0.6, we get S = 1 + 0.6/1 – 0.6 = 1.6/0.4 = 4."
    },
    {
        "id": 733,
        "Question": "4.\tThe maxima and minima voltage of the standing wave are 6 and 2 respectively. The standing wave ratio is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t3",
            "c)\t1/2",
            "d)\t 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ratio of voltage maxima to voltage minima is given by the standing wave ratio SWR. Thus S = VMAX/VMIN. On substituting the given data, we get S = 6/2 = 3."
    },
    {
        "id": 734,
        "Question": "5.\tFind the standing wave ratio, when a load impedance of 250 ohm is connected to a 75 ohm line.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.3",
            "b)\t75",
            "c)\t250",
            "d)\t3.33"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The standing wave ratio is the ratio of the load impedance to the characteristic impedance. Thus S = ZL/Zo. On substituting for ZL = 250 and Zo = 75, we get S = 250/75 = 3.33."
    },
    {
        "id": 735,
        "Question": "6.\tFind the reflection coefficient of the wave with SWR of 3.5.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.55",
            "b)\t0.23",
            "c)\t0.48",
            "d)\t0.68"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The reflection coefficient in terms of the SWR is given by R = S – 1/S + 1. On substituting for S = 3.5, we get 3.5 – 1/3.5 + 1 = 0.55."
    },
    {
        "id": 736,
        "Question": "7.\tThe range of the standing wave ratio is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0 < S < 1",
            "b)\t-1 < S < 1",
            "c)\t1 < S < ∞",
            "d)\t0 < S < ∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The standing wave ratio is given by S = 1 – R/1 + R. Thus the minimum value of S is 1. It can extend upto infinity for long lines. Thus the range is 1 < S < ∞."
    },
    {
        "id": 737,
        "Question": "8.\tFor matched line, the standing wave ratio will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t∞",
            "c)\t-1",
            "d)\t1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In a matched line, maximum transmission occurs. The reflection will be zero. The standing wave ratio S = 1 – R/1 + R. For R = 0, the SWR is unity for matched line."
    },
    {
        "id": 738,
        "Question": "9.\tThe maximum impedance of a 50 ohm transmission line with SWR of 3 is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t50/3",
            "b)\t3/50",
            "c)\t150",
            "d)\t450"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum impedance is given by the product of the characteristic impedance and the SWR. Thus Zmax = S Zo. On substituting for S = 3 and Zo = 50, we get ZMAX = 3 X 50 = 150 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 739,
        "Question": "10.\tThe minimum impedance of a 75 ohm transmission line with a SWR of 2.5 is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t100",
            "b)\t50",
            "c)\t25",
            "d)\t30"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The minimum impedance in terms of SWR is given by ZMIN = Zo/S.  Substituting the given data for S = 2.5 and Zo = 75, we get Zmin = 75/2.5 = 30."
    },
    {
        "id": 740,
        "Question": "11.\tThe standing wave ratio of  short circuited and open circuited lines will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t-1",
            "d)\t∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The transmission line will reflect high power when it is short or circuited. This will lead to high reflection coefficient. Thus the standing wave ratio will be infinity for these extreme cases."
    },
    {
        "id": 741,
        "Question": "12.\tThe current reflection coefficient of a line with voltage reflection coefficient of 0.65 is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t0.65",
            "c)\t-0.65",
            "d)\t 0.35"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The current reflection coefficient at any point on the line is the negative of the voltage reflection coefficient at that point, i.e, -R. Given that the voltage reflection coefficient is 0.65, thus the current reflection coefficient is -0.65. "
    },
    {
        "id": 742,
        "Question": "1.\tThe power of the electromagnetic wave with electric and magnetic field intensities given by 12 and 15 respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t180",
            "b)\t90",
            "c)\t45",
            "d)\t120"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Poynting vector gives the power of an EM wave. Thus P = EH/2. On substituting for E = 12 and H = 15, we get P = 12 x 15/2 = 90 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 743,
        "Question": "2.\tThe power of a wave of with voltage of 140V and a characteristic impedance of 50 ohm is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.96",
            "b)\t19.6",
            "c)\t196",
            "d)\t19600"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The power of a wave is given by P = V2/2Zo, where V is the generator voltage and Zo is the characteristic impedance. on substituting the given data, we get P = 1402/(2×50) = 196 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 744,
        "Question": "3.\tThe power reflected by a wave with incident power of 16 units is(Given that the reflection coefficient is 0.5)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t8",
            "c)\t6",
            "d)\t4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The fraction of the reflected to the incident power is given by the reflection coefficient. Thus Pref = R2xPinc. On substituting the given data, we get Pref = 0.52 x 16 = 4 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 745,
        "Question": "4.\tThe power transmitted by a wave with incident power of 16 units is(Given that the reflection coefficient is 0.5)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t12",
            "b)\t8",
            "c)\t16",
            "d)\t4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The fraction of the transmitted to the incident power is given by the reflection coefficient. Thus Pref = (1-R2) Pinc. On substituting the given data, we get Pref = (1- 0.52) x 16 = 12 units. In other words, it is the remaining power after reflection."
    },
    {
        "id": 746,
        "Question": "5.\tThe incident and the reflected voltage are given by 15 and 5 respectively. The transmission coefficient is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1/3",
            "b)\t2/3",
            "c)\t1",
            "d)\t3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ratio of the reflected to the incident voltage is the reflection coefficient. It is given by R = 5/15 = 1/3. To get the transmission coefficient, T = 1 – R = 1 – 1/3 = 2/3."
    },
    {
        "id": 747,
        "Question": "6.\tThe current reflection coefficient is given by -0.75. Find the voltage reflection coefficient.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t-0.75",
            "b)\t0.25",
            "c)\t-0.25",
            "d)\t0.75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The voltage reflection coefficient is the negative of the current reflection coefficient. For a current reflection coefficient of -0.75, the voltage reflection coefficient will be 0.75."
    },
    {
        "id": 748,
        "Question": "7.\tThe attenuation is given by 20 units. Find the power loss in decibels.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t13.01",
            "b)\t26.02",
            "c)\t52.04",
            "d)\t104.08"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The attenuation refers to the power loss. Thus the power loss is given by 20 units. The power loss in dB will be 10 log 20 = 13.01 decibel."
    },
    {
        "id": 749,
        "Question": "8.\tThe reflection coefficient is 0.5. Find the return loss.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t12.12",
            "b)\t-12.12",
            "c)\t6.02",
            "d)\t-6.02"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The return loss is given by RL = -20log R, where is the reflection coefficient. It is given as 0.5. Thus the return loss will be RL = -20 log 0.5 = 6.02 decibel."
    },
    {
        "id": 750,
        "Question": "9.\tThe radiation resistance of an antenna having a power of 120 units and antenna current of 5A is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t4.8",
            "b)\t9.6",
            "c)\t3.6",
            "d)\t1.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The power of an antenna is given by Prad = Ia2 Rrad, where Ia is the antenna current and Rrad is the radiation resistance. On substituting the given data, we get Rrad = Prad/Ia2 = 120/52 = 4.8 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 751,
        "Question": "10.\tThe transmission coefficient is given by 0.65. Find the return loss of the wave.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t9.11",
            "b)\t1.99",
            "c)\t1.19",
            "d)\t9.91"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The transmission coefficient is the reverse of the reflection coefficient, i.e, T + R = 1. When T = 0.65, we get R = 0.35. Thus the return loss RL = -20log R = -20log 0.35 = 9.11 decibel."
    },
    {
        "id": 752,
        "Question": "11.\tThe return loss is given as 12 decibel. Calculate the reflection coefficient.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.35",
            "b)\t0.55",
            "c)\t0.25",
            "d)\t0.75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The return loss is given by RL = -20log R. The reflection coefficient can be calculated as R = 10(-RL/20), by anti logarithm property. For the given return loss RL = 12, we get R = 10(-12/20) = 0.25."
    },
    {
        "id": 753,
        "Question": "12.\tFind the transmission coefficient of a wave, when the return loss is 6 decibel.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.498",
            "b)\t0.501",
            "c)\t0.35",
            "d)\t0.65"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The return loss is given by RL = -20log R. The reflection coefficient can be calculated as R = 10(-RL/20), by anti logarithm property. For the given return loss RL = 6, we get R = 10(-6/20) = 0.501. The transmission coefficient will be T = 1 – R = 1-0.501 = 0.498."
    },
    {
        "id": 754,
        "Question": "1.\tThe intrinsic impedance of a wave with electric and magnetic field of 10 and 8 respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.6",
            "b)\t1.11",
            "c)\t1.25",
            "d)\t0.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The intrinsic impedance of a wave is given by η = √(E/H). on substituting for E = 10 and H = 8, we get η = 1.11 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 755,
        "Question": "3.\tThe intrinsic impedance in free space is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t60π",
            "b)\t12π",
            "c)\t6π",
            "d)\t120π"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The intrinsic impedance is defined as the ratio of the electric field intensity to the magnetic field intensity. It is denoted by η. It is a complex quantity."
    },
    {
        "id": 756,
        "Question": "5.\tCalculate the propagation constant of a wave with impedance and admittance given by 32 and 12 respectively.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t19.6",
            "b)\t17.6",
            "c)\t15.6",
            "d)\t13.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The intrinsic impedance of the free space is the ratio of the permittivity to the permeability. For air medium, the value is 120π or 377 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 757,
        "Question": "6.\tThe intrinsic angle is 250, find the loss angle.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t12.5",
            "b)\t50",
            "c)\t25",
            "d)\t75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The propagation constant is a complex quantity. It is given by γ = α + jβ, where α is the attenuation constant, a real value and β is the phase constant, a complex value."
    },
    {
        "id": 758,
        "Question": "7.\tThe standing wave ratio of the wave with maximum and minimum electric field intensities of 12 and 4 is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t12",
            "b)\t4",
            "c)\t3",
            "d)\t48"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The propagation constant is given by γ = √(ZY), where Z is the impedance and Y is the admittance. On substituting for Z = 32 and Y = 12,  we get γ = 19.6 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 759,
        "Question": "8.\tThe standing wave ratio of a wave travelling through two media having intrinsic impedances of 3 and 2 is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2⁄3",
            "b)\t3⁄2",
            "c)\t1⁄5",
            "d)\t5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The loss angle is twice of the intrinsic angle. It is given by δ = 2θn. On substituting for θn = 25, the loss angle δ = 2(25) = 50 degree."
    },
    {
        "id": 760,
        "Question": "9.\tThe reflection coefficient of a wave travelling through two media having electric intrinsic impedances of 3 and 5 respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t8",
            "c)\t5⁄3",
            "d)\t1/4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The SWR is defined as the ratio of maximum electric field intensities to the minimum field intensities. It is given by S = EMAX/EMIN. Thus for the given data, S = 12/4 = 3."
    },
    {
        "id": 761,
        "Question": "10.\tThe reflection coefficient of a wave travelling through two media having magnetic intrinsic impedances of 2 and 1 respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1⁄2",
            "b)\t1⁄3",
            "c)\t1⁄4",
            "d)\t1⁄5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The standing wave ratio is given by the ratio of the intrinsic impedance of medium 1 to the intrinsic impedance of medium 2. Thus S = η1/η2. On substituting for η1 = 3 and η2 = 2, we get S = 3/2."
    },
    {
        "id": 762,
        "Question": "11.\tThe transmission coefficient of a wave travelling through two media having electric intrinsic impedances of 3 and 2 respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2⁄2",
            "b)\t8⁄9",
            "c)\t4⁄5",
            "d)\t1⁄4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The reflection coefficient in terms for intrinsic impedance is R= η2-η1/η2+η1. On substituting the given data, we get R = 5 – 3/5 + 3 = 2/8 = ¼."
    },
    {
        "id": 763,
        "Question": "12.\tThe transmission coefficient of a wave travelling through two media having electric intrinsic impedances of 3 and 4 respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2⁄3",
            "b)\t8⁄9",
            "c)\t2⁄5",
            "d)\t6⁄7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The reflection coefficient in terms for magnetic intrinsic impedance is R = η1 – η2/η1 + η2. On substituting the given data, we get R = 2 – 1/2 + 1 = 1/3."
    },
    {
        "id": 764,
        "Question": "1.\tThe skin effect is a phenomenon observed in",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tInsulators",
            "b)\tDielectrics",
            "c)\tConductors",
            "d)\tSemiconductors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The skin of the conductor allows a certain amount of electromagnetic power to pass through it. This phenomenon is called the skin effect. This is the reason why, electromagnetic waves cannot travel inside a conductor."
    },
    {
        "id": 765,
        "Question": "2.\tThe skin depth is measured in",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMeter",
            "b)\tMillimetre",
            "c)\tCentimetre",
            "d)\tMicrometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The depth to which the electromagnetic waves pass through the conductor is very small. It is measured in μm."
    },
    {
        "id": 766,
        "Question": "4.\tThe attenuation constant is 0.5 units. The skin depth will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.5",
            "b)\t0.25",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The skin depth is the measure of the depth to which the amplitude of an EM wave will reduce to 36.8% of its initial value. Thus it can be calculated if the initial amplitude is known."
    },
    {
        "id": 767,
        "Question": "5.\tCalculate the skin depth of a conductor, having a conductivity of 200 units. The wave frequency is 10 GHz in air.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t355.8",
            "b)\t3.558",
            "c)\t35.58",
            "d)\t0.3558"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The skin depth is the reciprocal of the attenuation constant. Thus δ = 1/α. On substituting for α = 0.5, we get δ = 1/0.5 = 2 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 768,
        "Question": "6.\tThe effective skin resistance of a material with conductivity 120 and skin depth of 2μm is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t4.16 kilo ohm",
            "b)\t4.16 mega ohm",
            "c)\t41.6 kilo ohm",
            "d)\t41.6 mega ohm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The skin depth is calculated by δ = 1/√(πfμσ), where f is the frequency, μ is the permeability and σ is the conductivity. For the given data, f = 10 x 109, μ = 4π x 10-7 in air and σ = 200, we get δ = 355.8 μm."
    },
    {
        "id": 769,
        "Question": "7.\tThe skin depth is used to find which parameter?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDC resistance",
            "b)\tAC resistance",
            "c)\tPermittivity",
            "d)\tPotential"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The effective skin resistance is given by Rs = 1/δσ, where δ is the skin depth and σ is the conductivity. For the given data, δ = 2 x 10-6 and σ = 120, we get Rs = 1/(120x2x10-6) = 4.16 kilo ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 770,
        "Question": "8.\tThe relation between the skin depth and frequency is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSkin depth α f",
            "b)\tSkin depth α 1/f",
            "c)\tSkin depth α √f",
            "d)\tSkin depth α 1/√f"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Since the skin depth varies for different frequencies, it can be used to calculate the varying AC resistance for a material."
    },
    {
        "id": 771,
        "Question": "9.\tA perfect dielectric acts as a",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPerfect transmitter",
            "b)\tPerfect reflector",
            "c)\tBad transmitter",
            "d)\tBad reflector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The skin depth is given by δ = 1/√(πfμσ). Thus the relation between the skin depth and the frequency is, Skin depth α 1/√f."
    },
    {
        "id": 772,
        "Question": "10.\tA perfect conductor acts as a",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPerfect transmitter",
            "b)\tPerfect reflector",
            "c)\tBad transmitter",
            "d)\tBad reflector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A perfect dielectric acts as a perfect transmitter. In other words, a wave incident on a perfect dielectric will transmit completely through it."
    },
    {
        "id": 773,
        "Question": "11.\tThe resultant electric field of two components in the x and y direction having amplitudes 6 and 8 respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t100",
            "b)\t36",
            "c)\t64",
            "d)\t10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A perfect conductor acts as a perfect reflector. In other words, a wave incident on a perfect conductor will be totally reflected back into the same medium. There will be no skin effect."
    },
    {
        "id": 774,
        "Question": "12.\tThe skin depth of the wave having a frequency of 3MHz and a velocity of 12 m/s is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t3",
            "c)\t4",
            "d)\t6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The resultant electric field of two components is given by E = √(Ex2 + Ey2). For the given data, the electric field will be E = √(62+82) = 10 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 775,
        "Question": "1.\tIdentify which of the following is not a transmission line?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTelephone lines",
            "b)\tPower transmission",
            "c)\tUnderground cables",
            "d)\tCavity resonators"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The types of transmission line are telephone lines, power transmission lines, underground cables, coaxial cables, fibre optic cable transmission etc. Cavity resonators are not transmission lines, they are components that aid maximum transmission."
    },
    {
        "id": 776,
        "Question": "2.\tThe open wire transmission line consists of",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConductor",
            "b)\tDielectric",
            "c)\tBoth conductor and dielectric",
            "d)\tEither conductor or dielectric"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The open wire is a common form of transmission line. The open wire consists of conductors. The conductors of such lines are considered to be parallel and separated by a dielectric."
    },
    {
        "id": 777,
        "Question": "4.\tThe cable transmission line consists of",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConductors",
            "b)\tInsulators",
            "c)\tInsulated conductors",
            "d)\tInsulated conductors with dielectric"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The open wire lines are long and used for distant wired communication. Such lines are telephone and power lines."
    },
    {
        "id": 778,
        "Question": "6.\tThe coaxial cable consists of",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConductors",
            "b)\tDielectric",
            "c)\tConductor with dielectric",
            "d)\tTwo conductors with dielectric"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cable lines are underground transmission lines. The line consists of hundreds of individual paper insulated conductors twisted in pairs and combined inside a protective lead or plastic sheath, which is usually a solid dielectric."
    },
    {
        "id": 779,
        "Question": "7.\tThe coaxial cable are used in",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTelephone cables transmission",
            "b)\tPower transmission",
            "c)\tTelevision signal transmission",
            "d)\tShort wave transmission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In all the transmission lines, the conductors are considered to be parallel with a solid dielectric."
    },
    {
        "id": 780,
        "Question": "8.\tIdentify which is not a type of waveguide.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRectangular",
            "b)\tCircular",
            "c)\tCylindrical",
            "d)\tCavity resonator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The coaxial cable consists of a hollow conductor and the second conductor is located inside and coaxial with the tube. The dielectric may be solid or gaseous."
    },
    {
        "id": 781,
        "Question": "9.\tThe range of frequencies handled by the waveguides is in",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tHz",
            "b)\tKHz",
            "c)\tMHz",
            "d)\tGHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Practically, the coaxial cables are employed in the transmission of the television signals from the dish antenna to the transponder."
    },
    {
        "id": 782,
        "Question": "10.\tThe range of frequencies operated by the coaxial cables is in",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tHz",
            "b)\tkHz",
            "c)\tMHz",
            "d)\tGHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rectangular waveguide is a commonly used waveguide. Cylindrical and circular waveguides are the same. Cavity resonator is not a waveguide. "
    },
    {
        "id": 783,
        "Question": "11.\tThe cut off frequency for waveguide operation is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2 MHz",
            "b)\t6 GHz",
            "c)\t4 MHz",
            "d)\t6 MHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The waveguides are operated in the GHz range. In particular, the waveguides are active above 6 GHz. The range goes upto several tens of GHz. Beyond this range, the transmission is handled by optic fibre cables."
    },
    {
        "id": 784,
        "Question": "12.\tThe highest means of communication is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tInternet",
            "b)\tTelephone",
            "c)\tTelevision",
            "d)\tRadio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Coaxial cables are operated in the MHz range. The main application includes television cable line transmission."
    },
    {
        "id": 785,
        "Question": "1.\tThe transmission line is said to be lossless when the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConductor is perfect and dielectric is lossless",
            "b)\tConductor is perfect and dielectric is lossy",
            "c)\tConductor is imperfect and dielectric is lossy",
            "d)\tConductor is imperfect and dielectric is lossless"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lossless transmission line refers to a line with no losses or attenuation. This is possible only when the conductor is perfect and the dielectric is lossless."
    },
    {
        "id": 786,
        "Question": "2.\tThe resistance of a lossless transmission line is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t-1",
            "d)\tInfinity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The lossless transmission line will have minimal loss of power. Thus in the ideal cases, the resistance is assumed to be zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 787,
        "Question": "3.\tWhich two parameters given below are zero in the lossless line?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tL, C",
            "b)\tC, G",
            "c)\tG, α",
            "d)\tR, L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Due to the minimal losses in the lossless transmission line, the parameters of conductance and attenuation constant are assumed to be zero. Practically, a lossless line is not possible."
    },
    {
        "id": 788,
        "Question": "4.\tThe characteristic impedance of the line having primary constants L and C as 35 milli henry and 70 micro farad respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t500",
            "b)\t22.36",
            "c)\t125",
            "d)\t50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The characteristic impedance of a lossless line is given by Zo = √(L/C). On substituting for L = 35 x 10-3 and C = 70 x 10-6, we get Zo = √(500) = 22. 36 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 789,
        "Question": "5.\tThe attenuation constant is measured in the units of",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tOhm",
            "b)\tNeper",
            "c)\tDecibel",
            "d)\tRadian/sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The attenuation is the loss of power due to the transmission. It is measured in the Neper units. 1 neper = 8.68 decibel/m."
    },
    {
        "id": 790,
        "Question": "6.\tThe velocity of the transmission line with a frequency of 35 radian/s and phase constant of 68.5 is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.95",
            "b)\t2.36",
            "c)\t4.56",
            "d)\t3.48"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The velocity of the wave in a transmission line is the ratio of the frequency to the phase constant. Thus v = ω/β. On substituting for ω = 35 and β = 68.5, we get v = 68.5/35 = 1.95 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 791,
        "Question": "7.\tThe condition that holds good in a distortionless transmission line is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tR/L = G/C",
            "b)\tRL = GC",
            "c)\tL/R = C/G",
            "d)\tRG/LC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a distortionless transmission line, the primary constants are related by R/L = G/C."
    },
    {
        "id": 792,
        "Question": "8.\tGiven that R = 20 ohm, L = 40 mH, C = 40 μF, G = 0.02 mho. Find whether the line is distortionless or not.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDistorted line",
            "b)\tDistortionless line",
            "c)      All of the mentioned",
            "d)       None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For a distortionless line, the condition R/L = G/C must be true. On substituting for R = 20, L = 40 mH, C = 40 μF, G = 0.02, we get R/L = 500 and G/C = 500. Thus the line is distortionless."
    },
    {
        "id": 793,
        "Question": "9.\tFor R= 20 ohm and G= 0.8 mho, the attenuation constant will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t16",
            "b)\t4",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\t32"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The attenuation constant is given by α = √(RG), where R and G is the resistance and conductance respectively. On substituting for R = 20 and G = 0.8, we get α = √(20 x 0.8) = 4 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 794,
        "Question": "10.\tThe velocity of an electromagnetic wave with frequency 6MHz and a skin depth of 1.6 μm.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3.75",
            "b)\t0.26",
            "c)\t9.6",
            "d)\t7.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The velocity of a wave is the product of the frequency and the skin depth. It is given v = f. δ. On substituting for f = 6 x 106 and δ = 1.6 x 10-6, we get v = 6 x 106 x 1.6 x 10-6 = 9.6 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 795,
        "Question": "11.\tThe characteristic impedance of the transmission line with R= 45 ohm and G= 0.45 mho is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t100",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t0.1",
            "d)\t10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The characteristic impedance in terms of R, G is Zo = √(R/G). On substituting for R = 45 and G = 0.45, we get Zo = 10 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 796,
        "Question": "1.\tThe Smith chart is a polar chart which plots",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tR vs Z",
            "b)\tR vs Znorm",
            "c)\tT vs Z",
            "d)\tT vs Znorm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Smith chart is a frequency domain plot. It is the polar chart of the reflection coefficient R with respect to the normalised impedance Znorm."
    },
    {
        "id": 797,
        "Question": "3.\tThe Smith chart consists of the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConstant R and variable X circles",
            "b)\tVariable R and constant X circles",
            "c)\tConstant R and constant X circles",
            "d)\tVariable R and variable X circles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Smith chart is used for calculating the reflection coefficient and standing wave ratio for normalised load impedance of a transmission line."
    },
    {
        "id": 798,
        "Question": "4.\tThe circles in the Smith chart pass through which point?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t(0,1)",
            "b)\t(0,-1)",
            "c)\t(-1,0)",
            "d)\t(1,0)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Smith chart consists of the constant resistance circles and the constant reactance circles. The impedances are plotted using these circles. Also stub matching can be done using the Smith chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 799,
        "Question": "5.\tMoving towards the clockwise direction in the Smith chart implies moving",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTowards generator",
            "b)\tTowards load",
            "c)\tTowards stub",
            "d)\tTowards waveguide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the constant resistance and reactance circles in the Smith chart pass through the (1,0) point. This is the midpoint of the Smith Chart. The resistance is unity and reactance is zero at this point."
    },
    {
        "id": 800,
        "Question": "6.\tThe centre of the point having a normalised resistance of 1.2 ohm and reactance of 1.5 ohm is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t(0.54,0)",
            "b)\t(0.45,0)",
            "c)\t(0.36,0)",
            "d)\t(0.78,0)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: On moving towards the clockwise direction in the Smith chart, we are traversing towards the generator. This is used to calculate the normalised load impedance. "
    },
    {
        "id": 801,
        "Question": "7.\tThe normalised load impedance of the transmission line 50 ohm with a load of 30 ohm is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t30",
            "b)\t150",
            "c)\t5/3",
            "d)\t3/5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The centre of a point in Smith chart is given by C = (r/1+r, 0). On substituting for r = 1.2, we get centre as (1.2/1+1.2,0) = (0.54,0)."
    },
    {
        "id": 802,
        "Question": "8.\tThe radius of the point having a normalised resistance of 1 ohm is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t0.2",
            "c)\t0.5",
            "d)\t0.25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The normalised impedance is calculated by dividing the impedance with the characteristic impedance. Given that the load impedance is 30 ohm, the normalised load impedance of the 50 ohm transmission line is 30/50 = 3/5 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 803,
        "Question": "9.\tThe best stub selection for the transmission line will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSeries open",
            "b)\tSeries short",
            "c)\tShunt open",
            "d)\tShunt short"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The radius of the point with a radius r is given by R = 1/r+1. On substituting for r = 1, we get R = 1/1 + 1 = ½ = 0.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 804,
        "Question": "10.\tThe centre and radius of a line with normalised load impedance of 1 + 0.5j is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t(1,2) and 2",
            "b)\t(2,1) and 2",
            "c)\t(1,2) and 1",
            "d)\t(2,1) and 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Normally series stubs are not preferred as modification of the stub parameters requires changing the whole stub setup. Shunt stubs enable modification with ease. Open circuited stubs are not preferred as it will radiate power like an antenna, which is undesirable. Hence shorted stubs are used."
    },
    {
        "id": 805,
        "Question": "1.\tThe open circuit impedance of the transmission line is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tZOC = j Zo tan βl",
            "b)\tZOC = – j Zo tan βl",
            "c)\tZOC = j Zo cot βl",
            "d)\tZOC = -j Zo cot βl"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The open circuit in a transmission line refers to the load side open circuited. In this case, the load impedance will be infinite. Thus the transmission line equation will be ZOC = -j Zo cot βl."
    },
    {
        "id": 806,
        "Question": "2.\tThe short circuit impedance of the transmission line is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tZSC = j Zo tan βl",
            "b)\tZSC = -j Zo tan βl",
            "c)\tZSC = j Zo cot βl",
            "d)\tZSC = -j Zo cot βl"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The short circuit in a transmission line refers to the load side shorted. In this case, the load impedance will be zero. Thus the transmission line equation will be ZSC = j Zo tan βl."
    },
    {
        "id": 807,
        "Question": "3.\tIn a shorted line, the reflection coefficient will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t-1",
            "d)\t∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The shorted line will absorb more power than any other line. Thus the reflection coefficient is considered to be negative."
    },
    {
        "id": 808,
        "Question": "4.\tThe open circuit line will have a reflection coefficient of",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t-1",
            "d)\t∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An open circuit line has infinite output impedance. Any wave incident at the output will be completely reflected. Thus the reflection coefficient is unity."
    },
    {
        "id": 809,
        "Question": "5.\tThe standing wave ratio in short and open circuit transmission lines will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t-1",
            "c)\t1",
            "d)\t∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The reflection coefficient is 1 and -1 in open and shorted lines respectively. This value of reflection coefficient will yield infinite standing wave ratio. "
    },
    {
        "id": 810,
        "Question": "6.\tThe characteristic impedance of a line having open and short impedances of 20 and 5 respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t20",
            "b)\t100",
            "c)\t25",
            "d)\t10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The characteristic impedance is the geometric mean of the short and open circuit impedance. It is given by Zo2 = Zsc Zoc. On substituting Zoc = 20 and Zsc = 5, we get Zo2 = 20 X 5 = 100. Thus Zo = 10 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 811,
        "Question": "7.\tThe short circuit impedance is given by 18 ohm and the characteristic impedance is 50 ohm. Find the open circuit impedance.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t138.8",
            "b)\t188.3",
            "c)\t388.1",
            "d)\t838.1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The relation between characteristic impedance, open and short impedance is given by Zo2 = Zsc Zoc. For the given values Zo = 50 and Zsc = 18, we get Zoc = 502/18 = 138.8 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 812,
        "Question": "8.\tFor maximum power transfer theorem to be applied to the transmission line, the reflection coefficient has to be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t-1",
            "c)\t0",
            "d)\t∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Maximum power transfer between the load and source is possible, only when both are matched. This will lead to no reflections. Thus the reflection coefficient will be zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 813,
        "Question": "9.\tFind the transmission coefficient of a 75 ohm line with load impedance of 40 ohm.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.69",
            "b)\t0.96",
            "c)\t0.31",
            "d)\t0.13"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The transmission coefficient in terms of the load impedance is given by T = ZL/Z0. On substituting for ZL = 40 and Zo = 75, we get T = 40/75 = 0.69."
    },
    {
        "id": 814,
        "Question": "The standing wave ratio for the maximum power transfer in a transmission line is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1:2",
            "b) 2:1",
            "c) -1:1",
            "d) 1:1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  The open circuit voltage and short circuit current will be same for a transmission line. The phase difference is λ/8."
    },
    {
        "id": 815,
        "Question": "1.\tThe phenomenon employed in the waveguide operation is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tReflection",
            "b)\tRefraction",
            "c)\tTotal internal reflection",
            "d)\tAdsorption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The waveguides use total internal reflection phenomenon to transmit the waves passing through it. Thus the acceptance angle and critical angle are important for effective transmission."
    },
    {
        "id": 816,
        "Question": "2.\tThe dominant mode in waveguide is the mode which has",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tHighest frequency",
            "b)\tHighest wavelength",
            "c)\tLowest phase constant",
            "d)\tHighest attenuation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The dominant mode is the mode which has the minimum frequency or maximum wavelength available for propagation of the waves."
    },
    {
        "id": 817,
        "Question": "3.\t The modes are calculated from which parameter?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tFrequency",
            "b)\tWavelength",
            "c)\tPhase constant",
            "d)\tV number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The modes are calculated from the V number of the waveguides. It is given by M= V2/2."
    },
    {
        "id": 818,
        "Question": "4.\tThe circular waveguides use which function in the frequency calculation?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLaplace function",
            "b)\tSchottky function",
            "c)\tBessel function",
            "d)\tTransfer function"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The circular or cylindrical waveguides use the Bessel function for the frequency calculation of a particular mode."
    },
    {
        "id": 819,
        "Question": "5.\tThe scattering parameters are used to indicate the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPermittivity and permeability",
            "b)\tElectric and magnetic field intensities",
            "c)\tReflection and transmission coefficients",
            "d)\tFrequency and wavelength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The scattering matrix consists of the transmission coefficients in the main diagonal and the reflection coefficients in the opposite diagonal."
    },
    {
        "id": 820,
        "Question": "6.\tWhich of the following two parameter models cannot be used to represent a transmission line?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tH parameter model",
            "b)\tT parameter model",
            "c)\tABCD parameter model",
            "d)\tS parameter model"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The T, ABCD and S parameter models are used in the transmission line modelling. The h parameter is not used for the same."
    },
    {
        "id": 821,
        "Question": "7.\tFor the matched line, the parameters S12 and S21 are",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t0",
            "c)\t-1",
            "d)\t∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The parameters S12 and S21 are the reflection coefficients. For a matched line, the reflection coefficients are zero. Thus the parameters S12 and S21 are also zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 822,
        "Question": "8.\tThe waveguides are materials with characteristics of",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLow bulk resistivity",
            "b)\tHigh bulk resistivity",
            "c)\tHigh conductivity",
            "d)\tLow conductivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Generally, the waveguides are made of materials with low bulk resistivity like brass, copper, silver etc. But if the interior walls are properly plated, it is possible with poor conductivity materials too. It is even possible to make plastic waveguides."
    },
    {
        "id": 823,
        "Question": "1.\tThe waveguide is employed in the transmission lines, when operated at the range of",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tHz",
            "b)\tKHz",
            "c)\tMHz",
            "d)\tGHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Waveguides are employed for effective transmission, when the lines carry electromagnetic waves in the GHz range."
    },
    {
        "id": 824,
        "Question": "2.\tThe cut off frequency for a waveguide to operate is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3 MHz",
            "b)\t3 GHz",
            "c)\t6 MHz",
            "d)\t6 GHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cut off frequency of the waveguide is 6 GHz. This is the frequency at which the waveguide will start to operate."
    },
    {
        "id": 825,
        "Question": "3.\tIn rectangular waveguides, the dimensions a and b represent the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBroad wall dimensions",
            "b)\tBroad wall and side wall dimension respectively",
            "c)\tSide wall and broad wall dimension respectively",
            "d)\tSide wall dimensions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In rectangular waveguide, the a parameter is the broad wall dimension of the waveguide and the b parameter is the side wall dimension of the waveguide. Always, a > b in a waveguide."
    },
    {
        "id": 826,
        "Question": "4.\tThe Bessel function is denoted by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tJn(ha)",
            "b)\tJm(ha)",
            "c)\tJn(hb)",
            "d)\tJm(hb)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Bessel function is used in the circular waveguides. Normally Jn(ha) = 0. Here n is the order of the Bessel function."
    },
    {
        "id": 827,
        "Question": "5.\tIn a waveguide, always which condition holds good?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tphase velocity = c",
            "b)\tphase velocity greater than c",
            "c)\tphase velocity lesser than c",
            "d)\tgroup velocity = c"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In air medium, the phase velocity is assumed to be the speed of light. For waveguides, the phase velocity is always greater than the speed of the light."
    },
    {
        "id": 828,
        "Question": "7.\tFind the group wavelength of a wave, given that the group phase constant is 6.28 units.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t3.14",
            "c)\t6.28",
            "d)\t1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In a waveguide, the phase velocity is greater than the velocity of light. Thus the group velocity will be less. This implies the group wavelength will be greater than the wavelength at any point."
    },
    {
        "id": 829,
        "Question": "8.\tThe phase velocity of a wave with frequency of 15 radian/sec and group phase constant of 2 units is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t30",
            "b)\t15",
            "c)\t7.5",
            "d)\t2/15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The group wavelength is given by λg = 2π/βg, where βg is the group wavelength of the wave. On substituting for βg = 6.28, we get group wavelength as unity."
    },
    {
        "id": 830,
        "Question": "9.\tThe modes in a material having a V number of 20 is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t20",
            "b)\t400",
            "c)\t200",
            "d)\t100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The phase velocity of a wave is given by Vp = ω/βg. on substituting for ω = 15 and βg = 2, we get phase velocity as 15/2 = 7.5 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 831,
        "Question": "10.\tThe number of modes is given as 50, find the V number.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t5",
            "b)\t10",
            "c)\t50",
            "d)\t2500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The relation between the modes and the V number is given by m = v2/2. Given that v = 20, we get m = 202/2 = 200 modes."
    },
    {
        "id": 832,
        "Question": "1.\tThe real part of the propagation constant is the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAttenuation constant",
            "b)\tPhase constant",
            "c)\tPermittivity",
            "d)\tPermeability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The propagation constant is given by γ = α + jβ. Here the real part is the attenuation constant and the imaginary part is the phase constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 833,
        "Question": "2.\tThe phase constant of a wave is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tω√(LC)",
            "b)\tω√(L/C)",
            "c)\tω√(C/L)",
            "d)\tω√(1/LC)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The phase constant of a wave in a transmission line is given by β = ω√(LC), where L and C are the specifications of the line."
    },
    {
        "id": 834,
        "Question": "3.\tThe cut off frequency of the dominant mode in a TE wave in the line having a and b as 2.5 cm and 1 cm respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t4.5 GHz",
            "b)\t5 GHz",
            "c)\t5.5 GHz",
            "d)\t6 GHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The dominant mode in TE is TE10. The cut off frequency will be mc/2a, where m = 1 and a = 0.025 are given. On substituting, we get the frequency as 1 x 3 x 108/2 x 0.025 = 6 GHz."
    },
    {
        "id": 835,
        "Question": "4.\tThe cut off frequency of the TE01 mode will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tmc/2a",
            "b)\tmc/2b",
            "c)\tnc/2a",
            "d)\tnc/2b"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cut off frequency consists of modes m and n. For m = 0, the dimension b will be considered. Thus the frequency is nc/2b, where c is the speed of the light."
    },
    {
        "id": 836,
        "Question": "5.\tThe condition which will satisfy the dimensions of the waveguide is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\ta = b",
            "b)\ta > b",
            "c)\ta < b",
            "d)\tab = 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The dimensions a and b represent the broad wall and the side wall dimensions respectively. The broad wall will be greater than the side wall. Thus the condition a>b is true."
    },
    {
        "id": 837,
        "Question": "6.\tThe cut off wavelength of the TE10 mode having a broad wall dimension of 5cm is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.1",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t10",
            "d)\t0.01"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cut off wavelength of the waveguide is given by λc = 2a/m. on substituting for a = 0.05 and m = 1, we get λc = 2 x 0.05/1 = 0.1 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 838,
        "Question": "7.\tThe broad wall dimension of a waveguide having a cut off frequency of 7.5 GHz is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t2",
            "c)\t3",
            "d)\t4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cut off frequency and the broad wall dimension are related by fc = mc/2a. On substituting for m = 1 and fc = 7.5 GHz, we get a = 0.02  or 2 cm."
    },
    {
        "id": 839,
        "Question": "8.\tThe sin θ in the waveguide refers to the ratio of the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tFrequency to wavelength",
            "b)\tWavelength to frequency",
            "c)\tCut off frequency to frequency",
            "d)\tFrequency to cut off frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The ratio of the cut off frequency to the frequency at any point gives the sin θ in a waveguide."
    },
    {
        "id": 840,
        "Question": "10.\tThe dimension for a waveguide in dominant mode with a cut off wavelength of 2 units is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2",
            "b)\t4",
            "c)\t6",
            "d)\t8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cut off frequency for waveguide operation is 6 GHz. Thus a wave of 5 GHz is not possible for transmission in a waveguide."
    },
    {
        "id": 841,
        "Question": "11.\tThe waveguides are used in a transmission line for",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIncreasing transmission coefficient",
            "b)\tIncreasing reflection coefficient",
            "c)\tDecreasing transmission coefficient",
            "d)\tDecreasing reflection coefficient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cut off wavelength of a waveguide is given by λc = 2a/m. For the dominant mode, m = 1. Given that λc = 2, thus we get a = 4 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 842,
        "Question": "12.\tThe attenuation coefficient of the wave having a resistance of 15 ohm in a 50 ohm line is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t15",
            "b)\t1.5",
            "c)\t0.15",
            "d)\t0.015"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The waveguides are used to increase the transmission efficiency of the waves travelling through it."
    },
    {
        "id": 843,
        "Question": "1.\tIn transverse electric waves, which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tE is parallel to H",
            "b)\tE is parallel to wave direction",
            "c)\tE is transverse to wave direction",
            "d)\tH is transverse to wave direction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In TE waves, the electric field strength will be transverse to the wave direction. Thus the TE waves are also called H waves."
    },
    {
        "id": 844,
        "Question": "2.\tThe dominant mode in rectangular waveguide is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTE01",
            "b)\tTE10",
            "c)\tTM01",
            "d)\tTM10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: TE10 is the dominant mode in the rectangular waveguide. This is because it gives the minimum cut off frequency required for transmission."
    },
    {
        "id": 845,
        "Question": "3.\tThe number of modes in a waveguide having a V number of 10 is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t10",
            "b)\t25",
            "c)\t100",
            "d)\t50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The number of modes is given by m = V2/2, where V is the v number. On substituting for V = 10, we get m = 100/2 = 50."
    },
    {
        "id": 846,
        "Question": "5.\tThe mode which has the highest wavelength is called",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDominant mode",
            "b)\tEvanescent mode",
            "c)\tGenerate mode",
            "d)\tDegenerate mode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For a waveguide, the dimension a should be greater than b. Here a = 3 and b = 5.5, thus such waveguide does not exist."
    },
    {
        "id": 847,
        "Question": "6.\tThe intrinsic impedance of a TE wave having a cut off frequency of 6 GHz at a frequency of 7.5 GHz in air is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t628.33",
            "b)\t338.62",
            "c)\t498.76",
            "d)\t342.24"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dominant modes are the modes having least cut off frequency. This implies they have highest cut off wavelength."
    },
    {
        "id": 848,
        "Question": "7.\tThe cut off frequency of a rectangular waveguide of dimensions 3 cm x 1.5 cm is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t12 GHz",
            "b)\t6 GHz",
            "c)\t4 GHz",
            "d)\t5 GHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The intrinsic impedance of a TE wave is given by ηTE = η/cos θ, where cos θ is given by √(1- (fc/f)2). On substituting for fc = 6 GHz, f = 7.5 GHz and η = 377, we get the intrinsic impedance as 628.33 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 849,
        "Question": "8.\tThe propagation constant for a lossless transmission line will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tReal",
            "b)\tComplex",
            "c)\tReal and equal to phase constant",
            "d)\tComplex and equal to phase constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cut off frequency in dominant mode will be fc = mc/2a. On substituting for c = 3 x 108 and a = 0.03, we get the cut off frequency as 5 GHz."
    },
    {
        "id": 850,
        "Question": "9.\tThe attenuation of a 50 ohm transmission line having a resistance of 100 ohm is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.01",
            "b)\t0.1",
            "c)\t1",
            "d)\t10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The propagation constant is given by γ = α + jβ, where α and β are the attenuation and phase constants respectively. For a lossless line, the attenuation constant is zero. Thus γ = jβ. It is clear that γ is complex and equal to β."
    },
    {
        "id": 851,
        "Question": "10.\tThe cut off frequency of a TE wave with waveguide dimension of a= 3.5 cm in a medium of permittivity 2.2 is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2.88 GHz",
            "b)\t3.32 GHz",
            "c)\t4.5 GHz",
            "d)\t2.12 GHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The attenuation of a wave is given by α = R/2Z0. On substituting for R = 100 and Z0 = 50, we get α = 100/(2 x 50) = 1 unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 852,
        "Question": "11.\tThe phase constant and frequency are related by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPhase constant α ω",
            "b)\tPhase constant α 1/ω",
            "c)\tPhase constant α 1/2ω",
            "d)\tPhase constant α ω/2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cut off frequency of a TE wave in any other medium is mc/2a√εr. On substituting for a = 0.035 and εr = 2.2, we get the cut off frequency as 2.88 GHz."
    },
    {
        "id": 853,
        "Question": "12.\tWhich of the following parameter is non zero for a lossless line?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAttenuation",
            "b)\tResistance",
            "c)\tConductance",
            "d)\tPhase constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The phase constant is given by β = ω√LC. Thus the relation is β is directly proportional to ω."
    },
    {
        "id": 854,
        "Question": "1.\tIn transverse magnetic waves, which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tE is parallel to H",
            "b)\tH is parallel to wave direction",
            "c)\tH is transverse to wave direction",
            "d)\tE is transverse to H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In transverse magnetic waves, the magnetic field strength is transverse to the wave direction. They are also called E waves."
    },
    {
        "id": 855,
        "Question": "2.\tThe dominant mode in the TM waves is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTM01",
            "b)\tTM10",
            "c)\tTM20",
            "d)\tTM11"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The modes TM10, TM01 and TM20 does not exist in any waveguide. The TM11 mode is the dominant mode in the waveguide."
    },
    {
        "id": 856,
        "Question": "3.\tThe modes in a waveguide having a V number of 20 is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t400",
            "b)\t200",
            "c)\t100",
            "d)\t40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The number of modes in a waveguide is given by m = V2/2. On substituting for V = 20, we get m = 400/2 = 200 modes."
    },
    {
        "id": 857,
        "Question": "4.\tThe v number of a waveguide having 120 modes is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t15.5",
            "b)\t18",
            "c)\t24",
            "d)\t12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The number of modes in a waveguide is given by m = V2/2. On substituting for m = 120, we get V = √(2 x 120) = 15.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 858,
        "Question": "5.\tThe intrinsic impedance of a TM wave will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGreater than 377 ohm",
            "b)\tEqual to 377 ohm",
            "c)\tLesser than 377 ohm",
            "d)\tDoes not exist"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The intrinsic impedance of the transverse magnetic wave is given by ηTM = η √(1-(fc/f)2). Here the term √(1-(fc/f)2) is always lesser than unity. Thus the intrinsic impedance of the TM wave is lesser than 377 ohms."
    },
    {
        "id": 859,
        "Question": "6.\tThe modes TMmo and TMon are called",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGenerate modes",
            "b)\tDegenerate modes",
            "c)\tDominant modes",
            "d)\tEvanescent modes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The modes TMmo and TMon does not exist. These modes are said to be evanescent mode."
    },
    {
        "id": 860,
        "Question": "7.\tTwo modes with same cut off frequency are said to be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGenerate modes",
            "b)\tDominant modes",
            "c)\tDegenerate modes",
            "d)\tRegenerate modes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Two modes with same cut off frequency are called as degenerate modes. These modes have same field distribution."
    },
    {
        "id": 861,
        "Question": "9.\tThe boundary between the Fresnel and Fraunhofer zones having a length of 12 units and a wavelength of 3 units is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t96",
            "b)\t48",
            "c)\t192",
            "d)\t36"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Modes in the format of TMmo and TMon does not exist. The given mode is in the form of TMmo, which is does not exist. It is an evanescent mode."
    },
    {
        "id": 862,
        "Question": "10.\tThe reflection coefficient, when a resonant cavity is placed between the waveguide is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t-1",
            "d)\tInfinite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Fresnel- Fraunhofer boundary is related by the wavelength as R = 2L2/λ. On substituting for L = 12 and λ = 3, we get R = 2 x 122/3 = 96 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 863,
        "Question": "11.\tThe distance between two terminated plates is given by the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGuided wavelength",
            "b)\t2(guided wavelength)",
            "c)\tGuided wavelength/2",
            "d)\t(Guided wavelength)/4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the waveguide is shorted by conducting plates, the reflection coefficient will be unity. This will lead to the occurrence of standing waves. "
    },
    {
        "id": 864,
        "Question": "12.\tFind the guided wavelength if the distance between the two conducting plates in the waveguide is 2 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t4cm",
            "b)\t2cm",
            "c)\t1cm",
            "d)\t0.5cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The distance between the terminating plates is given by Vmin = λg/2, where λg is the guided wavelength."
    },
    {
        "id": 865,
        "Question": "1.\tIn a transverse electric magnetic wave, which of the following will be true?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tE is transverse to H",
            "b)\tE is transverse to wave direction",
            "c)\tH is transverse to wave direction",
            "d)\tE and H are transverse to wave direction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the transverse electric magnetic wave (TEM wave), both the electric and magnetic field strengths are transverse to the wave propagation."
    },
    {
        "id": 866,
        "Question": "2.\tThe cut off frequency of the TEM wave is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1 GHz",
            "c)\t6 GHz",
            "d)\tinfinity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The TEM waves have both E and H perpendicular to the guide axis. Thus its cut off frequency is zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 867,
        "Question": "3.\tWhich component is non zero in a TEM wave?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tEx",
            "b)\tHz",
            "c)\tEz",
            "d)\tAttenuation constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In a TEM wave, the wave propagates along the guided axis. Thus the components Ez and Hz are zero. The attenuation is also zero. The non-zero component will be Ex."
    },
    {
        "id": 868,
        "Question": "5.\tThe cut off wavelength in the TEM wave will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\tNegative",
            "c)\tInfinity",
            "d)\t1/6 GHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rectangular waveguide does not allow the TEM wave. TEM mode can exist only in two conductor system and not in hollow waveguide in which the centre conductor does not exist."
    },
    {
        "id": 869,
        "Question": "6.\tThe guided wavelength of a TEM wave in a waveguide having a wavelength of 5 units is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\tInfinity",
            "c)\t5",
            "d)\t1/5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The cut off frequency in a TEM wave is zero. Thus the cut off wavelength will be infinity."
    },
    {
        "id": 870,
        "Question": "7.\tThe guided phase constant of a TEM wave in a waveguide with a phase constant of 2.8 units is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2.8",
            "b)\t1.4",
            "c)\t0",
            "d)\tInfinity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The guided wavelength is same as the wavelength of the waveguide with a TEM wave. Thus the guided wavelength is 5 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 871,
        "Question": "8.\tWhich type of transmission line accepts the TEM wave?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCopper cables",
            "b)\tCoaxial cable",
            "c)\tRectangular waveguides",
            "d)\tCircular waveguides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The guided phase constant is same as the phase constant of the waveguide. For the given data, the guided phase constant is 2.8 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 872,
        "Question": "9.\tFor a TEM wave to propagate in a medium, the medium has to be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAir",
            "b)\tInsulator",
            "c)\tDispersive",
            "d)\tNon dispersive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hollow transmission lines support TE and TM waves only. The TEM wave is possible only in the coaxial cable transmission line, which is not hollow."
    },
    {
        "id": 873,
        "Question": "1.\tIn a waveguide, which of the following condition is true always?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tphase velocity = c",
            "b)\tgroup velocity = c",
            "c)\tphase velocity > c",
            "d)\tphase velocity < c"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The phase velocity is always greater than the speed of light in waveguides. This implies the group velocity is small."
    },
    {
        "id": 874,
        "Question": "2.\tThe term cos θ is given by 2.5. Find the phase velocity.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3",
            "b)\t5",
            "c)\t7.5",
            "d)\t2.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The phase velocity is given by Vp = c cos θ. On substituting for cos θ = 2.5 and the speed of light, we get the phase velocity as 7.5 x 108 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 875,
        "Question": "3.\tThe cut off wavelength and the guided wavelength are given by 0.5 and 2 units respectively. Find the wavelength of the wave.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.48",
            "b)\t0.32",
            "c)\t0.45",
            "d)\t0.54"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cut off wavelength and the guided wavelength are related as (1/λ)2 = (1/λc)2 + (1/λg)2. On substituting for λc = 0.5 and λg = 2, we get λ = 0.48 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 876,
        "Question": "4.\tThe cut off wavelength of the rectangular waveguide in dominant mode with dimensions 6 cm x 4 cm is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t12cm",
            "b)\t6cm",
            "c)\t4cm",
            "d)\t2cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cut off wavelength in the dominant mode is given by λc = 2a/m, where a is the broad wall dimension. On substituting for m = 1 and a = 6cm, we get the cut off wavelength as 12cm."
    },
    {
        "id": 877,
        "Question": "5.\tThe product of the phase and the group velocities is given by the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSpeed of light",
            "b)\tSpeed of light/2",
            "c)\t2 x Speed of light",
            "d)\t(speed of light)/4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The product of the phase and the group velocities is given by the square of the speed of the light. Thus Vp x Vg = c2 is the relation."
    },
    {
        "id": 878,
        "Question": "6.\tThe phase velocity of a wave having a group velocity of 6 x 106 is (in order of 108 m/s)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2.4",
            "b)\t3",
            "c)\t15",
            "d)\t150"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: We know that the phase and the group velocities are given by Vp x Vg = c2. On substituting for Vg = 6 x 106 and the speed of light, we get Vp = 150 x 108 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 879,
        "Question": "7.\tThe group velocity of a wave with a phase velocity of 60 x 109 is (in 106 order)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.5",
            "b)\t2",
            "c)\t2.5",
            "d)\t3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We know that the phase and the group velocities are given by Vp x Vg = c2. On substituting for Vp = 60 x 109 and the speed of light, we get Vg = 1.5 x 106 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 880,
        "Question": "8.\tThe phase velocity of a wave having a phase constant of 4 units and a frequency of 2.5 x 109 radian/sec is (in 108 order)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3.25",
            "b)\t3.75",
            "c)\t6.25",
            "d)\t6.75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The phase velocity and the phase constant are related by Vp = ω/βg. On substituting for ω = 2.5 x 109 and β = 4, we get the phase velocity as 6.25 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 881,
        "Question": "9.\tThe guided wavelength and the phase constant are related by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t2π/βg = λg",
            "b)\t1/βg = λg",
            "c)\t1/2πβg = λg",
            "d)\tβg = λg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The guided wavelength and the phase constant are related by 2π/βg = λg, where βg is the guided phase constant and λg is the guided wavelength. "
    },
    {
        "id": 882,
        "Question": "11.\tThe phase and group velocities does not depend on which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tFrequency",
            "b)\tWavelength",
            "c)\tPhase constant",
            "d)\tAttenuation constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The phase velocity refers to a single wave and the group velocity refers to a group of waves."
    },
    {
        "id": 883,
        "Question": "12.\tThe distance between two successive points in a waveguide is the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGuided wavelength",
            "b)\t2 x guided wavelength",
            "c)\tGuided wavelength/2",
            "d)\t(guided wavelength)/4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The phase and the group velocities are directly related by the frequency, wavelength and the phase constant. It is independent of the attenuation constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 884,
        "Question": "1.\tThe source voltage of a 75ohm transmission line is given by 150V. Find the load current.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.5",
            "b)\t2",
            "c)\t4",
            "d)\t1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The load current is given by IL = VS/Z0. On substituting for VS = 150 and Z0 = 75, we get IL = 150/75= 2A."
    },
    {
        "id": 885,
        "Question": "2.\tThe guided terminations are used to",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIncrease reflection",
            "b)\tIncrease transmission",
            "c)\tEliminate reflection loss",
            "d)\tEliminate attenuation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The guided termination refers to the waveguide shorted by conducting plates. This is done in order to eliminate the reflection losses."
    },
    {
        "id": 886,
        "Question": "3.\tWhich type of wave does the resonant cavity produce?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tStanding waves",
            "b)\tGuided waves",
            "c)\tTransmitted waves",
            "d)\tAttenuated waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Resonant cavity is the waveguide shorted by a conducting plate. This is to reduce the reflection losses. Such arrangement leads to standing waves."
    },
    {
        "id": 887,
        "Question": "4.\tWhich of the following parameter cannot be calculated from the standing waves?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPeak voltage and peak current",
            "b)\tSWR",
            "c)\tReflection and transmission coefficients",
            "d)\tAttenuation constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "View AnswerAnswer: d\nExplanation: The peak voltage and current can be directly measured from the standing waves. The standing wave ratio, reflection coefficient and the transmission coefficient can also be calculated from it. Only the attenuation constant cannot be calculated directly."
    },
    {
        "id": 888,
        "Question": "5.\tFor efficient transmission, the characteristic impedance of the transmission line has to be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t50 ohm",
            "b)\t75 ohm",
            "c)\tEither 50 or 75 ohm",
            "d)\tNeither 50 nor 75 ohm"
        ],
        "Answer": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 889,
        "Question": "6.\tThe cavity resonators are used in the klystron amplifiers for",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAmplifying RF signals",
            "b)\tAmplifying microwave signals",
            "c)\tAttenuating RF signals",
            "d)\tAttenuating microwave signals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Generally, for ideal transmission lines, the characteristic impedance should be either 50 ohm or 75 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 890,
        "Question": "7.\tThe cavity resonators used in the reflex klystron oscillators are for",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGenerating RF signals",
            "b)\tGenerating microwave signals",
            "c)\tAmplifying RF signals",
            "d)\tAmplifying microwave signals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cavity resonators are employed in the klystron amplifiers for amplifying the microwave signals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 891,
        "Question": "9.\tCavity wave meters are used to measure which parameter of the wave?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tWavelength",
            "b)\tReflection factor",
            "c)\tPhase",
            "d)\tFrequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Oscillators are devices that generate signal waveforms. The reflex klystron oscillator is used to generate microwave signals."
    },
    {
        "id": 892,
        "Question": "10.\tThe waveguides are terminated by the procedure of",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTrimming",
            "b)\tPolishing",
            "c)\tTapering",
            "d)\tPruning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cavity resonator is used in duplexers of RADAR systems, as resonant cavity in transmit receive (TR) tubes and antitransmit receive (ART) tubes."
    },
    {
        "id": 893,
        "Question": "1.\tThe resonant circuit in a waveguide refers to the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTank circuit",
            "b)\tRC circuit",
            "c)\tBridge circuit",
            "d)\tAttenuator circuit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resonant circuit refers to the tank circuit. It is parallel combination of an inductor and a capacitor."
    },
    {
        "id": 894,
        "Question": "2.\tWhen a waveguide is terminated, the mode of the guided termination will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tzero",
            "b)\tnon-zero",
            "c)\tinfinite",
            "d)\tdoes not exist"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A waveguide mode with a guided termination is represented by TEmnp and TMmnp. Here m and n are the orders of the waveguide and p is the order of the resonant cavity. It is always a non-zero value."
    },
    {
        "id": 895,
        "Question": "3.\tThe cut off frequency of a waveguide with resonant cavity is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tV√((m/a)2 + (n/b)2 + (p/d)2)/2",
            "b)\tV√((m/a)2 + (n/b)2 + (p/d)2)",
            "c)\t2V√((m/a)2 + (n/b)2 + (p/d)2)",
            "d)\tV√((m/a) + (n/b) + (p/d))/2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cut off frequency of the waveguide of dimensions a x b with the resonant cavity of dimension d is given by fc = √((m/a)2 + (n/b)2 + (p/d)2)/2. Here m and n are the orders of the waveguide, p is the order of the cavity and v is the velocity."
    },
    {
        "id": 896,
        "Question": "4.\tThe power of a wave in a transmission line, when the current and the resistance are 5A and 120 ohm respectively is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3000",
            "b)\t4000",
            "c)\t2000",
            "d)\t1500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The power of a line is given by P = I2R. On substituting for I = 5 and R = 120, we get P = 52 x 120 = 3000 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 897,
        "Question": "5.\tThe power of a wave having a magnetic field intensity of 2.5 units is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1.17 kilo watt",
            "b)\t1.17 mega watt",
            "c)\t1.17 watt",
            "d)\t11.7 watt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The power of a wave is given by P = 0.5 η H2, where η is the intrinsic impedance and H is the magnetic field intensity. On substituting for η = 377 and H = 2.5, we get P = 0.5 x 377 x 2.52 = 1.17 kilo watts."
    },
    {
        "id": 898,
        "Question": "6.\tThe power of a wave having an electric field strength of 12.8 units is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0.217",
            "b)\t0.721",
            "c)\t0.127",
            "d)\t0.172"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The power of a wave is given by P = 0.5 E2/η, where E is the electric field intensity and η is the intrinsic impedance. On substituting for E = 12.8 and η = 377, we get P = 0.5 x 12.82/377 = 0.217 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 899,
        "Question": "7.\tThe form or mode of propagation is determined by which factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tType of excitation device",
            "b)\tLocation of excitation device",
            "c)\tType and location of the excitation device",
            "d)\tWaveguide characteristics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The form and the mode of propagation of the wave in a waveguide is determined by the type and location of the excitation device."
    },
    {
        "id": 900,
        "Question": "8.\tThe phase of the wave after the installation of the guided terminations will be",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t45",
            "c)\t90",
            "d)\t180"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Using a guided termination, the guides serves as a reflector. If the distance between the exciter and the wall is properly adjusted, the transmitted and the reflected wave will be in phase."
    },
    {
        "id": 901,
        "Question": "9.\tThe exciter of the waveguide in a transmission line is the",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTransmitter",
            "b)\tReceiver",
            "c)\tTransponder",
            "d)\tAntenna"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The waveguide is usually excited by the antenna rod. The reflection depends on the phase of excitation and the antenna current."
    },
    {
        "id": 902,
        "Question": "10.\tA waveguide imitates which type of filter characteristics?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLow pass filter",
            "b)\tHigh pass filter",
            "c)\tBand pass filter",
            "d)\tBand reject filter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A waveguide passes only high frequency waves (in GHz range) and attenuates low frequencies. This is the characteristic of a high pass filter."
    },
    {
        "id": 903,
        "Question": "The tangential component of an electric field will be continuous in which boundary?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conductor-Conductor",
            "b) Conductor-Dielectric",
            "c) Dielectric-Dielectric",
            "d) Any boundary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The tangential component of an electric field will be continuous in any type of boundary."
    },
    {
        "id": 904,
        "Question": "The depth of penetration of a wave in a lossy dielectric increases with increasing",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conductivity",
            "b) Permeability",
            "c) Wavelength",
            "d) Permittivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The depth of penetration or skin depth is inversely proportional to the frequency. Thus it has to be directly proportional to the wavelength."
    },
    {
        "id": 905,
        "Question": "Magnetic vector potential is a vector",
        "Options": [
            "a) Whose curl is equal to the magnetic flux density",
            "b) Whose curl is equal to the electric field intensity",
            "c) Whose divergence is equal to electric potential",
            "d) Which is equal to the vector product E x H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The magnetic vector potential is A. The curl of A is a vector and it is equal to the magnetic flux density. It is given by Curl(A) = B."
    },
    {
        "id": 906,
        "Question": "For the wave equation E = 10sin (wt-5z)ax, the wave propagation will be in the direction of",
        "Options": [
            "a) Y direction",
            "b) Z direction",
            "c) X direction",
            "d) XY direction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The equation represents the electric field component of the wave. Here, ax represents the electric wave direction and z represents the wave direction."
    },
    {
        "id": 907,
        "Question": "An electric field on a plane is described by its potential V = 20(r-1 + r-2), where r is the distance from the source. The field is due to",
        "Options": [
            "a) A monopole",
            "b) A dipole",
            "c) Both a monopole and a dipole",
            "d) A quadruple"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the potential given, one component is inversely proportional to r, which is due to a monopole and the other component is inversely proportional to r2, which is due to a dipole."
    },
    {
        "id": 908,
        "Question": "The electric field strength at a far-off point P due to a point charge, +q located at the origin O is 100 milliVolt/meter. The point charge is now enclosed by a perfectly conducting hollow metal sphere with its centre and the origin O. The electric field strength at the point, P is",
        "Options": [
            "a) Remains unchanged in its magnitude and direction",
            "b) Remains unchanged in its magnitude but reverse in direction",
            "c) Would be that due to a dipole formed by the charge, +q, at O and -q induced",
            "d) Would be zero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: According to Gauss Law, the total displacement or electric flux through any closed surface surrounding charges is equal to the amount of charge enclosed. The total enclosed charge is -q + q = 0. Thus the flux and electric field strength will be zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 909,
        "Question": "The electric field of a uniform plane electromagnetic wve in free space, along the positive direction, is given by E = 10(ay + jaz)e-j25x. The frequency and polarization of the wave, respectively are",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.2 GHz, left circular",
            "b) 4 GHz, left circular",
            "c) 1.2 GHz, right circular",
            "d) 4 GHz, right circular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The amplitudes of the components are the same. Hence it is circular polarization. The phase difference is +90 degree. Thus it is left hand circular polarisation. The frequency f = c/wavelength = 3 x 108 x 25/2 x 3.14 = 1.2 GHz."
    },
    {
        "id": 910,
        "Question": "Identify which one of the following will NOT satisfy the wave equation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50ej(wt – 3z)",
            "b) sin(w(10z + 5t))",
            "c) cos(y2 + 5t)",
            "d) sin x cos t"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  c\nExplanation: The wave cos(y2 + 5t) does not satisfy the general wave equation. Thus it is not an electromagnetic wave."
    },
    {
        "id": 911,
        "Question": "The intrinsic impedance of copper at high frequencies is",
        "Options": [
            "a) Purely resistive",
            "b) Purely inductive",
            "c) Complex with a capacitive component",
            "d) Complex with a inductive component"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The intrinsic impedance is given by √(jwµ√ϭ + jw€). Since copper is a good conductor, ϭ << jw€, thus the intrinsic impedance will have +j component only. This refers to complex with an inductive component."
    },
    {
        "id": 912,
        "Question": "A loop is rotating about the y axis in a magnetic field B = Bocos(wt + α)at. The voltage in the loop is",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero",
            "b) Due to rotation only",
            "c) Due to transformer action only",
            "d) Due to both rotation and transformer action"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The voltage in the loop is due to two reactions – time varying magnetic field and voltage induced in a loop moving with velocity v in steady magnetic field. Thus the voltage in the loop is due to both rotation and transformer action."
    },
    {
        "id": 913,
        "Question": "Copper behaves as a",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conductor always",
            "b) Conductor or dielectric depending on the applied electric field strength",
            "c) Conductor or dielectric depending on the frequency",
            "d) Conductor or dielectric depending on the electric current density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The loss tangent for copper is very large due to its high conductivity. This shows that the copper behaves as a conductor in all conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 914,
        "Question": "In a good conductor the phase relation between the tangential components of electric E and the magnetic field H is as follows",
        "Options": [
            "a) E and H are in phase",
            "b) E and H are out of phase",
            "c) H leads E by 90",
            "d) E leads H by 45"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In a conductor, the intrinsic impedance gives the phase relation between E and H. For a conductor, the electric field and magnetic field are in 45 degree phase difference. E and H are 45 leading."
    },
    {
        "id": 915,
        "Question": "For an electromagnetic wave incident from one medium to a second medium, total internal reflection takes place when",
        "Options": [
            "a) Angle of incidence is equal to the Brewster angle with E field perpendicular to the plane of incidence",
            "b) Angle of incidence is equal to the Brewster angle with E field parallel to the plane of incidence",
            "c) Angle of incidence is equal to the critical angle with the wave moving from the denser to rarer medium",
            "d) Angle of incidence is equal to the critical angle with the wave moving from the rarer to denser medium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Total internal reflection takes place when the angle of incidence is greater than the critical angle. Also the wave should move from the denser medium to a rarer medium."
    },
    {
        "id": 916,
        "Question": "For maximum power transfer, a lossless transmission line 50 ohm is to be matched to a resistive load impedance of 100 ohm. The characteristic impedance of the wavelength/4 transformer is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 70.7",
            "b) 50",
            "c) 100",
            "d) Infinity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For maximum power transfer, Zin = Z02/ZL. On substituting for the given values, we get the characteristic impedance as 70.7 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 917,
        "Question": "In an impedance Smith chart , a clockwise movement along a constant resistance circle gives rise to",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrease in reactance",
            "b) Increase in reactance",
            "c) No change in reactance",
            "d) No change in impedance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In clockwise direction, along the constant resistance circle gives rise to an increase in the value of reactance."
    },
    {
        "id": 918,
        "Question": "A transmission line is distortionless if",
        "Options": [
            "a) RL = 1/GC",
            "b) RL = GC",
            "c) LG = RC",
            "d) RG = LC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Condition for distortionless line is R/L = G/C. In other words, the rise time constant is equal to the fall time constant. Hence RC = LG."
    },
    {
        "id": 919,
        "Question": "A lossless line having 50 ohm characteristic impedance and length wavelength/4 is short circuited at one end connected to an ideal voltage source of 1V at the other end. The current drawn from the voltage sources is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 0.02",
            "c) Infinity",
            "d) 50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a quarter wave transformer, the input impedance is given by Zin = Z02/ZL. The load impedance will be zero in case of short circuit. Thus the input impedance will be infinite. The current drawn is I = V/ZL = 1/∞ = 0."
    },
    {
        "id": 920,
        "Question": "The capacitance per unit length and the characteristic impedance of a lossless transmission line are C and Z respectively. The velocity of a travelling wave on the transmission line is",
        "Options": [
            "a) ZC",
            "b) 1/ZC",
            "c) Z/C",
            "d) C/Z"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The characteristic impedance of the Z = √(L/C) and the velocity of propagation is V = 1/√(LC). Thus we get V = 1/ZC."
    },
    {
        "id": 921,
        "Question": "The minimum distance of the stub from the load side is 5 cm. Calculate the guided wavelength of the transmission line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 cm",
            "b) 2.5 cm",
            "c) 10 cm",
            "d) 1.25 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The minimum distance of the stub from the load line is given by Vmin = wavelength/2. On substituting the given value, we get the guided wavelength as 10 cm."
    },
    {
        "id": 922,
        "Question": "One end of a lossless transmission line having the characteristic impedance of 75 ohm and length of 1 cm is short circuited. At 3 GHz, the input impedance at the other end of the transmission line is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) Resistive",
            "c) Inductive",
            "d) Capacitive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The input impedance is given by ZIN = j Zo tan 2pi l/wavelength. For short circuited line, ZL = 0. On substituting the given values we get the input impedance as j54.49 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 923,
        "Question": "In the design of a single mode step index optical fiber close to upper cut off, the single mode operation is NOT preserved if",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radius as well as operating wavelength are halved",
            "b) Radius as well as operating wavelength are doubled",
            "c) Radius is halved and operating wavelength is doubled",
            "d) Radius is doubled and operating wavelength is halved"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cut off frequency is given by f = 2πa sin α/wavelength, where a is the radius of core. For a single mode step index fiber, f must lie between 0 and 2.405. Thus to get f below 2.405, the radius must be doubled and wavelength must be halved."
    },
    {
        "id": 924,
        "Question": "Which parameters cannot be computed from the Smith chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Impedance",
            "b) Admittance",
            "c) Reflection coefficient and VSWR",
            "d) Intrinsic impedance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: From the Smith chart, the parameters impedance, admittance, reflection coefficient and VSWR can be computed directly. The intrinsic impedance cannot be calculated."
    },
    {
        "id": 925,
        "Question": "Consider a transmission line of characteristic impedance 50 ohm. Let it be terminated at one end by +j50 ohm. The VSWR produced by it in the transmission line will be",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 0",
            "c) Infinity",
            "d) +j"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The reflection coefficient is given by R = j50 – 50/j50 + 50 = j – 1/j + 1. Thus the reflection coefficient is given by 1. The VSWR = 1 + R/1 – R = 2/0 = infinity."
    },
    {
        "id": 926,
        "Question": "A transmission line whose characteristic impedance is a pure resistance",
        "Options": [
            "a) Must be a lossless line",
            "b) Must be a distortionless line",
            "c) May not be a lossless line",
            "d) May be a lossless and may not be a distortionless line"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When the characteristic line is a pure resistance, the line must be a distortionless line. But it may not be a lossless line."
    },
    {
        "id": 927,
        "Question": "A two wire transmission line of characteristic impedance Z is connected to a load impedance ZL(ZL and Zo are not equal). Impedance matching cannot be achieved with",
        "Options": [
            "a) A quarter wavelength transformer",
            "b) A half wavelength transformer",
            "c) An open circuited parallel stub",
            "d) A short circuited parallel stub"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the characteristic and load impedance are not same, a half wavelength transformer cannot be used for impedance matching because when l = wavelength/2, we get Zin = ZL."
    },
    {
        "id": 928,
        "Question": "A transmission line of pure resistance characteristic impedance is terminated with an unknown load. The measured value of VSWR on the line is 2 and a voltage minimum point is found to be at the load. The load impedance is then",
        "Options": [
            "a) Complex",
            "b) Purely capacitive",
            "c) Purely resistive",
            "d) Purely inductive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Given, voltage minimum point is at load. If minimum voltage or maximum voltage occurs at the load for a lossless transmission line then the load impedance is purely resistive."
    },
    {
        "id": 929,
        "Question": "Which one of the following field patterns represents a TEM wave travelling in the positive x direction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) E = +8y, H = -4z",
            "b) E = -2y, H = -3z",
            "c) E = +2z, H = +2y",
            "d) E = -3y, H = +4z"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: To get wave travelling in the positive direction, the E component has to be in negative y direction and the H component has to be in negative z direction. Thus E = -2y and H = -3z is the right option."
    },
    {
        "id": 930,
        "Question": "The modes in a rectangular waveguide are denoted by TEmn / TMmn, where m and n are the Eigen values along the larger and smaller dimensions of the waveguide respectively. Which one of the following statements is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The TM10 mode does not exist",
            "b) The TE10 mode does not exist",
            "c) The TE10 and TM10 both exist and have same cut off frequencies",
            "d) When m and n are increases, the cut off frequency decreases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For TM mode, TM00, TM10, TM01 does not exist. For TE mode, TE00 does not exist but TE10 and TE01 exists."
    },
    {
        "id": 931,
        "Question": "In a microwave test bench, why is the microwave signal amplitude modulated at 1 kHz?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To increase the sensitivity of measurement",
            "b) To transmit the signal to a far off place",
            "c) To study amplitude modulation",
            "d) Because crystal detector fails at microwave frequencies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since crystal detector fails at microwave frequencies, microwave signal amplitude is modulated at 1kHz."
    },
    {
        "id": 932,
        "Question": "Consider a lossless antenna with a directive gain of +6 decibel. If 1 milliwatt of power is fed to it, the total power radiated by the antenna will be (in milliwatt)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 7",
            "d) 1/4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For a lossless antenna, the input power and the radiated power will be same. The efficiency will be 100%. Thus the radiated power will also be 1 milliwatt.  "
    }
]